<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-09T12:00:40-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Crypto Business Models and Libra</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190708/crypto-business-models.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crypto Business Models and Libra" /><published>2019-07-08T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-08T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190708/crypto-business-models</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190708/crypto-business-models.html">&lt;p&gt;Fred Wilson recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://avc.com/2019/07/business-model-innovation/&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about how Crypto’s promise is not just in the technical but the business model innovation that comes alongside it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an analogy that comes to mind - gaming and virtual currencies. In-app purchases and subscriptions are often mapped to coins, passes, candy and other currencies that can be redeemed in an app. Once they have been translated into these virtual currencies, we can similarly innovate on different business models that might work best in a specific scenario. For example, we can use the subscription API to give users coins every month (instead of simple access), and then use those coins to purchase content or pay other users in an app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This full capability (especially that to pay users with coins) isn’t yet possible with the In-app purchase API’s provided by Apple and Google. But ultimately, the behaviours that have a lot of traction will then get adopted into those platform API’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of Facebook - the world’s largest social network - as a game, the Libra cryptocurrency is their virtual good. Difference being that they’re not the only ones controlling it. It has value pegged to real currency, can be used to trade goods and services, and can be traded in for other currencies on different exchanges. More so, when another app uses Libra, it creates network effect for that currency and the utility value increases for users of Libra. Already, Uber, Ebay, Lyft, Spotify and others have joined. More mature games have multiple currencies running in parallel, much in the same way there are hundreds of possible cryptocurrencies to purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lot’s of hurdles still to cross, but it’s an incredibly interesting time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Fred Wilson recently wrote about how Crypto’s promise is not just in the technical but the business model innovation that comes alongside it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Kawhi</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190706/kawhi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Kawhi" /><published>2019-07-06T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-06T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190706/kawhi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190706/kawhi.html">&lt;p&gt;What a difference a day makes. Just like that, Kawhi is no longer a Raptor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His sober get-it-done demeanor was the most &lt;em&gt;Canadian&lt;/em&gt; way to win a championship. It’s appropriate that Toronto is having the most &lt;em&gt;Canadian&lt;/em&gt; possible response: we’re upset, but we’re not angry. He wanted to go home. You can’t be mad at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether or not the backroom stories are true, it really tells of the power of the right phone call. In this case, it was Kawhi’s to Durant and then Paul George.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asking for what you want is an underappreciated skill in life and business. What sets apart the winners is often they’re just a bit more clear about what they want, and aren’t afraid to ask for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What a difference a day makes. Just like that, Kawhi is no longer a Raptor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Microlearning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190704/microlearning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Microlearning" /><published>2019-07-04T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-04T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190704/microlearning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190704/microlearning.html">&lt;p&gt;Learning happens in small increments - bits of knowledge that collectively stitch together to form mental models of understanding. So it’s only natural that online learning services minify and break up content into consumable chunks. Mobile amplifies this - shorter attention spans come with being able to consume any content on the go - we fit those moments into the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept can be extended pretty far - potentially doing away with the concept of fixed courses altogether to a more fluid learning structure. Using Microlearning structures we can eventually unbundle a college degree - although more likely is that it will  helps for the construction of more specialized degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software for learning will continue to become more adaptive to how humans learn - and microlearning is a big part of that trend for educationalists tech.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Learning happens in small increments - bits of knowledge that collectively stitch together to form mental models of understanding. So it’s only natural that online learning services minify and break up content into consumable chunks. Mobile amplifies this - shorter attention spans come with being able to consume any content on the go - we fit those moments into the day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kawhi Watch</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190703/kawhiwatch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kawhi Watch" /><published>2019-07-03T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-03T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190703/kawhiwatch</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190703/kawhiwatch.html">&lt;p&gt;The world was on #KawhiWatch today. I was getting multiple messages full of rumours and hearsay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s pretty insane to see this happening. No athlete in recent memory has gotten this type of attention. It’s incredible to be a witness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice should be  clear. Toronto objectively is a better city for Kawhi. The  chance to defend the championship, a highly competent organization at all level, and cap space to offer upto a 5 year max. That said, we probably need to chill a little bit :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The world was on #KawhiWatch today. I was getting multiple messages full of rumours and hearsay.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Boring Technology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190702/boring-technology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boring Technology" /><published>2019-07-02T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-02T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190702/boring-technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190702/boring-technology.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked in tech long enough to see a familiar game play out many times: engineers want to use the latest and greatest technology, often overlooking the maintenance cost of new tech. At the same time, they look down on ‘old technology’ as inferior, when the opposite is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan McKinley has a great presentation on this topic aptly titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://boringtechnology.club/&quot;&gt;Boring Technology&lt;/a&gt;. Check it out; its a great read and nails the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve worked in tech long enough to see a familiar game play out many times: engineers want to use the latest and greatest technology, often overlooking the maintenance cost of new tech. At the same time, they look down on ‘old technology’ as inferior, when the opposite is true.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Free Agency</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190701/secrets.markdoown" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free Agency" /><published>2019-07-01T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-01T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190701/secrets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190701/secrets.markdoown">The first day of NBA free agency has been a whirlwind. Some massive trades by Brooklyn - with KD and Kyrie although Durant's injury almost guarantees we won't see this play out until 2020/2021. 

The most WTF trade of the day was the  announcement Golden State and Brooklyn  agreed on a sign-and-trade, sending D’Angelo Russell to the Warriors on a four-year, $117M maximum contract. 🤔

Obviously we're still waiting for the Fun Guy to make his decision. Unsurprisingly, he clearly knows how to keep a secret.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The first day of NBA free agency has been a whirlwind. Some massive trades by Brooklyn - with KD and Kyrie although Durant's injury almost guarantees we won't see this play out until 2020/2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Learning Styles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190701/learning-styles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Learning Styles" /><published>2019-07-01T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-01T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190701/learning-styles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190701/learning-styles.html">&lt;p&gt;Had a really great conversation today about how learning styles greatly affect comprehension. This would indicate instructors should cater their courses to every individual. So if someone is a visual learner we should look for a way to visually represent our lessons to them. Except this isn’t always true and most importantly doesn’t always lead to better outcomes. I read a &lt;a href=&quot;https://career.ucsf.edu/sites/career.ucsf.edu/files/Article%20UCSF%20SEJC%20January%202017.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; on this topic which concludes the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Theories of learning styles suggest that individuals think and learn best in different ways. These are not differences of ability but rather preferences for processing certain types of information or for processing information in certain types of way. If accurate, learning styles theories could have important implications for instruction because student achievement would be a product of the interaction of instruction and the student’s style. There is reason to think that people view learning styles theories as broadly accurate, but, in fact, scientific support for these theories is lacking. We suggest that educators’ time and energy are better spent on other theories that might aid instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientific American &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-problem-with-learning-styles/&quot;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; something similar, that while people understand they have different learning styles, they don’t behave rationally in picking the right learning strategy. From the article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Despite knowing their own, self-reported learning preferences, nearly 70% of students failed to employ study techniques that supported those preferences. Most visual learners did not rely heavily on visual strategies (e.g., diagrams, graphics), nor did most reading/writing learners rely predominantly on reading strategies (e.g., review of notes or textbook), and so on. Given the prevailing belief that learning styles matter, and the fact many students blame poor academic performance on the lack of a match between their learning style and teachers’ instructional methods, one might expect students to rely on techniques that support their personal learning preferences when working on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some more resources on the topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://buildingrti.utexas.org/resource-pages/learning-styles-neuromyth-debunked&quot;&gt;Learning Styles: Neuromyth Debunked&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5366351/&quot;&gt;Evidence-Based Higher Education – Is the Learning Styles ‘Myth’ Important?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Had a really great conversation today about how learning styles greatly affect comprehension. This would indicate instructors should cater their courses to every individual. So if someone is a visual learner we should look for a way to visually represent our lessons to them. Except this isn’t always true and most importantly doesn’t always lead to better outcomes. I read a paper on this topic which concludes the following:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Waves</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190626/waves.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waves" /><published>2019-06-26T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-26T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190626/waves</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190626/waves.html">&lt;p&gt;A product or company’s success is dependent on the waves it’s riding. These waves can be broad market trends, shifts in behaviour or the success of other products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, mobile app companies rode the wave of broad global smartphone adoption. Similarly, instability in the public markets increases adoption of Bitcoin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s nice to think success is always fully earned, the truth is in understanding the broader system. It’s often the larger waves that influence a company’s success more than anything else.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A product or company’s success is dependent on the waves it’s riding. These waves can be broad market trends, shifts in behaviour or the success of other products.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Printing Your Brain on Paper</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190625/printing-your-brain-on-paper.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Printing Your Brain on Paper" /><published>2019-06-25T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-25T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190625/printing-your-brain-on-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190625/printing-your-brain-on-paper.html">&lt;p&gt;Mindmapping is the act of articulating a thought pattern onto paper (or screen). Great clarity emerges from visualizing how thoughts connect. It becomes a systems diagram for thought - showing how one thought triggers another in a chain reaction. When I feel stuck on a decision, it’s often because that chain reaction creates a cyclical pattern I keep traversing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision mindmaps look like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Directed_acyclic_graph&quot;&gt;directed acyclical graph&lt;/a&gt;. Each node represents an Action or State, and each arrow represents a specific path of consequence (which then leads to another action or state).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of decisions, a node would be something like “Work at Company X” or “Ship Feature Y”. Connector arrows lead to other states. Obviously a state can also include emotional states like ‘satisfaction’, or ‘regret’. This can both increase self awareness and decision-making quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connecting them on paper gives me &lt;em&gt;control&lt;/em&gt; - it removes me from the thought, gives me a guide to navigate it, which then results in a more sound decision. Charlie Munger’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/2013/04/munger-two-step/&quot;&gt;approach to decision making&lt;/a&gt; is a two step process - first understand the forces at play, and then the psychological factors that might be leading you astray. A mindmap is a great way to understand both.s&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Mindmapping is the act of articulating a thought pattern onto paper (or screen). Great clarity emerges from visualizing how thoughts connect. It becomes a systems diagram for thought - showing how one thought triggers another in a chain reaction. When I feel stuck on a decision, it’s often because that chain reaction creates a cyclical pattern I keep traversing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">When They See Us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190624/when-they-see-us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When They See Us" /><published>2019-06-24T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-24T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190624/when-they-see-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190624/when-they-see-us.html">&lt;p&gt;Ava DuVernay’s latest work is a 4 part series on Netflix about the Central Park 5. It goes into detail about their experience - on the night of the event, throughout unfair incarceration, and assimilation back into normal society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will grip you, make your blood boil, and make you cry. It is important storytelling. Check it out on Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ava DuVernay’s latest work is a 4 part series on Netflix about the Central Park 5. It goes into detail about their experience - on the night of the event, throughout unfair incarceration, and assimilation back into normal society.</summary></entry></feed>