<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-26T15:25:38-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Getting Closer to Software, Again</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190926/getting-closer-to-software.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Closer to Software, Again" /><published>2019-09-26T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-26T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190926/getting-closer-to-software</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190926/getting-closer-to-software.html">&lt;p&gt;Amazon announced it’s echo buds recently, creating a low priced Airpods competitor tied to the Alexa ecosystem. The relatively low pricepoint ($130) can skyrocket adoption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago I wrote about how we are &lt;a href=&quot;/20190129/closer-software.html&quot;&gt;getting closer to software&lt;/a&gt;. While Echobuds aren’t novel, it’s just another development in bringing software closer to our physical selves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also happened to talk to a student from &lt;a href=&quot;https://theksociety.com/&quot;&gt;The Knowledge Society&lt;/a&gt;, an incubator for some brilliant high school students - who was investigating the world of 3D printed organs, gene editing and CRISPR. This is how software is eating the world from the inside out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technologists love to extrapolate potential, but mass adoption is often a multi-decade sport. But at the same time, our future already exists in today’s science fiction. It’s wild to think about our world in twenty or thirty years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Amazon announced it’s echo buds recently, creating a low priced Airpods competitor tied to the Alexa ecosystem. The relatively low pricepoint ($130) can skyrocket adoption.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Thoughts on Social Finance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190925/social-finance.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Thoughts on Social Finance" /><published>2019-09-25T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-25T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190925/social-finance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190925/social-finance.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday Anish Acharya published this post entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/09/24/how-fintech-startups-find-users/&quot;&gt;Five Ways Fintech Companies can find Customers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the tactics he mentioned was activating social networks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Social networks have been largely underutilized in fintech thus far. But existing social bonds can be a powerful tool used to encourage saving and extend credit—ROSCAs are an age-old (offline) example. Looking ahead, a16z general partner Connie Chan recently wrote about the use of WhatsApp and WeChat groups in China to facilitate product experiences in travel, shopping, fitness, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two layers to social finance. One leans on the dynamics in which money moves between people. This encompasses everything from peer to peer transfers to shared savings pools (the ROSCAs referred to above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is simply adding a social layer on top of the current financial services, that encourages people to be more open about matters of money. This includes safe spaces to ask others about money (Reddit’s finance forums, for example - although I wouldn’t broadly classify Reddit as a safe space), but also things like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetcleo.com/&quot;&gt;cheeky financial advice chat bots&lt;/a&gt; that are fun to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our relationships with money are complicated, and many seek social validation to make sure they’re on the right track. For most, being a part of the right pack is exactly what they need. Financial advisors provide this ability but there’s so much more room for experimentation here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Yesterday Anish Acharya published this post entitled Five Ways Fintech Companies can find Customers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Zone To Win</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190924/zone-to-win.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zone To Win" /><published>2019-09-24T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-24T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190924/zone-to-win</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190924/zone-to-win.html">&lt;p&gt;Geoffrey Moore, author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crossing_the_Chasm&quot;&gt;Crossing the Chasm&lt;/a&gt;, was in Toronto today giving a talk about his new book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zonetowin.com/&quot;&gt;Zone to Win&lt;/a&gt;. It details a framework for how established enterprises can compete amongst the threat of disruptive innovations. In it, he details 4 “zones” of work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Performance Zone, where the key metric is to make the number. It consists of the sales organizations accountable for bookings and the product and service organizations accountable for revenue—and no one else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Productivity Zone, where success means delivering efficient systems and effective programs while ensuring all operations are regulatory compliant. Virtually everyone who is not directly accountable for a booking or revenue number works here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Incubation Zone, where the objective is to make, market, and sell products and services that are highly disruptive to the status quo. These efforts are deliberately kept sequestered from the prior two zones to speed cycle time, embrace innovation, and take risk. Success here consists of creating viable businesses in net new uncorrelated categories that can be scaled to material size.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Transformation Zone, where success equates either to driving an incubated business to material scale or fending off a direct attack on a core business model. In either case an initiative in this zone takes priority over all activities in the other three zones, and they must make whatever adjustments necessary to accommodate it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first 3 are fairly well understood. “Performance” and “Productivity” are relevant to sustaining innovation - either extracting maximum value from a market, or for enabling functions. The Incubation zone efforts are the lab-type efforts that exist in almost every enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to say that big companies can’t innovate isn’t really true. Most big companies work well in Zone 1 and 2. They also invest in Zone 3, to address the disruptive forces themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his presentation, he highlighted cases from 56 companies that were once market leaders, all had innovation labs, but never were able to counter the disruptive forces working against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reason, in all those organizations, was the lack of a “transformation” zone type effort. In this zone, companies move into &lt;em&gt;war time&lt;/em&gt; mode to ensure that the successful incubated projects are actualized into the rest of the company. Most companies fail at this - even successful incubated projects either struggle to integrate with the rest of the organization / product line. In this zone, everyone in the organization needs to be &lt;em&gt;focused&lt;/em&gt; on making this transformation successful, which can sometimes mean sacrificing short term revenue targets for revenue growth potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few examples are Apple’s focus on the iPod (when the Mac was making it the most money), and Microsoft’s recent shift to cloud computing (so dramatic that there’s no longer a Windows division in the company).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Geoffrey Moore, author of Crossing the Chasm, was in Toronto today giving a talk about his new book, Zone to Win. It details a framework for how established enterprises can compete amongst the threat of disruptive innovations. In it, he details 4 “zones” of work:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Greta Thunberg</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190923/greta.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greta Thunberg" /><published>2019-09-23T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-23T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190923/greta</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190923/greta.html">&lt;p&gt;Greta Thunberg is a 16 year old climate activist, and is currently one of the most powerful forces in the fight against the climate crisis. She is speaking at the United Nations today and just gave an absolutely moving speech. Highlights on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/i/events/1176168425762127873&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People are suffering, people are dying, entire ecosystems are collapsing. We are in the beginning of a mass extinction and all you can talk about is money and fairy tales of eternal economic growth. &lt;em&gt;How dare you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Greta Thunberg is a 16 year old climate activist, and is currently one of the most powerful forces in the fight against the climate crisis. She is speaking at the United Nations today and just gave an absolutely moving speech. Highlights on Twitter here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Cycles We’re Stuck Inside</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190922/the-cycles-we-are-in.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cycles We're Stuck Inside" /><published>2019-09-22T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-22T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190922/the-cycles-we-are-in</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190922/the-cycles-we-are-in.html">&lt;p&gt;I was listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/09/05/hustlers-guide-getting-paid-early-ontime-hustlin-tech/&quot;&gt;The Hustler’s Guide to Gettin’ Paid&lt;/a&gt;, and the CEO of Earnin was talking about how a alarming 40% of American’s don’t have access to $400 if they needed it for an unexpected expense. Banks with excessive fees and loan providers with excessive interest are making this problem so much worse. Earnin provides a no-fee service that gives people access to capital as soon as they work, so they don’t have to wait until the biweekly Friday pay-cycle. The notion of a ‘payday’ means that companies are withholding access to money so that &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; can put it to work versus the people it’s owed to. It’s great that Earnin is trying to fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made me think about some of the cycles that modern society is seemingly stuck in. Some that are top of mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The daily 9-5 cycle, created as a by-product of the industrial revolution but no longer relevant in a knowledge economy. Within this is also the daily commute cycle, a 2-3 hour block of lost productivity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cycle of higher education as the only path to unlock success&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cycle of reactive, symptom-focused care perpetuated by the modern medical industry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some are norms that have been perfected for years for us to inherit. But, the internet has given us infrastructure to pass information and value in real time, so it’s time to apply first-principles thinking and think of the best solutions to these problems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I was listening to The Hustler’s Guide to Gettin’ Paid, and the CEO of Earnin was talking about how a alarming 40% of American’s don’t have access to $400 if they needed it for an unexpected expense. Banks with excessive fees and loan providers with excessive interest are making this problem so much worse. Earnin provides a no-fee service that gives people access to capital as soon as they work, so they don’t have to wait until the biweekly Friday pay-cycle. The notion of a ‘payday’ means that companies are withholding access to money so that they can put it to work versus the people it’s owed to. It’s great that Earnin is trying to fix the problem.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Notes on the Bill Gates Documentary</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190921/bill-gates.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Notes on the Bill Gates Documentary" /><published>2019-09-21T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-21T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190921/bill-gates</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190921/bill-gates.html">&lt;p&gt;The Bill Gates documentary series was released on Netflix on Friday. It’s a behind-the-scenes look at Bill’s life - focusing on his work at the Bill and Melinda Gates foundation, but also covers his childhood, his work at Microsoft, reading habits and much more. It’s pretty fascinating, and I will probably watch it a few times. This is a post of a few things I took away from the documentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bill Gates is a first principles thinker.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When designing the next generation &lt;em&gt;toilet&lt;/em&gt;, he approaches the problem with a few unchangable restrictions. In this case, it’s the current conditions of the places where these toilets are needed the most - especially the lack of electricity and running water. The foundation ran a contest to encourage innovation around a toilet that doesn’t require running water, access to electricity, and where the byproduct can be re-used instead of being dumped into rivers and lakes. These next generation toilets are being produced and deployed around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bill Gates uses mental models for everything.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Melinda Gates says it best - “[Bill] makes a framework in his mind, and then starts slotting in the information. If something doesn’t line up, he gets very frustrated.” He uses frameworks to understand complex topics and then devours as much information as he can to complete that model. Mental models create simple structures to understand the real world, which are essential to linking the facts together. I’m guessing that’s why he’s most often the smartest guy in the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many other learnings - on the habits he’s formed to devour and retain information, his sense of competition, and also the incredible privelege that allowed for him to explore his interests throughout his life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Bill Gates documentary series was released on Netflix on Friday. It’s a behind-the-scenes look at Bill’s life - focusing on his work at the Bill and Melinda Gates foundation, but also covers his childhood, his work at Microsoft, reading habits and much more. It’s pretty fascinating, and I will probably watch it a few times. This is a post of a few things I took away from the documentary.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Notes on The Passive Investing Bubble</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190920/passive-investing-bubble.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Notes on The Passive Investing Bubble" /><published>2019-09-20T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-20T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190920/passive-investing-bubble</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190920/passive-investing-bubble.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve read a few articles recently about the bubble in passive investing. It started with Michael Burry declaring that index investing is a bubble similar to the collateralized debt obligations (CDO’s) that brought down the global economy in 2007. The simple premise is that ETF’s mostly invest in larger companies, and small cap stocks are being thereby being “neglected”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As money pours into exchange-traded funds and other index-tracking products that skew toward big companies, Burry says smaller value stocks are being unduly neglected around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben Hunt from &lt;a href=&quot;www.epsilontheory.com&quot;&gt;Epsilon Theory&lt;/a&gt; points out the bias in that statement in his article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epsilontheory.com/ive-got-a-secret/&quot;&gt;I’ve Got a Secret&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Burry – like every small cap value investor since the dawn of time – is saying that the market doesn’t appreciate the information &lt;strong&gt;he’s&lt;/strong&gt; uncovered about his small cap value stocks, and that there are structural reasons why the market doesn’t appreciate that information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to say the bubble is in the prevailing “always be buying” mentality that surrounds passive investment strategies. That strategy states - passive investing always beats active investing, that stocks always goes up in the long term, buying and holding for the long term without picking individual stocks is your best bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is true &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;, it may not &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; be true. Passive investment is not a way to shortcut independent thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is different about today’s stock market that didn’t really exist even 10 years ago is the volume of investment information and commentary (thanks to Twitter), and the ease of participating in the market (thanks to so many fintechs). At a macro level the narrative makes sense: that the contrarian path is to move away from passive vehicles, because everyone already knows that’s the best form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wealthfront also recently published the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.wealthfront.com/the-myth-of-the-passive-investing-bubble/&quot;&gt;Myth of the Passive Investment Bubble&lt;/a&gt;, and referenced an &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.wealthfront.com/indexing-worse-than-marxism/&quot;&gt;earlier article&lt;/a&gt; from 2016, which states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To be sure, index investors are free riders.  They do receive the benefits that result from active trading without bearing the costs.  But free riding on price signals provided by others is hardly a flaw of the capitalist system; it is an essential feature of that system.  In a free-market economy we all benefit from relying on a set of market prices that are determined by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve read a few articles recently about the bubble in passive investing. It started with Michael Burry declaring that index investing is a bubble similar to the collateralized debt obligations (CDO’s) that brought down the global economy in 2007. The simple premise is that ETF’s mostly invest in larger companies, and small cap stocks are being thereby being “neglected”:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Question Quality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190919/question-quality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Question Quality" /><published>2019-09-19T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-19T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190919/question-quality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190919/question-quality.html">&lt;p&gt;Question &lt;em&gt;quality&lt;/em&gt; is a good signal to measure progress whenever learning something new. As we begin to understand something more - whether it’s a new language, skill or domain - the questions we ask about the unknowns in that domain become more specific and in most senses, better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found this especially true when learning code. Initially, I start trying to solve problems by asking general questions like “why doesn’t this button do this thing that I want it to?”. It’s difficult to find answers to questions like that, and often leads to dead ends. When that’s happening enough, that’s a great signal that maybe I don’t understand the &lt;em&gt;basics&lt;/em&gt; of a specific domain as well as I should. Often this happens because of an incomplete glossary or understanding of the larger system in which my code is operating. When I develop that, my questions become more precise, stack traces become more understandable, and answers become easier to find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this learning ability is relevant to code, it applies in almost very domain, and I often end up assessing my question quality as a measure of how well I understand something.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Question quality is a good signal to measure progress whenever learning something new. As we begin to understand something more - whether it’s a new language, skill or domain - the questions we ask about the unknowns in that domain become more specific and in most senses, better.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">History of the Credit Card</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190918/history-of-the-credit-card.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="History of the Credit Card" /><published>2019-09-18T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-18T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190918/history-of-the-credit-card</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190918/history-of-the-credit-card.html">&lt;p&gt;Alex Rampell of A16Z recently published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/arampell/status/1174359694950842368&quot;&gt;thread&lt;/a&gt; about the history of the credit card, focusing on Bank of America’s card that was mailed to 60,000 residents of Fresno.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Diners club and American Express started before this (for meals, travel and entertainment), this was the first example of a revolving line of credit, with a card supported by all types of merchants. Mailing it to customers without any “approval” process was a genius way to jumpstart usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bank of America also published an article with video on how everything got started; check it out &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.bankofamerica.com/en-us/our-story/birth-of-modern-credit-card.html#fbid=9T0dAH1X58G&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Alex Rampell of A16Z recently published a thread about the history of the credit card, focusing on Bank of America’s card that was mailed to 60,000 residents of Fresno.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Adding an Email Newsletter</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190917/email-newsletter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Adding an Email Newsletter" /><published>2019-09-17T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-17T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190917/email-newsletter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190917/email-newsletter.html">&lt;p&gt;Based on a few requests I just added an email newsletter to this blog, thanks to the now decade old service (but still relevant!) &lt;a href=&quot;www.feedburner.com&quot;&gt;Feedburner&lt;/a&gt;. This is something I’ve been putting off for a while, and finally got to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/subscribe.png&quot; alt=&quot;Email newsletter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested, subscribe to get regular updates in your inbox. Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@davideiaiunese/the-problem-why-a-newsletter-baae4409a526&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; for detailed instructions on how to add a Feedburner newsletter to a Jekyll Blog.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Based on a few requests I just added an email newsletter to this blog, thanks to the now decade old service (but still relevant!) Feedburner. This is something I’ve been putting off for a while, and finally got to it.</summary></entry></feed>