<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-05T22:59:52-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Getting Paid</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200304/getting-paid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Paid" /><published>2020-03-04T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-04T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200304/getting-paid</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200304/getting-paid.html">&lt;p&gt;Compensation is a sensitive topic. We think about it often but don’t discuss it openly. This informaton asymmetry creates silos where a few people are in “the know”, and many others are seemingly left out. Often because they’re not asking the right questions, don’t know who to ask, or simply - are not sure how to start the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had one of these conversations recently, and I offered some advice to a friend. This post summarizes some of my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do your homework. Understand comparables and what is fair for your industry and level, and set your own expectations accordingly. Make sure you are equipped with this prior.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Own the conversation, don’t wait for it or let it happen to you. Compensation conversations often happen too late so it’s best to bring up your expectations earlier in your job search.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are no “deals”. I’ve found the best compensation conversations end with a feeling that this is the beginning of a strong partnership, versus one side feeling they got the better or worse end of a deal.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use an intermediary if it makes you more comfortable. Using a recruiter has the advantage of avoiding direct confrontation. I’ve found this to be useful, but also see a lot of value in directness.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Undertstand that there’s so much more than base. Negotiate along multiple lines - base, upside and downside. You want a base with a good savings rate buffer,  to maximize your upside, and to minimize any downside risks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make sure your base covers living comfortably, with a good buffer for savings. My target was 60-70% of my base should cover my living expenses - including mortgages / nannies etc. The rest would go into savings. I think in a world where pensions are not the norm, a 30-40% savings rate should be considered “normal”. Life circumstances become a good negotiation lever - it’s hard to push back on. New houses, kids, parents to support, all that helps.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maximize your upside (equity, bonuses etc) - make sure you’re able to participate in the long term success of the company. In startupworld, equity is the name of the game but I think we’ll soon see different forms of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/l/long_term_incentive-plan.asp&quot;&gt;long term equity compensation&lt;/a&gt;. Long term bonus and equity are more difficult than any other category to negotiate when you’re in the job, so doing this upfront is important. You can negotiate the “option to reevaluate” any part of this if the company doesn’t have formal performance planning and associated compensation adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Minimuze your downside - Make sure you have severance included. This is your only time to negotiate your severance package. It can be an uncomfortable discussion but they expect it to happen but never bring it up. You have to do this yourself, and it’s a good signal. It’s standard to ask for at least 9-12 months.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be adding to this as more thoughts arise on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Compensation is a sensitive topic. We think about it often but don’t discuss it openly. This informaton asymmetry creates silos where a few people are in “the know”, and many others are seemingly left out. Often because they’re not asking the right questions, don’t know who to ask, or simply - are not sure how to start the conversation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Upfront Summit</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200303/upfront-summit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Upfront Summit" /><published>2020-03-03T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-03T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200303/upfront-summit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200303/upfront-summit.html">&lt;p&gt;Fred Wilson and Albert Wenger were interviewed by Erin Griffith at the Upfront Summit. It’s a great conversation about the climate crisis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3Dx_z_t8mrs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Fred Wilson and Albert Wenger were interviewed by Erin Griffith at the Upfront Summit. It’s a great conversation about the climate crisis:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Fear</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200302/on-fear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Fear" /><published>2020-03-02T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-02T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200302/on-fear</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200302/on-fear.html">&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus has spread into our conversations faster than the virus itself. Markets are spooked and grocery lineups are getting longer. The virus is here, and as we ramp up detection we’ll find out how prevalant it is (and perhaps has been for weeks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fear will start in communities globally based on the news of the virus. But it will likely subside while the virus continues to spread globally and becomes another part of our everyday life. The fear and the virus will spread independent of each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is already a clear economic impact, but not all effects will be negative. I’m thinking particularly about the dramatic drop in air pollution, and dramatic rise of remote working policies. COVID-19 might be the moment we pause and re-evaluate how we’re going about our lives - and make the right changes in response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Coronavirus has spread into our conversations faster than the virus itself. Markets are spooked and grocery lineups are getting longer. The virus is here, and as we ramp up detection we’ll find out how prevalant it is (and perhaps has been for weeks).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LED Walls</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200301/some-thoughts-on-media.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LED Walls" /><published>2020-03-01T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-01T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200301/some-thoughts-on-media</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200301/some-thoughts-on-media.html">&lt;p&gt;Some info on LED wall technology:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I recently heard about LED wall technology through &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cabel/status/1234160439660953601&quot;&gt;this Twitter thread&lt;/a&gt;, about The upcoming Bourne Stuntacular at Universal uses a giant LED wall as background, and it’s synchronized perfectly with stunt actors and props in the foreground. The result is a cinema quality production that’s playing out in front of viewers eyes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is also the same way that Star Wars Mandalorian was shot. ILM recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gUnxzVOs3rk&quot;&gt;showcased&lt;/a&gt; how dramatically this changed the production process. Unreal Engine also showcased LED walls in use in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bErPsq5kPzE&quot;&gt;this Youtube video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The impact of LED wall technology has the potential to make complex production techniques more accessible. This will dramatically impact the financial structure of big budget filmmaking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Some info on LED wall technology:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Financial Instrumenting</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200229/securitization-of-everything.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Financial Instrumenting" /><published>2020-02-29T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-02-29T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200229/securitization-of-everything</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200229/securitization-of-everything.html">&lt;p&gt;Some notes on the broader trend of turning more assets into financial instrument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any asset that has increasing value over time is being packaged as a financial instrument, to allow for more people to participate in that value increase. This is happening in traditional categories like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.withotis.com/&quot;&gt;art&lt;/a&gt;, but also with &lt;a href=&quot;https://edly.info/&quot;&gt;new students entering the workforce&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exercise is not different from securitization, in which different forms of contractual debt is repackaged as bonds or CDO’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trend feels like something that can only occur in a booming market cycle, when investors are looking for new opportunities to generate wealth. This seems to be coming to an end. I’m not spelling doom and gloom for these new innovative ‘asset classes’ - I think investors will generally skew towards fewer abstractions and increased certainty.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Some notes on the broader trend of turning more assets into financial instrument:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on ‘Debt is Coming’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200228/debt-is-coming.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on 'Debt is Coming'" /><published>2020-02-28T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-02-28T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200228/debt-is-coming</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200228/debt-is-coming.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alexdanco.com/2020/02/07/debt-is-coming/&quot;&gt;Alex Danco’s article&lt;/a&gt; on debt from a few weeks ago made a lot of rounds. I’ve finally read it and I’m using this post as a way of summarizing some notes on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post starts by exploring the relationship between financial capital, or FK (money used for investments like equity) and production capital, or PK (money used for producing real goods and services).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There’s a recurring dynamic of how FK and PK perceive each other and work with one another. Jerry Neumann’s explanation is good: “My long-ago operations research textbook had a cartoon showing one MBA talking to another: ‘Things? I didn’t come here to learn how to make things, I came here to learn how to make money.’ This is the view of financial capital. The view of production capital is exemplified by Peter Drucker: ‘Securities analysts believe that companies make money. Companies make shoes.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FK is deployed into companies that use it for PK. In early stage of any technology where potential is unknown, venture capital is the prevailing model to follow here. A small number of those deployed bets will produce outsized returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The new technology is exciting, and the market opportunities are large but unknown. Speculative investment, with ambitious but inexact expectations of financial return, is important fuel for founders who build the unknown future. However, investors and operators are often deeply misaligned: investors think in bets, while operators think in consequences. The relationship is tense, but can be explosively productive. The VC model is an institutional expression of this tension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When technology is widely adopted and then becomes a part of everyday fabric of society, it becomes easier to predict how that technology will be adopted. Therefore, FK can be deployed with an more predictable outcome. VC is not the appropriate model here - but &lt;em&gt;venture debt&lt;/em&gt; definitely is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The overall bet may still be speculative, but the median VC dollar isn’t anymore. It’s buying customer acquisition and then financing service delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This change will start to occur in areas where technology has entered the “deployment phase” - i.e. mobile. And for founders building those companies, they should consider more options for financing other than VC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you’re a tech founder raising capital today, there’s really one mainstream way to fund it: by selling equity. The VC model capital stack, which the Silicon Valley venture ecosystem has optimized itself around, is the one-size-fits-all funding model for startups of all shapes and sizes. We know it like muscle memory at this point. If your career began after the dot com crash, as mine and I’m sure many of yours did, you’ve probably never known any other way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Alex Danco’s article on debt from a few weeks ago made a lot of rounds. I’ve finally read it and I’m using this post as a way of summarizing some notes on the topic.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Conversations and Products</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200227/what-people-talk-about.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Conversations and Products" /><published>2020-02-27T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-02-27T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200227/what-people-talk-about</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200227/what-people-talk-about.html">&lt;p&gt;A great source of product ideas comes from daily conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too often, products are built around &lt;em&gt;perceived&lt;/em&gt; problems. Conversations contain unfiltered signal that helps us understand people’s &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too often, products are built with a “if we build it, they will come” mentality (despite best intentions of the opposite). Understanding how people recommend products helps build distribution mechanics into a product itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User research should always strive towards getting signal that is as close to those daily conversations as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A great source of product ideas comes from daily conversations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Thoughts on Marketplaces</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200226/some-thoughts-on-marketplaces.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Thoughts on Marketplaces" /><published>2020-02-26T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-02-26T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200226/some-thoughts-on-marketplaces</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200226/some-thoughts-on-marketplaces.html">&lt;p&gt;Some disconnected thoughts on marketplaces:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Online marketplaces create demand by bringing previously scarce or untapped supply and making it easily accessible. Focusing on supply is the tried and tested formula for growing marketplaces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once bootstrapped, online marketplaces aggregate demand (users) and allow for suppliers of all types find new business. In this sense, an online marketplace is an MVP for a supplier (driver, merchant, etc) to test whether there is a market for their business. Once that is done, it likely serves them better to own the customer relationship directly. This is to avoid overreliance of their business on any one platform.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some marketplaces are resilient to individual suppliers leaving, and are easily substituted. Those are often more transactional and where there is no strong connection between the two sides (i.e. a rider doesn’t really care who their driver is).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some marketplaces are very sensitive to suppliers leaving, and can respond to this by enabling paths for suppliers to be successful both on and off platform.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marketplaces can think of themselves as ad networks for influential suppliers, providing better targeting for them and greater reach on platform (and potentially off platform too). This has the double benefit of serving as a source of additional revenue for the marketplace.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To protect their marketplace, becoming a platform for other businesses to reach their suppliers can create an additional moat for the business. It becomes a one-stop shop for creators, and in addition creates another source of network effects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Some disconnected thoughts on marketplaces:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Right Questions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200225/customer-interview-questions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Right Questions" /><published>2020-02-25T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-02-25T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200225/customer-interview-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200225/customer-interview-questions.html">&lt;p&gt;Question quality is a good proxy for how well you really understand something. This applies for every discipline, but especially for building products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early stages, product discovery often starts with questions for your customer about their attitudes about something. In bad research, the questions are too pointed, even though they might not seem to be on the surface. In good research, the questions invite potential customers to tell a story about themselves. These stories often lead to the ground truth around customer attitudes, and ultimately, their behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.producttalk.org/2016/03/customer-interview-questions&quot;&gt;Teresa Torres&lt;/a&gt; really sums it up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I recently asked a woman what factors she considered when buying a new pair of jeans. She didn’t hesitate in her answer. She said, “Fit is my number one factor.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;That seems reasonable. It’s hard to find a pair of jeans that fit well.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I then asked her to tell me about the last time she bought a pair of jeans. She said, “I bought them on Amazon.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I laughed and asked, “How did you know if they fit?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;She said, “I didn’t, but they were a brand I liked and they were on sale.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a huge difference between what people say and what people do. Good research should always try to get towards the latter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Question quality is a good proxy for how well you really understand something. This applies for every discipline, but especially for building products.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Range</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200223/range.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Range" /><published>2020-02-23T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-02-23T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200223/range</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200223/range.html">&lt;p&gt;A very short post today. I started readiing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Range-Generalists-Triumph-Specialized-World/dp/0735214484&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/a&gt; last night, and enjoyed this last paragraph from the introduction. The reference is to the approach taken by Tiger Woods versus Roger Federer. The former specialized in golf since he demonstrated a childhood aptitude for the sport, and the latter dabbled in skiing, wrestling, swimming, skateboarding - all while he played tennis. Both became the best in the world at their sports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The challenge we all face is how to maintain the benefits of breadth, diverse experience, interdisciplinary thinking, and delayed concentration in a world that increasingly incentivizes, even demands, hyperspecialization. While it is undoubtedly thrue that there are areas that require individuals with Tiger [Woods]’ precocity and clarity of purpose, as complexity increases - as technology spins the world into vaster webs of interconnected systems in which each individual only sees a small part - we also need more Roger [Federers]: people who start broad and ebrace diverse experiences while they progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A very short post today. I started readiing Range last night, and enjoyed this last paragraph from the introduction. The reference is to the approach taken by Tiger Woods versus Roger Federer. The former specialized in golf since he demonstrated a childhood aptitude for the sport, and the latter dabbled in skiing, wrestling, swimming, skateboarding - all while he played tennis. Both became the best in the world at their sports.</summary></entry></feed>