<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-07T00:12:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">On Urgency</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190605/urgency.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Urgency" /><published>2019-06-05T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-05T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190605/urgency</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190605/urgency.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s 11:50 pm. That gives me 10 minutes to write and publish a post that I haven’t even conceived yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for some reason, I’m not worried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10 minutes is also 600 seconds, a unit shift that adds a different perspective. Some funny math starts to happen - If the fastest person in the world can run 100 meters in less than 10 seconds, in 600 seconds they can run 6000 meters. Obviously this isn’t true, but the perspective, however flawed, creates abundance from scarcity. This triggers a peace of mind and creates space for focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mental tricks alone aren’t enough. A fast approaching deadline is another type of boundary in which creativity can flourish. A boundary that can be manufactured consistently by, well, procrastinating. This is a familiar place - I subconsciously wait for times like this to &lt;em&gt;force&lt;/em&gt; creative output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be amazing if I could maintain this pace of output throughout the day. But for now…time’s up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It’s 11:50 pm. That gives me 10 minutes to write and publish a post that I haven’t even conceived yet.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Game 3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190604/game-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Game 3" /><published>2019-06-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190604/game-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190604/game-3.html"></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Best Product: A Great Team</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190602/the-best-product.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Best Product: A Great Team" /><published>2019-06-02T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-02T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190602/the-best-product</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190602/the-best-product.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently came across this &lt;a href=&quot;http://blas.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/The-Best-Product-A-Great-Team.pdf&quot;&gt;excellent essay&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;www.blas.com&quot;&gt;Blas Moros&lt;/a&gt; about the principles that guide great teams. It’s a summary of the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/31aYRdA&quot;&gt;The Dream Machine&lt;/a&gt;, which details the stories and people from the days of ARPA and PARC. Specifically, how their leaders JCR Licklider and Bob Taylor created environments of consistent innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These principles are below but the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blas.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/The-Best-Product-A-Great-Team.pdf&quot;&gt;essay&lt;/a&gt; is worth the read many times over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Getting the air right - creating and fostering the right environment, the right culture.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Attracting, retaining, and inspiring the best people, and then giving them the freedom and autonomy to run&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Providing a grand vision which get people to go all-in&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Creating a self-sustaining and self-organizinggroup that can prosper even when the leader steps away.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Invert! Always Invert - As important as what to do is what &lt;em&gt;not to do&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently came across this excellent essay by Blas Moros about the principles that guide great teams. It’s a summary of the book The Dream Machine, which details the stories and people from the days of ARPA and PARC. Specifically, how their leaders JCR Licklider and Bob Taylor created environments of consistent innovation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Where Good Ideas Come From</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190601/ideas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where Good Ideas Come From" /><published>2019-06-01T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-01T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190601/ideas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190601/ideas.html">&lt;p&gt;Erik Torenberg published a pretty epic twitter thread about how to think of markets and business ideas (albeit from a VC perspective- which has its own specific lean).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check it out &lt;a href=&quot;https://mobile.twitter.com/eriktorenberg/status/1135272936657416192&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/amp/s/25iq.com/2015/02/21/a-dozen-things-ive-learned-from-don-valentine-about-venture-capital-and-business/amp/&quot;&gt;Some more notes&lt;/a&gt; on this topic from Tren Griffin.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Erik Torenberg published a pretty epic twitter thread about how to think of markets and business ideas (albeit from a VC perspective- which has its own specific lean).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Game 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190530/nba-finals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Game 1" /><published>2019-05-30T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-30T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190530/nba-finals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190530/nba-finals.html">&lt;p&gt;Toronto and Canada hosts its first NBA finals today. The first time the Canadian National anthem will be played during the finals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s so much energy in the city. Sports does such a great job to set aside differences and bring people together. Toronto is already a friendly city but it feels like we’re really banding together to celebrate this, and to recognize our own greatness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an amazing vibe. I can’t wait.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Toronto and Canada hosts its first NBA finals today. The first time the Canadian National anthem will be played during the finals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Strangely Breaking Habits</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190527/strangely-breaking-habits.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Strangely Breaking Habits" /><published>2019-05-27T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-27T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190527/strangely-breaking-habits</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190527/strangely-breaking-habits.html">&lt;p&gt;My writing habit is breaking down in a very strange way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last few weeks I’ve found myself fall into a familiar pattern - skip writing for a few days (or only write a few notes in a draft), and make up for it by writing 3-4 blog posts in one day. I’m not a fan of this intermittence, but also am happy that I’m keeping pace with a single blog post per day &lt;em&gt;on average&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day after writing 3 or 4 posts, I’m tapped out. So I take a break, and the cycle perpetuates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure exactly how to reposition the habit so it can happen more regularly. Mornings are tough because those are my deep work sessions that I like to use. One way I’ve seen it work is when I can complete a post right before I leave work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, I’m not sure how this habit will regularize itself again - but one thing is clear - writing everyday at EOD isn’t working that well. I’m hoping to get this fixed soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My writing habit is breaking down in a very strange way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Disparate Thoughts on Product Management</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190527/some-disconnected-thoughts-on-product.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Disparate Thoughts on Product Management" /><published>2019-05-27T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-27T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190527/some-disconnected-thoughts-on-product</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190527/some-disconnected-thoughts-on-product.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve had some great conversations recently about product management. This post is a collection of those [highly disparate] notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Shaping Products&lt;/strong&gt;: Iconic products have a &lt;em&gt;shape&lt;/em&gt;. Instagram, Twitter and Facebook are known for their unique takes on the feed. Tinder is about swiping. Messenger apps all have a very specific structure. Products shape around a core and adjacent user problem. To understand the shape your product should take, it’s critical to understand those problems and resulting customer funnel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Major Releases&lt;/strong&gt;: Making large changes to a product in market is filled with anxiety and excitement. The former because large changes are necessary, but their success or failure is hard to pinpoint to one specific improvement. Many use this argument to focus on small incremental changes over time. I’m not dogmatic about either approach - but writing off one approach is a fools errand. There is a time and place for large releases. When it’s overapplied, it becomes an easy target. But without it, a startup can end up spinning wheels towards local maximums.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Decision Confidence&lt;/strong&gt;: Much has been written about decisionmaking frameworks. One I like to use often is the decision confidence rule - if you have 80% of information to make a decision, it’s time to make the call. Any more work will be diminishing returns. I find so many product managers scared to use their own earned instinct. This signals a lack of confidence in their own decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve had some great conversations recently about product management. This post is a collection of those [highly disparate] notes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning Systems in a Company</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190526/managing-learning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning Systems in a Company" /><published>2019-05-26T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-26T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190526/managing-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190526/managing-learning.html">&lt;p&gt;This post is an unstructured set of notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve become interested in understanding how the best companies think about managing the learning infrastructures in their organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How employees are given learning opportunities for personal growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How teams are provided the tools to continuously learn and get better&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How the feedback loops from markets help a team evolve a product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That last point is arguably just the domain of product management. For the first two - I’m not sure if there’s an obvious market leader. Learning Management Systems aren’t new, but they seem like an overly heavy solution. Since learning is so individually driven, there feels like there’s space in a market for an LMS with a Slack-like distribution model - driven by employees but ultimately paid for by the company.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This post is an unstructured set of notes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Diversity and Building Software</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190524/tech-society-diversity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diversity and Building Software" /><published>2019-05-24T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-24T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190524/tech-society-diversity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190524/tech-society-diversity.html">&lt;p&gt;I was having a conversation recently about diversity, which quickly turned into one about responsible technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two prevailing ways I think about this, and I wanted to clarify them in a post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First - software is a strange beast. It has a disproportionate impact across the world than any other industry. The global impact of software requires that the teams building it are considerate to the needs of more types of cultures, races, genders, and other segments. It’s not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; the right thing to do - it’s the smart and profitable thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second - building a company, especially a software company - and ultra especially a successful one - requires you to take a broader look at your company’s role in society. You are building a system that empowers your employees to create massive impact. If that opportunity was only provided to a priveleged few, you are only building a system to perpetuate the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two perspectives have helped me understand the importance of diversity and inclusion especially for a technology startup today.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I was having a conversation recently about diversity, which quickly turned into one about responsible technology.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Not Us?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190523/why-not-us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Not Us?" /><published>2019-05-23T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-23T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190523/why-not-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190523/why-not-us.html">&lt;p&gt;The Toronto Raptors made the NBA finals for the first time in it’s 25 year history, defeating the Milwaukee Bucks 100-94 in Game 6 of the Eastern Conference Finals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s very little else on my mind. But more than the game, it’s this question. Why &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not Toronto? Why not the Raptors? Why do we carry a collective impostor syndrome that tells us - we’re good, but not &lt;em&gt;good enough&lt;/em&gt; for that ultimate title. It can feel undeserved; unattainable. It’s also bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not us? There’s no reason. It’s time to get our mental stigmas out of our own way - and show the world what we’re capable of. Let’s go, Raptors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Toronto Raptors made the NBA finals for the first time in it’s 25 year history, defeating the Milwaukee Bucks 100-94 in Game 6 of the Eastern Conference Finals.</summary></entry></feed>