<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-28T11:32:49-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Printing Your Brain on Paper</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190625/printing-your-brain-on-paper.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Printing Your Brain on Paper" /><published>2019-06-25T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-25T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190625/printing-your-brain-on-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190625/printing-your-brain-on-paper.html">&lt;p&gt;Mindmapping is the act of articulating a thought pattern onto paper (or screen). Great clarity emerges from visualizing how thoughts connect. It becomes a systems diagram for thought - showing how one thought triggers another in a chain reaction. When I feel stuck on a decision, it’s often because that chain reaction creates a cyclical pattern I keep traversing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision mindmaps look like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Directed_acyclic_graph&quot;&gt;directed acyclical graph&lt;/a&gt;. Each node represents an Action or State, and each arrow represents a specific path of consequence (which then leads to another action or state).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of decisions, a node would be something like “Work at Company X” or “Ship Feature Y”. Connector arrows lead to other states. Obviously a state can also include emotional states like ‘satisfaction’, or ‘regret’. This can both increase self awareness and decision-making quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connecting them on paper gives me &lt;em&gt;control&lt;/em&gt; - it removes me from the thought, gives me a guide to navigate it, which then results in a more sound decision. Charlie Munger’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/2013/04/munger-two-step/&quot;&gt;approach to decision making&lt;/a&gt; is a two step process - first understand the forces at play, and then the psychological factors that might be leading you astray. A mindmap is a great way to understand both.s&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Mindmapping is the act of articulating a thought pattern onto paper (or screen). Great clarity emerges from visualizing how thoughts connect. It becomes a systems diagram for thought - showing how one thought triggers another in a chain reaction. When I feel stuck on a decision, it’s often because that chain reaction creates a cyclical pattern I keep traversing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">When They See Us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190624/when-they-see-us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When They See Us" /><published>2019-06-24T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-24T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190624/when-they-see-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190624/when-they-see-us.html">&lt;p&gt;Ava DuVernay’s latest work is a 4 part series on Netflix about the Central Park 5. It goes into detail about their experience - on the night of the event, throughout unfair incarceration, and assimilation back into normal society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will grip you, make your blood boil, and make you cry. It is important storytelling. Check it out on Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ava DuVernay’s latest work is a 4 part series on Netflix about the Central Park 5. It goes into detail about their experience - on the night of the event, throughout unfair incarceration, and assimilation back into normal society.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190623/one.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One" /><published>2019-06-23T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-23T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190623/one</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190623/one.html">&lt;p&gt;They turned one today; I’m so happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cl.ly/e388b73e182e/Image%202019-06-26%20at%2011.50.07%20PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;One&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">They turned one today; I’m so happy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Systems, Hallucination &amp;amp; Vision, and Making vs. Selling Art</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190622/hallucination-vision.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Systems, Hallucination &amp; Vision, and Making vs. Selling Art" /><published>2019-06-22T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-22T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190622/hallucination-vision</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190622/hallucination-vision.html">&lt;p&gt;This is easily a classic conversation. Brian Koppelman (of Rounders, Billions fame) sat down with Marc Andressen to talk about selling creativity, systems thinking, and so much more. So amazing. &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/03/12/hallucination-vision-scenius-networks-selling-using-making-art-brian-koppelman-marc-andreessen/&quot;&gt;Read here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Brian: But I guess what I’m asking is, how do you learn to — Do you think one can learn to do both things? To be a creator, founder/creator, and the salesman of your own work? Like, how does one learn to do that?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Marc: Yes. Well, so first of all… put it this way — this is, again, where I think systems thinking is actually helpful — ao, actually, we have a lot of this, so we have a lot of sort of founders who are like classical engineers, and they’re sort of classical introverts and the idea of having to go, kind of, you know, sell is like anathema, like, the idea. You know, they’ve got these kind of, I would say, misperceptions of the salesman as somebody who’s wearing a shiny suit &amp;lt;Brian: Yes, perfect!&amp;gt; selling somebody something that they don’t need.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And so, we have a couple of responses to that. We have a specific response to that, which is actually the role of sales is (at least in our industry) is not to sell something you don’t need — it’s actually to help somebody buy what they actually do need. And we can have a long conversation about that. The really good sales people in Silicon Valley who make a lot of money become very personally bonded to their customers; they end up going to their customers’, you know, weddings, to their kids’ weddings — like, they become like, very close allies to the careers of their customers. We can have a long conversation about that. It’s a real form of value-add to the customer.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But even deeper than that. The thing I tell the engineers is, look, dealing with customers, it’s another systems problem. Like, you are the master of solving a systems problem, which is how to get the computer to do what you want. Like, people aren’t computers, they’re different, but there is a system for dealing people. You can engineer a system for dealing with people. And actually, when you work with top-end sales people, what you find is they have incredibly elaborate, like, very real systems. Like, very, very, very thought-through kind of abstract systems of how they basically run like, a large-scale sales campaign and how they deal with the customer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is easily a classic conversation. Brian Koppelman (of Rounders, Billions fame) sat down with Marc Andressen to talk about selling creativity, systems thinking, and so much more. So amazing. Read here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Risk</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190621/risk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Risk" /><published>2019-06-21T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-21T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190621/risk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190621/risk.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been faced with some decisions recently that have tested my risk tolerance. Almost serendipitously I was catching up on The Knowledge Project, in particular &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/howard-marks/&quot;&gt;this episode&lt;/a&gt; featuring Howard Marks of Oaktree Capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some notes from this conversation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Outperformance: By definition this requires contrarian thinking. Getting ahead &lt;em&gt;by definition&lt;/em&gt; means you’re working either smarter or harder than everyone else. Working harder isn’t en vogue these days. And while Nothing is really deterministic but ultimately working hard is a predictor of success more than it isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two paragraphs from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/howard-marks/&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt; really hit home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To be an out-performer, you have to think different from the crowd. But most of the time, the crowd is about as close to being right as you can get. Ergo, the problem. So, to be an above average investor, number one you have to think different from the crowd. But number two, you have to be right. So, second-level thinking is thinking which is different and better.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The question is not, do you dare to be great? The question is, do you dare to be different? To diverge from the pack is required if you’re going to be a superior in anything. Number two, do you dare to be wrong? Number three, do you dare to look wrong? Because even things which are going to be right in the long run, maybe look wrong in the short run. So, you have to be willing to live with all those three things, different, wrong, and looking wrong, in order to be able to take the risk required and engage in the idiosyncratic behavior required for success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been faced with some decisions recently that have tested my risk tolerance. Almost serendipitously I was catching up on The Knowledge Project, in particular this episode featuring Howard Marks of Oaktree Capital.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Slack’s IPO</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190620/slack-ipo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Slack's IPO" /><published>2019-06-20T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-20T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190620/slack-ipo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190620/slack-ipo.html">&lt;p&gt;Slack IPO’d today and I was looking through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sec.report/Document/0001628280-19-004786/&quot;&gt;S-1&lt;/a&gt; they filed a few months prior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack gets a lot of love from the tech press, and &lt;a href=&quot;/20180923/slack-product-network-ecosystem.html&quot;&gt;I’m a fan&lt;/a&gt; of the product. I was taken aback at the scale of their loss and particularly the sales and marketing costs. Slack is upheld as the champion of bottoms up organic growth in the enterprise, but the numbers tell a slightly different story. Obviously an outsiders perspective but pretty interesting. Still gonna buy; too much FOMO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the risks section of their S-1:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have incurred significant net losses in each year since our inception, including net losses of $146.9 million, $140.1 million, and $138.9 million in fiscal years 2017, 2018, and 2019, respectively. We expect to continue to incur net losses for the foreseeable future and we may not achieve or maintain profitability in the future. Because the market for Slack, and the features, integrations, and capabilities we offer on Slack, is rapidly evolving and has not yet reached widespread adoption, it is difficult for us to predict our future results of operations or the limits of our market opportunity. &lt;strong&gt;We expect our operating expenses to significantly increase over the next several years as we hire additional personnel, particularly in sales and marketing&lt;/strong&gt;, expand our partnerships, operations, and infrastructure, both domestically and internationally, continue to enhance Slack and develop and expand its features, integrations and capabilities, and expand and improve our application programming interfaces, or APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Slack IPO’d today and I was looking through the S-1 they filed a few months prior.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Early Thoughts on Libra</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190619/libra.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Early Thoughts on Libra" /><published>2019-06-19T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-19T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190619/libra</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190619/libra.html">&lt;p&gt;Libra is a massive new initiative to deliver on the promise of the ‘internet of money’ using Blockchain technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Libra’s mission is to enable a simple global currency and financial infrastructure that empowers billions of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In simpler terms, Libra is a stable, fiat backed cryptocurrency that will launch inside some of the world’s largest consumer-facing applications (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usv.com/blog/why-usv-is-joining-the-libra-association&quot;&gt;USV&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot to take in with Libra but it’s pretty clear that the backing of the biggest consumer app in the world will jumpstart crypto adoption. The ability to send and receive money as quickly as we transfer data will unlock and create new opportunities. Being backed by a reserve gives it the necessary stability to build trust with developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, there’s a ton of challenge - trust itself being one. Facebook isn’t exactly known to be the most trusted organization but they are only a single member of the governing body. There are many questions around regulations. The government has already cracked down and asked Facebook to stop development on Libra, and the SEC has an investigation underway with Kik and it’s Kin cryptocurrency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to seeing this evolve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Libra is a massive new initiative to deliver on the promise of the ‘internet of money’ using Blockchain technology.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Futureland</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190618/futureland-alpha.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Futureland" /><published>2019-06-18T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-18T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190618/futureland-alpha</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190618/futureland-alpha.html">&lt;p&gt;Futureland is a community of creative self learners, each one committed to a daily practice of publishing something new everyday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen Futureland since it’s early days and it’s a really special corner of the Internet. It’s also an incredible learning technique. This blog is an example of one of these projects that started with a commitment to daily writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://internetvin.com/futureland-alpha/&quot;&gt;Futureland: Alpha&lt;/a&gt; and check the &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20220112&quot;&gt;discussion on HN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Futureland is a community of creative self learners, each one committed to a daily practice of publishing something new everyday.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fifth Discipline</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190617/revisiting-the-fifth-discipline.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fifth Discipline" /><published>2019-06-17T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-17T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190617/revisiting-the-fifth-discipline</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190617/revisiting-the-fifth-discipline.html">&lt;p&gt;The Fifth Discipline is one of my favorite leadership books. I’ll be coordinating a discussion on the book tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some disconnected notes on the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A learning organization is committed to self betterment and adaptiveness to change. This makes it naturally resillient and likely to last longer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A shared vision is developed together. Magic happens when you can connect someone’s personal vision to one that the company needs. It creates a natural flow that is impossible to do if leadership is inflexible about the vision. People who do not share the same vision might not contribute as much to the organization.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Systems thinking helps to connect everything together. I’ve used this in the past in the development of the leadership lattice - a framework of how companies work that highlights how everything is connected to each other.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Team Learning is a form of flow. When a team is focused on the same things and is consistently readjusting itself through instrospection and intelligent dialogue, it can create powerful business results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal mastery requires some level of introspection, but cannot be forced. It must be led by example and through creating environments of psychological safety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Fifth Discipline is one of my favorite leadership books. I’ll be coordinating a discussion on the book tomorrow.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Score Takes Care of Itself</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190616/the-score-takes-care-of-itself.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Score Takes Care of Itself" /><published>2019-06-16T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-16T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190616/the-score-takes-care-of-itself</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190616/the-score-takes-care-of-itself.html">&lt;p&gt;Recently read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sachinrekhi.com/bill-walsh-the-score-takes-care-of-itself&quot;&gt;What Silicon Valley Can Learn From Bill Walsh’s The Score Takes Care of Itself&lt;/a&gt;. Lots of great takeaways, for example this one on OKR’s and goalsetting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But what Bill Walsh correctly points out is that the ultimate outcome metric that you are so focused on in your OKRs is not in-fact in your control. Many of the inputs to that outcome are in your control. But certainly not the outcome itself. And so what Bill is saying is that an over-fixation on that outcome metric actually doesn’t help you get there. You should instead focus on the part that you can control. And when you do this well, the score (the ultimate outcome metric you care about) takes care of itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This illustrates Bill Walsh’s style to focus on the inputs (what you can directly control) vs. outputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you start to put these elements of Bill’s leadership style together, you start to see how it differs from the conventional wisdom. Bill encourages you to focus on the inputs and the process instead of the ultimate outcomes as the outcomes are not in your control. Bill expects leaders to be functional experts in the roles on their team in order to develop the Standard of Performance. These leaders are not just people managers. They are the very best at what they do. And they develop a powerful system, via the Standard of Performance and a passion for teaching, of inculcating their team to make them the very best at their roles. But unlike the benevolent dictator model, Bill certainly doesn’t encourage you to call all the shots yourself. But instead to build up the team and the team culture to be able to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Recently read What Silicon Valley Can Learn From Bill Walsh’s The Score Takes Care of Itself. Lots of great takeaways, for example this one on OKR’s and goalsetting:</summary></entry></feed>