<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-11-27T22:50:25-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Technology and Truth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191127/lux-capital-technology-truth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technology and Truth" /><published>2019-11-27T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-27T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191127/lux-capital-technology-truth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191127/lux-capital-technology-truth.html">&lt;p&gt;An really cool video made by Lux Capital at their annual dinner - all about technology as an arbiter of truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hvEPUasRBRg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An really cool video made by Lux Capital at their annual dinner - all about technology as an arbiter of truth.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NYSE Direct Listings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191126/nyse-direct-listings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NYSE Direct Listings" /><published>2019-11-26T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-26T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191126/nyse-direct-listings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191126/nyse-direct-listings.html">&lt;p&gt;The New York Stock Exchange &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2019/11/26/nyse-proposes-big-change-to-direct-listings/&quot;&gt;recently filed paperwork&lt;/a&gt; to make direct listings a reality. A lot has been talked about regarding direct listings, especially recently with tech IPO’s not turning out as planned. Direct listings allow companies to create a secondary market of existing shares (held by employees, advisors, insiders) available directly to the public. This allows companies to avoid the archaic process of going to banks, but more importantly lets the market decide the price via auction (vs. bankers). Letting the market decide also makes a lot of sense especially for companies that are more well known to individual investors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The New York Stock Exchange recently filed paperwork to make direct listings a reality. A lot has been talked about regarding direct listings, especially recently with tech IPO’s not turning out as planned. Direct listings allow companies to create a secondary market of existing shares (held by employees, advisors, insiders) available directly to the public. This allows companies to avoid the archaic process of going to banks, but more importantly lets the market decide the price via auction (vs. bankers). Letting the market decide also makes a lot of sense especially for companies that are more well known to individual investors.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Growing Marketplaces - Part 3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191125/marketplaces-part-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Growing Marketplaces - Part 3" /><published>2019-11-25T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-25T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191125/marketplaces-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191125/marketplaces-part-3.html">&lt;p&gt;Part 32 of Lenny Rachitsky’s series on marketplace growth is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lennyrachitsky.com/p/how-to-kickstart-and-scale-a-marketplace-911&quot;&gt;now available&lt;/a&gt;. This one is about how many startups scaled initial supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overwhelming answer here is &lt;em&gt;direct sales&lt;/em&gt;. Nothing beats going door to door, building a pipeline and running a process to execute it. A classic strategy that works across industries, and way more effective than any other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the most significant learnings (and surprises) for me in doing this research was how important one-on-one direct sales was to most early marketplaces. Sales ended up being a crucial lever for about 60% of the companies I talked to — twice as common as the next biggest lever (piggy-backing and referrals).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other mechanisms are all common marketing levers - referrals, piggybacking on another network (often craigslist), word of mouth (strong dynamics in supply side, eg. restauraunts), subsidizing, paid growth, using employees as early supply, building single player mode, flywheels, SEO, events, and community based marketing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Part 32 of Lenny Rachitsky’s series on marketplace growth is now available. This one is about how many startups scaled initial supply.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Forcing Focus</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191124/end-of-year-forcing-focus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Forcing Focus" /><published>2019-11-24T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-24T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191124/end-of-year-forcing-focus</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191124/end-of-year-forcing-focus.html">&lt;p&gt;November is a funny time of year. It’s too early to start celebrating the holidays, but the end of year is in plain sight. If you’re working, you’re probably heading into a seasonably busy or very slow few weeks. Either way, it feels entirely &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; than the months before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many software companies, it’s the final push. The last few sprints before a code freeze. The last launch before we call it a year. Thinking and planning for 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best part of this year is that it forces focus. When you only have a few weeks left in a year, priorities become evident and things are quickly shelved for later. I love this mode of quick decision making, of quiet efficiency. This is how things should &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; be.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">November is a funny time of year. It’s too early to start celebrating the holidays, but the end of year is in plain sight. If you’re working, you’re probably heading into a seasonably busy or very slow few weeks. Either way, it feels entirely different than the months before.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Growing Marketplaces - Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191123/marketplaces-part-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Growing Marketplaces - Part 2" /><published>2019-11-23T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-23T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191123/marketplaces-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191123/marketplaces-part-2.html">&lt;p&gt;Part 2 of Lenny Rachitsky’s series on marketplace growth is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lennyrachitsky.com/p/how-to-kickstart-and-scale-a-marketplace-9ee&quot;&gt;now available&lt;/a&gt;. This one is focused on deciding which side of the marketplace to focus on (supply or demand).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key highlight is that 80% of the marketplaces he examined grew on the back of supply side growth. Whether it was Lyft, Eventbrite or Opentable, all of them focused on growing the catalog available to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a few exceptions. Rover and Taskrabbit didn’t have supply issues - primarily because supply was independent entreprenuers doing this stuff on the side. Basically anyone could walk a dog or do a taskrabbit - you don’t need to be licensed. Another one was Zillow - where supply was just public data - not actual listings - which they used to bootstrap demand which then allowed them to get real data. It was an interesting ‘bait and switch approach’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another highlight is Patreon, which thought of itself as a marketplace first but now has clarified that it isn’t one at all, and only serves creators in the same way Shopify serves entrepreneurs. It’s a shift in thinking that’s creating an entirely new category of software - one that A16Z dubs the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/10/08/passion-economy/&quot;&gt;passion economy&lt;/a&gt;’.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Part 2 of Lenny Rachitsky’s series on marketplace growth is now available. This one is focused on deciding which side of the marketplace to focus on (supply or demand).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cybertruck</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191122/cybertruck.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cybertruck" /><published>2019-11-22T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-22T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191122/cybertruck</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191122/cybertruck.html">&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk unveiled the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tesla.com/cybertruck&quot;&gt;Cybertruck&lt;/a&gt; yesterday and it looks like it’s straight out of Bladerunner. Let’s see if this design makes it past the National Transportation Safety Board and into production. It would be pretty incredible if it does, because it’s pretty stunning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Elon Musk unveiled the Cybertruck yesterday and it looks like it’s straight out of Bladerunner. Let’s see if this design makes it past the National Transportation Safety Board and into production. It would be pretty incredible if it does, because it’s pretty stunning.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Forces at Play and Base Rates</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191121/forces-at-play-base-rates.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Forces at Play and Base Rates" /><published>2019-11-21T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-21T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191121/forces-at-play-base-rates</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191121/forces-at-play-base-rates.html">&lt;p&gt;We all find ourselves in situations sometimes where there’s a high degree of uncertainty in our decisions. It often comes when starting something new or entering a new domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two exercises that reduce this uncertainty are understanding the &lt;strong&gt;forces at play&lt;/strong&gt; and determining &lt;strong&gt;base rates&lt;/strong&gt;. Understanding forces at play is about becoming familiar with the system in which you are operating, so that you may use it to your advantage. Determining a base rate is about looking at history to examine what success (and failure) has looked like in the past, so as to establish a benchmark for your own actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘forces at play’ comes from Charlie Munger’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/2013/04/munger-two-step/&quot;&gt;two step decision making process&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A simple and easy approach to decision making that prevents us from being manipulated:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Understand the forces at play.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Understand how your subconscious might be leading you astray.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that first step:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The key to the first step is knowing what you know and what you don’t know. You need to understand your circle of competence. It’s just as important to know what you don’t know as it is to know what you know.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;If you know what you don’t know, you might still have to make a decision, but your approaches for making that decision will change. For example, if you’re forced to make a decision in an area that you know is well outside your circle of competence, one tool you can use is inversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forcing ourselves to understand the world around us, especially the ‘unknowns’, will help us harness those forces towards whatever objective we are trying to reach. That second step - to understand our own biases - is another important step especially before making any decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘base rates’ comes from statistics. It represents the percentage of a population that exhibit a certain characteristic. It’s most basic use is determining the probability that a member of that population will also have that characteristic. For example, if 40% of immigrants in Canada are from India, then if you choose one immigrant in Canada, they have a 40% chance of being from India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the great lessons from studying history is to do with “base rates”. “Base rate” is a technical term of describing odds in terms of prior probabilities. The base rate of having a drunken-driving accident is higher than those of having accidents in a sober state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding the base rates in a new environment helps to determine whether a certain decision you’re considering has worked before or not, or atleast give you a sense of whether it will work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both these techniques paired together can provide a broader context to how a new unfamiliar system works. One gives a general view of how the system behaves, and another gives insight into how a decision might fare in this system. They are useful on their own, but very powerful when paired together.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We all find ourselves in situations sometimes where there’s a high degree of uncertainty in our decisions. It often comes when starting something new or entering a new domain.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Kickstart and Scale a Marketplace Business</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191120/kickstarting-marketplaces.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Kickstart and Scale a Marketplace Business" /><published>2019-11-20T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-20T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191120/kickstarting-marketplaces</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191120/kickstarting-marketplaces.html">&lt;p&gt;Lenny Rachitsky just &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lennyrachitsky.com/p/how-to-kickstart-and-scale-a-marketplace&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; a really interesting resource for entrepreneurs building marketplace businesses. It’s a guide that steps through the initial stages (solving the chicken-and-egg problem), scaling and evolving the business. The first part is focused on solving the chicken and egg problem, and he provides a really useful ‘cheatsheet’ for the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/marketplacecheatsheet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Marketplace cheat sheet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like a great resource, with new parts are coming in following weeks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Lenny Rachitsky just published a really interesting resource for entrepreneurs building marketplace businesses. It’s a guide that steps through the initial stages (solving the chicken-and-egg problem), scaling and evolving the business. The first part is focused on solving the chicken and egg problem, and he provides a really useful ‘cheatsheet’ for the process.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Global Age Population</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191119/the-global-age-population.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Global Age Population" /><published>2019-11-19T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-19T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191119/the-global-age-population</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191119/the-global-age-population.html">&lt;p&gt;Morgan Housel wrote a few months ago about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/three-big-things-the-most-important-forces-shaping-the-world/&quot;&gt;three forces&lt;/a&gt; shaping the world. One of them was the changing demographics of different countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our World in Data published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/age-structure&quot;&gt;detailed interactive report&lt;/a&gt; on the age structures of countries around the world. There are many important insights here, one of which is there will be &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; more older people. People are living healthier lives due to better food quality and healthcare. For the first time there are more people over 64 than children younger than 5. The population pyramid visualizes this nicely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/uploads/2019/04/Population-Pyramid-1950-to-2100.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Age Population Pyramid&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Morgan Housel wrote a few months ago about three forces shaping the world. One of them was the changing demographics of different countries.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Education Transformation (via USV)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191118/the-education-transformation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Education Transformation (via USV)" /><published>2019-11-18T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-18T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191118/the-education-transformation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191118/the-education-transformation.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been lucky to work with the amazing team at Union Square Ventures here at Wattpad. Today they wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usv.com/writing/2019/11/the-education-transformation/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about the state of the education market, and the transformation taking place in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of the problem is that education represents the highest growing cost for an average American. It’s become increasingly difficult financially to afford a decent education - ironically at the same time education delivery technology has improved rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our education portfolio has become a core value driver in our funds. In part, we think this is because we have hit the tipping point in consumers’ interest in self-driven, direct-to-learner education because technology has enabled higher quality education to be delivered at a lower price point, a counter-balance to the inflationary trends we’ve seen to date. Appetite for products and services that reframe what it means to learn – and how to learn – is high, and quickly accelerating. Which is all to say, we’re ready for more and eager to meet the teams that are building the products and platforms that will restructure education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been lucky to work with the amazing team at Union Square Ventures here at Wattpad. Today they wrote a post about the state of the education market, and the transformation taking place in the industry.</summary></entry></feed>