<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-22T11:31:51-04:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Weekend Mode</title><link href="/20191021/weekend-mode.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weekend Mode" /><published>2019-10-21T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-21T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20191021/weekend-mode</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20191021/weekend-mode.html">&lt;p&gt;Parenting is rewarding, but it’s all-consuming. There’s no time that’s more obvious than the weekend. I’ve found a really good system to fall back on during the weekday, but weekend schedules tend to devolve pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of it comes down to how the day starts. And the problem with weekends is that they typically start inconsistently, or without any space for personal time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone mentioned recently they used a morning workout to &lt;em&gt;anchor their day&lt;/em&gt;. I like that analogy. It implies that it can’t swing about wildly, which is what weekends often feel like. By Sunday I’m craving that &lt;em&gt;routine&lt;/em&gt; again. Perhaps that ebb and flow is a necessary weekly rhythm. For now, I look for joy by embracing the chaos.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Parenting is rewarding, but it’s all-consuming. There’s no time that’s more obvious than the weekend. I’ve found a really good system to fall back on during the weekday, but weekend schedules tend to devolve pretty quickly.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Facebook’s Identity Crisis</title><link href="/20191021/facebook.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Facebook's Identity Crisis" /><published>2019-10-21T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-21T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20191021/facebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20191021/facebook.html">&lt;p&gt;Canada is going to the elections tomorrow. It’s been more polarizing than &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt;, whatever that even means these days. Social media has it on full display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2019/10/17/20919223/mark-zuckerberg-facebook-speech-live-politics-threats-free-expression&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that it will not ban poltical ads that contain known falsehoods, in defense of &lt;em&gt;free speech&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Given the sensitivity around political ads, I’ve considered whether we should stop allowing them altogether. From a business perspective, the controversy certainly isn’t worth the small part of our business they make up. But political ads are an important part of voice — especially for local candidates, up-and-coming challengers, and advocacy groups that may not get much media attention otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, Mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s rewind to 2016 - a fucked up year by most standards. Trump was elected, and even Mark admitted he didn’t anticipate nor fully accept responsibility for all the things that happen on his platform. First there was that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/facebook-blamed-trump-election-mark-zuckerberg-response-tone-deaf-2016-11&quot;&gt;tone-deaf denial&lt;/a&gt;. In their defense, they later started &lt;a href=&quot;https://fortune.com/2016/12/15/facebook-responsibility/&quot;&gt;taking responsibility&lt;/a&gt;. So after three long years of doing that, hiring &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/pazmgy/facebook-is-hiring-1000-more-people-to-block-fake-news-ads&quot;&gt;thousands&lt;/a&gt; to combat the issue, it just feels just so strange that we ended up here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All for this ridiculous fear that Facebook will no longer be a place for &lt;em&gt;free speech&lt;/em&gt;. Newsflash: it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/communitystandards/&quot;&gt;never was&lt;/a&gt;. Facebook is many things - but &lt;em&gt;neutral&lt;/em&gt; is definitely not one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsroom.fb.com/news/2019/10/mark-zuckerberg-stands-for-voice-and-free-expression/&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; “focusing on authenticity and verifying accounts is a much better solution than an ever-expanding definition of what speech is harmful.” Here’s how I read that: “We will block fake news from fake accounts. But real people, especially those real people that benefit the most from fake news - they’re cool. They can stay. Infact, we’ll take their money and promote them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversations defending Facebook’s right to exercise American values on a global platform (don’t get me started) revolve around how Facebook is &lt;em&gt;so different&lt;/em&gt;. That’s true along many dimensions. User generated content at scale changes the game in significant ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the crux of it. The finely tuned economic engine for Facebook behaves like a publisher. Not only is it taking advertiser money, it’s also exercising broad editorial standards. Just like a publisher. These are significant truths, albeit inconvenient for Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how this all &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt;. Mark doesn’t like what Facebook is today. He wants it to be a place where free speech can flourish, and hopefully not damage democracy in the process. But doing one without the other - that’s messy work. People work. Not high-gross-margin-platform-business work. And after years of effort trying to make it all, well, work…the answers still aren’t clear. Idealism is all that’s left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except it’s nowhere near enough. Here’s what bothers me the most - If you accept responsibility for something, you have to do it &lt;em&gt;fully&lt;/em&gt;. Commit to it, for the long term. And if you don’t want to take it on - &lt;strong&gt;that’s fine too&lt;/strong&gt;. Just don’t say one thing and do another.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Canada is going to the elections tomorrow. It’s been more polarizing than normal, whatever that even means these days. Social media has it on full display.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Running Towards Problems</title><link href="/20191018/running-towards-problems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Running Towards Problems" /><published>2019-10-18T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-18T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20191018/running-towards-problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20191018/running-towards-problems.html">&lt;p&gt;Ben Horowitz published a short but powerful &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/10/17/how-to-be-effective-ceo-leader/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about the mindset of a founder / CEO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On how being a founder means your temperament is tied to company ups and downs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you found a company, it tends to get wired into your nervous system. I used to become physically ill whenever there was something wrong in the company — even if I didn’t know what it was. Even if I couldn’t see it, I could feel it. It wasn’t a pleasant feeling. Most good founder/CEOs that I know have this same, gnarly experience. Unfortunately, feeling it turns out to be the easy part of the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that dreaded feeling that only a CEO can truly internalize:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Your last round’s valuation was high and valuations have fallen. Your topline growth is a bit lower than expected and your spend rate is as planned. You can feel that’s going to be a big problem. Do you intellectualize it away? “We’ve got a great new product release coming and we’ve gotten great press lately. We can make it up this quarter” or do you run towards the terrifying situation and try to figure it out now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On what seperates the good from the bad:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Which way you run is often the key differentiator between effective and ineffective CEOs. Almost all CEOs know where the problems are, but only the truly elite ones run towards the fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Required reading. Check it out &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/10/17/how-to-be-effective-ceo-leader/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ben Horowitz published a short but powerful post about the mindset of a founder / CEO.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Startups as Learning Communities</title><link href="/20191017/startups-as-learning-communities.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Startups as Learning Communities" /><published>2019-10-17T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-17T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20191017/startups-as-learning-communities</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20191017/startups-as-learning-communities.html">&lt;p&gt;The abstract definition of a “learning community” is a collective of individuals working towards some academic or skill development. Typically, there’s a cycle of collaborative and individual work (in academia, class and homework) and a cohort-based structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This definition applies well to startups too. The stages of a startup create a natural cohort structure too. Employees often “graduate” out of their roles within 2-3 years, and seek opportunities to learn either in the later stage organization, or elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startups should consider themselves learning communities with that have a common outcome. After all, in the knowledge economy, the raw ingredients for any startup is people. The most successful startups are known for their business results &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; their infrastructure for personal growth. This takes intentionality, a good relationship with failure and learning, all of which needs to be supported at leadership level. It’s a long term investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much attention about the “Future of Work” goes to the collaboration problems, but there’s more unlocked value in solving the higher order problems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The abstract definition of a “learning community” is a collective of individuals working towards some academic or skill development. Typically, there’s a cycle of collaborative and individual work (in academia, class and homework) and a cohort-based structure.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Startup Studios</title><link href="/20191016/startup-studios.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Startup Studios" /><published>2019-10-16T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-16T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20191016/startup-studios</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20191016/startup-studios.html">&lt;p&gt;With private markets awash with capital, there are so many new venture funds that have been created in the last few years. One of the models I’ve been really interested in is the startup studio model - a firm that builds companies by actively testing a specific thesis or idea. Some studios focus on novel ideas, others create clones for underserved markets. Some build operating teams, others just look to create the founding team. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/global-startup-studio-network/the-origin-and-evolution-of-the-startup-studio-3e442c35d21&quot;&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; goes through the evolution of the model and lists some of the most popular studios operating today, as well as their approach to the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a really interesting take and another example of venture taking different forms, especially in early stages of company formation. Sometimes the studio environment is perfect for a startup or team, and other times it won’t work. That said, while there isn’t any quantifiable evidence that it convincingly works better than the current venture model (atleast not yet), it’s really healthy to see funds playing experimenting with how they add value in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">With private markets awash with capital, there are so many new venture funds that have been created in the last few years. One of the models I’ve been really interested in is the startup studio model - a firm that builds companies by actively testing a specific thesis or idea. Some studios focus on novel ideas, others create clones for underserved markets. Some build operating teams, others just look to create the founding team. This article goes through the evolution of the model and lists some of the most popular studios operating today, as well as their approach to the model.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Roadblocks and Routines</title><link href="/20191015/roadblocks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Roadblocks and Routines" /><published>2019-10-15T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-15T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20191015/roadblocks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20191015/roadblocks.html">&lt;p&gt;Our perception is generally tuned towards the problems we see around us. It’s easy to become apathetic towards everything that’s going &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When those problems are [relatively] small, we can still see the forest for the trees and keep moving. But sometimes, we encounter problems that are seemingly so large that they appear as roadblocks preventing us from moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the tools I’ve found useful in those cases is creating a broader perspective - trying to look at your world in different domains - family, friends, lifestyle, career, your physical and mental capabilities. This is not for the sake of balancing - finding what’s good in one domain seldom counteracts what’s not great in another. It’s the awareness of the problem in the context of &lt;em&gt;everything else&lt;/em&gt; makes it more manageable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This level of awareness seems to build naturally when establishing a daily routine. Having a system to fall back on helps to anchor your day, and the result is a more calm outlook towards any problems you have - no matter their size.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Our perception is generally tuned towards the problems we see around us. It’s easy to become apathetic towards everything that’s going right.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stripe’s Accessible Color System</title><link href="/20191015/stripe-color-system.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stripe's Accessible Color System" /><published>2019-10-15T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-15T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20191015/stripe-color-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20191015/stripe-color-system.html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, Stripe published a blog post about accessible color systems - something most companies would not pay much attention to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, this wasn’t just &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; post on accessibility or design systems, it was a first principles breakdown of the problem and an incredibly thorough investigation of the best approach. Read it &lt;a href=&quot;https://stripe.com/au/blog/accessible-color-systems&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The content itself is interesting, but the real story is the level of investigation into the topic. It’s another one of the reasons I believe Stripe is one of those once-in-a-generation type of companies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Recently, Stripe published a blog post about accessible color systems - something most companies would not pay much attention to.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Food as Software</title><link href="/20191013/food-as-software.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Food as Software" /><published>2019-10-13T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-13T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20191013/food-as-software</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20191013/food-as-software.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently listened to a discussion about food technology on CBC Radio, and the upcoming disruption of the entire agricultural farming industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative food sector is seeing explosive growth, and brands like Impossible Burgers and Beyond Meat are a big part of the narrative. But the core of this disruption is research to synthetically create the actual proteins found in popular foods. This means that whether it’s coffee, or steak, or even milk - all of this will be producible synthetically and at a higher quality than factory farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part is particularly interesting, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rethinkx.com/food-and-agriculture#food-and-agriculture-download&quot;&gt;Rethinking Food and Agriculture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The current industrialized, animal-agriculture system will be replaced with a Food-as-Software model, where foods are engineered by scientists at a molecular level and uploaded to databases that can be accessed by food designers anywhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, this process costs thousands of dollars to create. But those cost curves are decreasing rapidly, and soon most burgers will be produced in a factory. Disruption theory is taking place in the food industry, and it’s pretty incredible. This also mirrors the evolution of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencehistory.org/the-history-and-future-of-plastics&quot;&gt;synthetic plastics industry&lt;/a&gt; in the early 1900’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More on the CBC conversation &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/radio/spark/from-lab-grown-meat-to-molecular-coffee-how-tech-is-disrupting-the-food-industry-1.5316906&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently listened to a discussion about food technology on CBC Radio, and the upcoming disruption of the entire agricultural farming industry.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Company Building</title><link href="/20191011/what-is-a-company.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Company Building" /><published>2019-10-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20191011/what-is-a-company</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20191011/what-is-a-company.html">&lt;p&gt;This morning, I had an amazing conversation with a good friend about his new venture. The topic went in many directions, but we talked for a while about company building and leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked a question that I’ve asked myself in my quest to learn how to become a more effective leader - &lt;em&gt;what is a company&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I get to that, a short diatribe about the current state of leadership advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leadership advice surrounds us in the tech community. It’s everywhere. It’s amazing that people from different companies at different stages are openly sharing their lessons in an effort to make us better. But that’s made for information overload. The problem of “popular advice” has never been worse. Popularity is a horrible proxy for many things, but especially so for advice. It creates recency bias and results in misapplying tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion I’ve reached is leadership advice needs to be received with more structure. All advice needs a mental framework in our minds, so we can use the right tools for the right jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That framework for me is the company system - people, organizing as teams, creating some output, received by a market, which done enough, produces impact. It translates the line between an individual and impact. There’s nuance around governance and company stage that needs to be considered, but for the most part the simple structure is an incredibly useful mental model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This simple framework also helps me place advice, and I look to challenge it everytime I learn something new (reading a new book, or a blog post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href=&quot;/20181020/leadership-lattice-simplified.html&quot;&gt;the company system&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This morning, I had an amazing conversation with a good friend about his new venture. The topic went in many directions, but we talked for a while about company building and leadership.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On ‘The China Cultural Clash’</title><link href="/20191010/china.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On 'The China Cultural Clash'" /><published>2019-10-10T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-10T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20191010/china</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20191010/china.html">&lt;p&gt;Ben Thompson writes about tech and strategy, but recently wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;https://stratechery.com/2019/the-china-cultural-clash/&quot;&gt;the NBA’s rift with China&lt;/a&gt;. I really enjoyed reading this one. These are some of my favorite captions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the fact that &lt;strong&gt;this isn’t new&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The truth is that the U.S. China relationship has been extremely one-sided for a very long time now: China buys the hardware it needs, and keeps all of the software opportunities for itself — and, of course, pursues software opportunities abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This understated the case: not only were Chinese companies allowed into the U.S. while U.S. companies remained locked out of China, Chinese attacks on U.S. tech companies were allowed by China’s censors, and in fact even augmented by the Great Firewall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This point is interesting. We worry about Chinese censorship of US content &lt;em&gt;in China&lt;/em&gt;, but we need to think of the reverse - US residents being censored within their own countries by a foreign government. This is especially true with the rise of tech startups with Chinese ownership (like TikTok) that have become popular globally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This should raise serious concern in the United States and other Western countries: is it at all acceptable to have a social network that has a demonstrated willingness to censor content under the control of a country that has clearly different views on what constitutes free speech?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On his personal conflict and the impetus for companies to choose morals over money:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am not particularly excited to write this article. My instinct is towards free trade, my affinity for Asia generally and Greater China specifically, my welfare enhanced by staying off China’s radar. And yet, for all that the idea of being a global citizen is an alluring concept and largely my lived experience, I find in situations like this that I am undoubtedly a child of the West. I do believe in the individual, in free speech, and in democracy, no matter how poorly practiced in the United States or elsewhere. And, in situations like this weekend, when values meet money, &lt;strong&gt;I worry just how many companies are capable of choosing the former?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the broader moral conflict:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The biggest, shift, though, is a mindset one. First, the Internet is an amoral force that reduces friction, not an inevitable force for good. Second, sometimes different cultures simply have fundamentally different values. Third, if values are going to be preserved, they must be a leading factor in economic entanglement, not a trailing one. This is the point that Clinton got the most wrong: money, like tech, is amoral. If we insist it matters most our own morals will inevitably disappear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ben Thompson writes about tech and strategy, but recently wrote about the NBA’s rift with China. I really enjoyed reading this one. These are some of my favorite captions:</summary></entry></feed>