<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-11-20T11:57:56-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Global Age Population</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191119/the-global-age-population.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Global Age Population" /><published>2019-11-19T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-19T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191119/the-global-age-population</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191119/the-global-age-population.html">&lt;p&gt;Morgan Housel wrote a few months ago about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/three-big-things-the-most-important-forces-shaping-the-world/&quot;&gt;three forces&lt;/a&gt; shaping the world. One of them was the changing demographics of different countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our World in Data published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/age-structure&quot;&gt;detailed interactive report&lt;/a&gt; on the age structures of countries around the world. There are many important insights here, one of which is there will be &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; more older people. People are living healthier lives due to better food quality and healthcare. For the first time there are more people over 64 than children younger than 5. The population pyramid visualizes this nicely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/uploads/2019/04/Population-Pyramid-1950-to-2100.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Age Population Pyramid&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Morgan Housel wrote a few months ago about three forces shaping the world. One of them was the changing demographics of different countries.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Education Transformation (via USV)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191118/the-education-transformation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Education Transformation (via USV)" /><published>2019-11-18T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-18T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191118/the-education-transformation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191118/the-education-transformation.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been lucky to work with the amazing team at Union Square Ventures here at Wattpad. Today they wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usv.com/writing/2019/11/the-education-transformation/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about the state of the education market, and the transformation taking place in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of the problem is that education represents the highest growing cost for an average American. It’s become increasingly difficult financially to afford a decent education - ironically at the same time education delivery technology has improved rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our education portfolio has become a core value driver in our funds. In part, we think this is because we have hit the tipping point in consumers’ interest in self-driven, direct-to-learner education because technology has enabled higher quality education to be delivered at a lower price point, a counter-balance to the inflationary trends we’ve seen to date. Appetite for products and services that reframe what it means to learn – and how to learn – is high, and quickly accelerating. Which is all to say, we’re ready for more and eager to meet the teams that are building the products and platforms that will restructure education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been lucky to work with the amazing team at Union Square Ventures here at Wattpad. Today they wrote a post about the state of the education market, and the transformation taking place in the industry.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">WYDIWYA: On Genghis Khan</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191117/notes-on-genghis-khan.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WYDIWYA: On Genghis Khan" /><published>2019-11-17T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-17T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191117/notes-on-genghis-khan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191117/notes-on-genghis-khan.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m slow reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/What-You-Do-Who-Are-ebook/dp/B07NVN4QCM&quot;&gt;What You Do is Who You Are&lt;/a&gt; by Ben Horowitz, and writing a series of posts to capture some key points from each major section. This post is about Genghis Khan’s rise to power and what it has to teach us about establishing culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genghis used a decentralized management and speed as his secret weapon against clans much largers than his own army. He also ensured best practices of the places he was conquering were brought into the fold in his army - enabling a culture of continuous learning. There were three principles that helped him create a stable culture: meritocracy, loyalty, and inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metitocracy was about destroying the hierarchical and sexist structures of the military in the past. He changed his military structure to operate as concentric circles vs. hierarchies with a consistent chain of command. This allowed him to get rid of those that were there just for status, and promote soliders to leaders if they demonstrated that ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loyalty was a “bilateral relationship”, almost synonymous with trust. It was about having the option to punish someone for not obeying orders, but also not always exercising that option. Genghis wanted to preserve Mongol life even as he was conquering the country, so this was applied universally not just within his army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inclusion was about getting rid of the aristocrats and helping soliders rise up from the bottoms up, thereby building trust and loyalty. This applied to the enemies he conquered too. He also created inclusion by creating new ethical boundaries - he outlawed crimes against women and children - something that was commonly accepted during those times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His decentralized approach to creating culture was a revolutionary approach, and although it fell apart because of succession issues, the change he was able to create was remarkable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m slow reading What You Do is Who You Are by Ben Horowitz, and writing a series of posts to capture some key points from each major section. This post is about Genghis Khan’s rise to power and what it has to teach us about establishing culture.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">WYDIWYA: On Senghor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191116/notes-on-senghor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WYDIWYA: On Senghor" /><published>2019-11-16T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-16T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191116/notes-on-senghor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191116/notes-on-senghor.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m slow reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/What-You-Do-Who-Are-ebook/dp/B07NVN4QCM&quot;&gt;What You Do is Who You Are&lt;/a&gt; by Ben Horowitz, and writing a series of posts to capture some key points from each major section. This post is about the chapter on Shaka Senghor who spent 20 years incarcerated and led change within that culture of violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senghor’s story is long and one of the most interesting chapters in the book. He rose ranks within the Melanics gang in his jail, then challenged it’s leaders on their adherence to their principles. This helped him build the trust of new recruits and eventually the leaders themselves. He used his platform to enact changes in the principles themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the key lessons from Sengor apply in the context of someone coming in to change the culture of an organization. In order to do this, one needs to understand some important truths. Here are a few:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture changes people so it’s hard to measure by asking everyone - but the best indicator is those new to the organization. In those first few weeks and months, employees figure out what they need to do to fit in, survive and succeed. If you want to understand your company culture, ask those folks right after those first weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One must live the code. This is an ideal Ben brings up in other chapters too. But in a jail environment, living the code can mean the difference between life or death; stability or chaos. One must put in cultural elements that you actually subscribe to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture is universal. It applies not only to how you treat employees, but also partners, vendors and everyone that your employees come into contact. Your culture travels with them and you need to be prepared to address issues in all those interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture will also get weaponized. People will interpret your code one way, and in an incentive to impress might choose to go to an extreme. It’s difficult to predict all the ways this can happen, but important to react quickly when it does. Often that means a clarification or counterbalancing rule. In Slack’s case, their “empathy” rule was being weaponized to dull negative feedback. So, they changed it to “collaborative”, making it clear that the team outcome is more important than any individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture might require you to change yourself. This is intentional, after all. You are trying to change behaviours of an entire group - this should also apply to you as an individual. Ben provides an example of how he himself ‘weaponized’ his value by equating the truth with simply what was legal. He changed himself and the value so that the emphasis was on the truth being &lt;em&gt;received&lt;/em&gt;, vs. simply just the truth being told. It was a higher bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture requires constant contact. Just like many leadership activities, repetition is the name of the game. It not only creates cadence but reinforces priority.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m slow reading What You Do is Who You Are by Ben Horowitz, and writing a series of posts to capture some key points from each major section. This post is about the chapter on Shaka Senghor who spent 20 years incarcerated and led change within that culture of violence.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">WYDIWYA: On Bushido</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191115/notes-on-bushido.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WYDIWYA: On Bushido" /><published>2019-11-15T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-15T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191115/notes-on-bushido</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191115/notes-on-bushido.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m slow reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/What-You-Do-Who-Are-ebook/dp/B07NVN4QCM&quot;&gt;What You Do is Who You Are&lt;/a&gt; by Ben Horowitz, and writing a series of posts to capture some key points from each major section. This post is about how understanding the Bushido code can help build a stronger company culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first lesson is the difference between values and virtues; the former being a set of beliefs vs the latter being behaviours, and how Bushido is structured:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bushido looks like a set of principles, but it’s a set of practices. The samurai defined culture as a code of action, as system not of values but of virtues. A value is merely a belief, but a virture is a belief that you actively prusue or embody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many corporate cultures center around ‘values’ which immediately makes them ineffective. As Ben states, “what you believe means nearly nothing. What you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; is who you are.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second lesson is on the importance of death. In the samurai context this meant living with the highest degree of honor and attention to your craft, because death can be around any corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The idea is to take care of your public and private duties day and night, and then whenever you have free time when your mind is unoccupied, you think of death, bringing it to mind attentively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a company context keeping death in mind at all times also means thinking about the worst case scenario and planning for what happens next. How do you want your company to be talked about after? How do you want your employees to feel about their time there? Keeping these questions in mind will help you prioritize what’s really important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there are eight samurai virtues, the ones discussed in detail in the book were honor, politeness, and veracity or sincerety. Honor is about how you apply your set of standards in an organization - whether it’s with business dealings, product quality, or employee issues. High honor companies are consistent and systematic in their approach. Politeness is about expressing love and respect for those around you. To ensure that politeness didn’t get used to be fake, there was strong emphasis on the truth - expressed in the virtue of sincerety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Why did the bushido have such a profound impact on Japanese society? The complex answer is that the samurai developed and refined their culture continuously over a very long period of time, using a variety of psychologically sophisticated techniques to make it feel indelible, inescapable and completely natural.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The simple answer is that they kept death in mind at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m slow reading What You Do is Who You Are by Ben Horowitz, and writing a series of posts to capture some key points from each major section. This post is about how understanding the Bushido code can help build a stronger company culture.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MSCHF and Creativity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191114/mschf-internet-creativity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MSCHF and Creativity" /><published>2019-11-14T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-14T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191114/mschf-internet-creativity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191114/mschf-internet-creativity.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bullandmoon.com/&quot;&gt;Bull and Moon&lt;/a&gt; is a satirical new app that helps you find investment opportunities using your astrological sign. It’s a project by &lt;a href=&quot;https://mschf.xyz/&quot;&gt;MSCHF&lt;/a&gt;, which creates products (physical and digital) that are designed to go viral. MSCHF is systemizing this approach with a biweekly drop of two projects. They recently also created &lt;a href=&quot;https://jesus.shoes/&quot;&gt;Jesus Shoes&lt;/a&gt; - which made over a million dollars in an hour. The consistent drops build anticipation and their projects have been featured on blogs and even late night television. “The Supreme for the Internet generation”, as a friend put it recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s amazing to see artists use the Internet as a &lt;em&gt;native&lt;/em&gt; medium of expression, vs. just an extension to what they’ve created already. I love this stuff. This is the best of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Bull and Moon is a satirical new app that helps you find investment opportunities using your astrological sign. It’s a project by MSCHF, which creates products (physical and digital) that are designed to go viral. MSCHF is systemizing this approach with a biweekly drop of two projects. They recently also created Jesus Shoes - which made over a million dollars in an hour. The consistent drops build anticipation and their projects have been featured on blogs and even late night television. “The Supreme for the Internet generation”, as a friend put it recently.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Guidelets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191113/guidelets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guidelets" /><published>2019-11-13T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-13T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191113/guidelets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191113/guidelets.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve often said that everyone has a both a music startup and travel startup idea in them. For travel, everyone has such a personal style that no single product can satisfy the all those niche interests and combinations of interests. Some plan, others are spontaneous. Some enjoy the highlights, others enjoy going off the beaten path. Ofcourse these are only two very simple dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, that travel idea is Guidelets - an app for beautiful “micro” city guides. Each guide is limited to 5 places, forcing curation. Each guide is also very pleasant to read and look at - inspired by the city guides featured in Monocle magazine. It’s just a product that I wish existed, so I decided to create it. As an MVP, I decided to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glideapp.io&quot;&gt;Glide&lt;/a&gt;, the no-code app creator to create a &lt;a href=&quot;https://guidelets.glideapp.io/&quot;&gt;Guidelets Glide app&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll be updating it with more guides from past travels and recommendations from friends’ travels.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve often said that everyone has a both a music startup and travel startup idea in them. For travel, everyone has such a personal style that no single product can satisfy the all those niche interests and combinations of interests. Some plan, others are spontaneous. Some enjoy the highlights, others enjoy going off the beaten path. Ofcourse these are only two very simple dimensions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Incentive Profiles for Leaders</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191112/incentive-profiles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Incentive Profiles for Leaders" /><published>2019-11-12T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-12T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191112/incentive-profiles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191112/incentive-profiles.html">&lt;p&gt;I had a really great conversation recently about how important it is to align leaders with similar incentive structures to foster the right behaviours. Compensation structures are the one of the highest leverage driver of behaviour in an org (especially at executive level), and it’s important for leaders to have common incentive profiles to ensure they are working in the collective interest vs. their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some teams work very differently so it’s not uncommon to see different structures coexist - certain executives compensated for making decisions that pay off in the long term (i.e. with equity), and others compensated for hitting short term goals (e.g. with cash bonuses).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if there are no &lt;em&gt;common&lt;/em&gt; elements to those incentive profiles, it can create unhealthy mercenary behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see this difference often in leaders of pipeline-centric vs product-centric orgs. Pipeline orgs are designed to push pipelines forward, get more and bigger deals done. There’s a very clear 1:1 relationship between effort and outcome. Product centric orgs can get squishier - many decisions don’t pay off in the short term. Infact sometimes the opposite can happen - a short term failure can lead to a long term success. In these cases it doesn’t make sense to compeonsate an employee with a short term incentive like cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen orgs do this well where all executives will have some component of their compensation that follows the same structure. Obviously stock option grants are a great way to make this happen. They are generally aligned towards long term goals and can make sure everyone acts in the long term best interests of the company.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I had a really great conversation recently about how important it is to align leaders with similar incentive structures to foster the right behaviours. Compensation structures are the one of the highest leverage driver of behaviour in an org (especially at executive level), and it’s important for leaders to have common incentive profiles to ensure they are working in the collective interest vs. their own.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Disagree</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191111/how-to-disagree.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Disagree" /><published>2019-11-11T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-11T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191111/how-to-disagree</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191111/how-to-disagree.html">&lt;p&gt;A sign of healthy company culture is meetings where people openly can disagree with each other. It signals a net of psychological safety in which dissent and challenge is seen as productive, and in which failure is seen as a sign of learning. This is especially true in knowledge organizations where the role of leadership is to &lt;em&gt;amplify&lt;/em&gt; the innovative ideas coming from the edges of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, getting here is difficult. The raw ingredients include trust and respect among peers, clear lines of decision making, and a collective intentionality to get better as a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trust and respect is built one interaction at a time. It requires listening more than talking. It’s about developing an honest curiosity for someone elses opinion. Delivering feedback in the right way (timely and direct) also signals respect for others opinions and intentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clear lines of decison making create structure for group interactions. When everyone knows the process of making a decision, who the owner is, and how much information is needed to make said decision, everything moves quicker. Without any of these things decisions start to linger. The point on intentionality is about paying attention to  &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; things are done, not just what is being done. Groups need to be mindful of their dynamic and understand how best to harness it together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For leaders providing feedback in group settings, I’ve found success in picking the right battles. Leaders have natural leverage that sometimes becomes overused on details that are often unimportant. Providing feedback on everything can quickly become noise and ignored (or worse yet, shut out altogether).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A sign of healthy company culture is meetings where people openly can disagree with each other. It signals a net of psychological safety in which dissent and challenge is seen as productive, and in which failure is seen as a sign of learning. This is especially true in knowledge organizations where the role of leadership is to amplify the innovative ideas coming from the edges of the company.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On The Wealth Gap Discussion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191110/wealth-gap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On The Wealth Gap Discussion" /><published>2019-11-10T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-10T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191110/wealth-gap</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191110/wealth-gap.html">&lt;p&gt;There has been much discussion on the wealth gap issues in the last few weeks, fueled by speeches on the US campaign trail to Bill Gates’ comments on the wealth tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve read a lot of polarizing views on this subject. One side wants all billionaires abolished, and proposes a massive redistribution of wealth. Another side extols the virtues of the free markets as if to say the wealth gap is a feature not a bug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is another example of smart people ignoring nuance on both sides. Albert from USV has a moderate and convincing &lt;a href=&quot;https://continuations.com/post/188901476550/bad-takes-on-taxing-wealth-especially&quot;&gt;commentary&lt;/a&gt; on the same issues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There has been much discussion on the wealth gap issues in the last few weeks, fueled by speeches on the US campaign trail to Bill Gates’ comments on the wealth tax.</summary></entry></feed>