<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-13T10:40:49-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Losing Focus</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190912/losing-focus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Losing Focus" /><published>2019-09-12T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-12T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190912/losing-focus</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190912/losing-focus.html">&lt;p&gt;“It is incredibly easy to lose focus”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend told me this yesterday; it resonated a lot. It made me think about focus through the lens of inversion. There are a lot of tools and frameworks avaialable for people to maintain focus. But, “keeping focus” is like a goal that you’re always fighting against. It sounds obvious, but anytime you &lt;em&gt;lose focus&lt;/em&gt;, you’ve lost in your battle to &lt;em&gt;keep it&lt;/em&gt;. So it demotivates you, and makes you feel like distraction is a part of your identity versus something that you simply experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, instead of trying to keep focus, just try to note when you’ve lost it. And when you do, bring it back to whatever you were working on last. The ability to note your distraction and come back to the task at hand is like a muscle - it will become stronger over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, you will also understand the &lt;em&gt;triggers&lt;/em&gt; that lead to distractive patterns. The best way to keep focus is then to avoid those triggers - something that is more actionable than simply trying to “keep focus”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“It is incredibly easy to lose focus”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Incomplete Financial Products</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190911/flexible-financial-products.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Incomplete Financial Products" /><published>2019-09-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190911/flexible-financial-products</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190911/flexible-financial-products.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bradmillscan/status/1171494009228812289&quot;&gt;this thread on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; about the banking experience for an elderly gentleman in Canada. It’s frankly horrific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The financial product landscape is monopolized by banks, which wouldn’t be a bad thing if there was a greater range of  products available. There are so many segments of the population that have unique problems that are not being served by existing products. This is true especially in Canada which is a very multicultural society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a more customer centric approach to banking and looking at the unique needs of these segments - the elderly, immigrants, caregivers - are paramount to creating a better banking experience. Whether it’s loan products with friendlier terms, financing for those taking care of their parents, appealing to those that have a cultural inhibition to debt - all of these things are not being addressed through the current product suite across banks. They have taken a bank-centric vs. customer centric approach, and it shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a problem and a huge opportunity. Thankfully, this is a known problem and many fintech companies (the entire industry, arguably) are actively working on solutions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently read this thread on Twitter about the banking experience for an elderly gentleman in Canada. It’s frankly horrific.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">9/11</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190911/nine-eleven.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="9/11" /><published>2019-09-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190911/nine-eleven</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190911/nine-eleven.html">&lt;p&gt;Eighteen years ago today, the world changed when the Twin Towers collapsed. It’s one of those &lt;em&gt;where were you when it happened&lt;/em&gt; moments. This is my story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in Seattle and it was the second day of an internship at Amazon.com. It was 2001 and I was working on the [tiny] mobile team. A friend generously lent me a space on their couch while I looked for an apartment, so I was sleeping on the couch when my friend woke me and turned on the TV. As the events were still unfolding, many major cities like Seattle were on high alert and were evacuating their skyscrapers. We actually went in to work, but then rushed back home. We were warned that being in a highrise wasn’t safe. It was a real and unforgettable fear. It was what I felt during scud missile attacks during the first Gulf War in Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also a time that brought people together. Strangers became family and friends, collectively supporting each other over the next few hours and days. I’m sure many of those bonds still last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans are capable of infinite love and hate. In a strange way, both were on display that day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Eighteen years ago today, the world changed when the Twin Towers collapsed. It’s one of those where were you when it happened moments. This is my story.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Notes on Culture and Decision Making</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190910/notes-on-culture.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Notes on Culture and Decision Making" /><published>2019-09-10T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-10T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190910/notes-on-culture</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190910/notes-on-culture.html">&lt;p&gt;Companies are complex systems. We create abstractions to simplify working within them. For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Strategy” is an abstraction for the collective of short and long term decisions to win in a market. 
“Operations” is an abstraction for the sum of working norms in place towards some enterprise output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s “Culture”, probably the most misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture is an abstraction for the sum of all interactions between people in an organization. Often articulated as a set of “Values”, this encompasses everything from everyday decision making to creating a sense of belonging and psychological safety. The broadest definition of culture is all-encompassing, and that’s perhaps why it’s interpreted in so many ways across companies. Today, it’s normal to see a company culture&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I read a really good blog post by Casey Winters, CPO at Eventbrite, who wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;https://caseyaccidental.com/cultural-values/&quot;&gt;cultural values&lt;/a&gt;. In it, he describes how cultural values are better described on a &lt;em&gt;spectrum&lt;/em&gt; rather than on their own. For example, on the spectrum of speed vs. quality, Facebook encourages it’s employees to bias towards speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much of culture is reflected in decision making, which in itself is an exercise in evaluating trade-offs. Cultural values should be clear about those trade-offs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Companies are complex systems. We create abstractions to simplify working within them. For example,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Notes on Fintech</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190909/fintech-growth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Notes on Fintech" /><published>2019-09-09T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-09T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190909/fintech-growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190909/fintech-growth.html">&lt;p&gt;Some thoughts about common growth and expansion vectors for Fintech startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first direction is horizontal expansion to offer more financial products (e.g. insurances, mortgages, loans, etc). This is the most common approach. Investment service providers expand to offer different savings and investment products. A good example is Wealthfront - known for it’s investment platform, which also now offers bridge loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second vector is verticalization, i.e. to own more of the customer experience upto the point of creating financial products. This applies to fintech’s that are mostly discovery / referral businesses. Verticalization means owning the application process and providing the financial product itself (i.e. a loan or insurance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of the above approaches lead to a fintech turning into a neo-bank (a digital native financial service provider).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third vector is geographic expansion. This approach requires an investment in regulatory compliance but is a relatively smaller investment than a bank establishing branches overseas. This is less common but there are some good examples of this - Wealthsimple in Canada operates in the US and UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three examples have a common thread - take a digital first, customer driven approach to financial services and compete on &lt;em&gt;simplicity&lt;/em&gt; to get the financial products.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Some thoughts about common growth and expansion vectors for Fintech startups.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Travel Decentralized</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190908/travel-decentralized.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Travel Decentralized" /><published>2019-09-08T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-08T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190908/travel-decentralized</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190908/travel-decentralized.html">&lt;p&gt;I live to travel. I love that tech has made it easy to experience the world, whether its through instant online booking, social recommendations or home-sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the convenience is great, I do miss parts of the travel agent experience. I miss the ability to contact someone that understands your travel preference, can find you things you might not have been looking for, and make the process of travel planning more fun than work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What tech has done is taken a fragmented supply (flights, hotels, etc) and make it really easy for the customer to make the best choices at the cheapest cost. In similar ways to other marketplaces, those suppliers now depend on travel bookings by these sites and advertise good reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I wonder if there’s a need for a product to help those travel agents become more successful, and to help people &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; travel agents. I have friends with amazing taste that refer people to travel destinations without participating in any upside for that referral. It would be really interesting to see a product that helps them participate in that; I think it’s worth it for all sides involved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I live to travel. I love that tech has made it easy to experience the world, whether its through instant online booking, social recommendations or home-sharing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Doing Things in Order</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190907/doing-things-in-order.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Doing Things in Order" /><published>2019-09-07T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-07T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190907/doing-things-in-order</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190907/doing-things-in-order.html">&lt;p&gt;I made a small adjustment to my planning routine recently - to simply &lt;em&gt;do things in priority order&lt;/em&gt;. This is a simple principle but incredible difficult to execute in practice. I’m sharing the method I use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I start with writing my global priorities. For me this is - my physical and mental health, the well being of my family and friends, and then the things that give me professional and creative fulfillment. Within this structure, I put down the tasks that I need to do during the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for my physical and mental health - this is working out, a short meditation and writing. 
For my family, these are the things to maintain and improve my most important personal relationships. 
For professional fulfillment, these are the things I do at work with a team trying to realize a collective vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I start working on them in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means I start my day with a workout, meditation, and writing. Then, I do the family &amp;amp; friends stuff - whether it’s ordering diapers on Amazon or getting back in touch with someone. And then I move on to work tasks, which I also &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; to prioritize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This only applies to weekdays. Weekends follow a very different structure when you have kids. This isn’t perfect and I still get distracted (noting when that happens is also critical). But I really appreciate getting the most important things done first.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I made a small adjustment to my planning routine recently - to simply do things in priority order. This is a simple principle but incredible difficult to execute in practice. I’m sharing the method I use.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Futureland Support Packs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190906/futureland-support-packs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Futureland Support Packs" /><published>2019-09-06T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-06T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190906/futureland-support-packs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190906/futureland-support-packs.html">&lt;p&gt;Futureland is a supportive multidisciplinary community of people committed to creating something &lt;em&gt;everyday&lt;/em&gt; for a year. It’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://hfo.futureland.tv/&quot;&gt;a new way to learn anything&lt;/a&gt;, and recently launched &lt;a href=&quot;https://internetvin.com/2019/09/06/futureland-support-packs/&quot;&gt;Futureland Support Packs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support Packs are a way to fund the development of the project, which is currently a solo-effort by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/internetvin&quot;&gt;InternetVin&lt;/a&gt;. He says it best in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://internetvin.com/2019/09/06/futureland-support-packs/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Futureland has demonstrated that it can be an effective tool for someone to learn new skills and stick to long term projects. I receive positive feedback on this project every day. But can Futureland continue to sustain itself? At this point, Futureland is entirely created and supported by me.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I started to wonder, how Futureand could ask for support in a way that (1) was respectful of early user support through their time and energy. And (2) recognizes that Futureland is still very much a product in development and therefore should not be priced like a final product.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The solution I came to was this concept of optional support for existing users. If users want and are in a position to support Futureland, they can. I created a few different methods to do that. Some are simple like a $20 pledge and others include cool products like a limited full-sleeve Futureland tee.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I will always be experimenting with new ways to sustain and expand Futureland while being respectful to its earliest users. The vision is to create a tool that makes it a little easier for any one on Earth to learn anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Futureland is a supportive multidisciplinary community of people committed to creating something everyday for a year. It’s a new way to learn anything, and recently launched Futureland Support Packs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Productivity Learnings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190905/productivity-lessons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Productivity Learnings" /><published>2019-09-05T12:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-05T12:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190905/productivity-lessons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190905/productivity-lessons.html">&lt;p&gt;I had a really great conversation today about managing time, and ended up going over some of my most important learnings about productivity over the last year. These are some of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with &lt;a href=&quot;/20180902/self-curiosity.html&quot;&gt;self curiosity&lt;/a&gt;. Try to understand your daily energy levels (what time of day you are most productive), and design your day around that. That will be a quick win that will help you understand how to replicate productive times throughout the day. I started this by &lt;a href=&quot;/20180918/time-tracking-update.html&quot;&gt;logging my time&lt;/a&gt; for an extended period to observe where it was being spent. Spend time to look back - I do &lt;a href=&quot;/20180911/productivity-planning-retros.html&quot;&gt;retrospectives&lt;/a&gt; on a regular basis to find patterns and ways I can improve. When you find out time is being spent in a way, or a time you don’t want it to - try to take it back. It’s yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving &lt;em&gt;yourself&lt;/em&gt; requires as much intention as improving &lt;em&gt;your work&lt;/em&gt;. Remember that you and your work are two separate things. Externalizing yourself from your work allows you to stay calm. A good tool is to understand the emotional triggers that lead you into time-consuming thought patterns (stress, intense excitement). I do this with an anxiety journal where I write down “what happened” and “how it made me feel”. The act of noting these triggers itself relieves stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By nature, this list will get better over time as I learn more about myself and what makes me productive and happy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I had a really great conversation today about managing time, and ended up going over some of my most important learnings about productivity over the last year. These are some of them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Thoughts on Marketplace Identity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190904/marketplace-identity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Thoughts on Marketplace Identity" /><published>2019-09-04T12:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-04T12:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190904/marketplace-identity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190904/marketplace-identity.html">&lt;p&gt;Marketplaces are a great place for consumers and producers to come together online. Across industries, dual-sided marketplaces have untapped latent demand or better utilized supply and created really interesting businesses along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As marketplaces grow, consumers come to expect the benefits of economies of scale - better selection, price and overall fulfillment experience. As producers become more savvy, they will want to exercise more control over the entire customer experience. Ultimately, as entrepreneurs, most of them will want to own that customer relationship themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This creates a choice that defines the identity the marketplace - to focus on building the largest end-customer base, or to focus on helping sellers become the most successful. There are of course examples where building for both can work for an extended period of time, but managing &lt;a href=&quot;/20190710/maintaining-equilibrium-marketplace-development.html&quot;&gt;equlibrium&lt;/a&gt; is incredibly difficult as marketplaces scale.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Marketplaces are a great place for consumers and producers to come together online. Across industries, dual-sided marketplaces have untapped latent demand or better utilized supply and created really interesting businesses along the way.</summary></entry></feed>