<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-08-14T11:33:45-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What Writing Everyday Has Taught Me</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190811/what-has-writing-regularly-taught-me.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Writing Everyday Has Taught Me" /><published>2019-08-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190811/what-has-writing-regularly-taught-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190811/what-has-writing-regularly-taught-me.html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I received a message from a friend asking, “What have you learned from writing on your blog regularly?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great question that provoked a number of thoughts, and I decided to write out my replies as a blog post itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, writing creates deeper comprehension. Learning and expressing a readable opinion is a great forcing function for understanding any topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing also teaches brevity and the art of getting to the point. Infact, writing is more often &lt;em&gt;removing&lt;/em&gt; words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing as a habit has taught me about myself - my default systems and common excuses. This is likely the byproduct of a the daily commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, writing has become an instrument to do work. It’s not exactly learning, but there’s a ton of value here. I often end meetings saying, ‘I’m going to write about this’, and that post has lasting value (and a nice reminder of our interaction).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today, I received a message from a friend asking, “What have you learned from writing on your blog regularly?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trends in Seed Investing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190811/seed-investing-trends.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trends in Seed Investing" /><published>2019-08-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190811/seed-investing-trends</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190811/seed-investing-trends.html">&lt;p&gt;Tom Tunguz recently shared some &lt;a href=&quot;https://tomtunguz.com/which-categories-of-seed-startups-are-thriving-which-aren-t/&quot;&gt;data and insights on seed investing trends&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s growing: AI, Blockchain, Fintech, Food and Beverage and Software (automating internal processes). 
What’s not: Advertising, Analytics, Big Data and Social Media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This data is a &lt;em&gt;signal of investor confidence level&lt;/em&gt; in each of these markets, which is correlated (and sometimes cuasal) to growth in the markets themselves. It’s important to understand this abstraction - especially since seed investing sometimes suffers from herd behaviour. For that reason, there’s probably an argument to discount the outliers, especially given the &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2019/03/16/decade-in-review-trends-in-seed-and-early-stage-funding/&quot;&gt;rise in seed funds&lt;/a&gt; over the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Tom Tunguz recently shared some data and insights on seed investing trends.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Risk in Startups</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190808/classic-risk-vs-quantum-risk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Risk in Startups" /><published>2019-08-08T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-08T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190808/classic-risk-vs-quantum-risk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190808/classic-risk-vs-quantum-risk.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about early stage startup risk especially in working on the presentations about minimum viable products. In that discussion, I’ll be talking about how MVP’s are a framework for de-risking startup investments. In the early stages of a startup, the risk of getting to product market fit is the largest (but not only) reason why most startups fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came across this article about startup risk authored by Kanyi Maqubela - &lt;a href=&quot;https://kanyi.blog/2018/10/18/classical-risk-vs-quantum-risk/&quot;&gt;classic risk vs. quantum risk&lt;/a&gt; - and it summarizes the &lt;em&gt;weight&lt;/em&gt; of product/market fit risk really well - essentially, the risk associated with P/M fit is so much higher than all other risks associated with activities in that stage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What does that mean for company formation? What if risk, as a function of milestones, looked less like classical mechanics, where there can be continuous, curve-like de-risking in time? What if all of the activity that comes along with building a company does not in fact de-risk it? What if product market-fit is in fact the only discrete state in the early stage that de-risks a company?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, you can de-risk an early stage venture through in many different ways but only P/M fit matters. Simply put, if you haven’t built the right product for the right people &lt;em&gt;at the right time&lt;/em&gt;, nothing else matters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been thinking about early stage startup risk especially in working on the presentations about minimum viable products. In that discussion, I’ll be talking about how MVP’s are a framework for de-risking startup investments. In the early stages of a startup, the risk of getting to product market fit is the largest (but not only) reason why most startups fail.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Value Propositions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190801/value-propositions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Value Propositions" /><published>2019-08-01T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-01T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190801/value-propositions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190801/value-propositions.html">&lt;p&gt;These are notes for a talk I’ll be giving in a few weeks about Value Propositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a product person, but even I will admit that most of product building is actually &lt;em&gt;sales&lt;/em&gt;. Building products for customers is more about selling than creating. And most of sales is about listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listening is knowing you customer. It’s knowing what your customer wants and needs. Sometimes they will tell you that, but most often they won’t. Which is why matching that with a solution is so difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first arsenal in your sales toolkit is often just a value proposition. This can be as simple as a statement or visualization of your customer’s problem and your solution. Your value proposition is used anytime you are trying to sell yourself to a customer, investor, or anyone curious about your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, &lt;a href=&quot;www.basecamp.com&quot;&gt;Basecamp&lt;/a&gt; has a great value proposition statement. &lt;em&gt;All growing businesses run into the same fundamental problems. Hair on fire, buried under email, stuff everywhere. The good news? &lt;strong&gt;Basecamp solves them&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part is about articulating your customer problem - what is their painpoint, or what they want to accomplish with your product or service. A great framework for this is Jobs to be Done, which asks “what job is your customer hiring your product/service for?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part flows from the first - it’s a simple expression your solution in a way that it solves that customer problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some interesting ways of breaking this whole process down into vitamins and painkillers, and filling out a &lt;a href=&quot;https://isaacjeffries.com/blog/2018/2/27/how-to-fill-in-a-value-proposition-canvas&quot;&gt;value proposition canvas&lt;/a&gt;. All these are great techniques but the basics are pretty simple.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">These are notes for a talk I’ll be giving in a few weeks about Value Propositions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Machines will Run the Financial World</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190731/machines-will-run-the-financial-world.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Machines will Run the Financial World" /><published>2019-07-31T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-31T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190731/machines-will-run-the-financial-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190731/machines-will-run-the-financial-world.html">&lt;p&gt;Anthony Pompliano aka “Pomp” is a crypto investor and author of the prolific Off the Chain Substack and podcast. He recently wrote a post entitle &lt;a href=&quot;https://offthechain.substack.com/p/the-machines-will-run-the-financial&quot;&gt;The Machines will Run the Financial World&lt;/a&gt; about how all assets are being tokenized into currencies (many through blockchain but not all). This enables quicker transactions, T0 settlement times and a market that never closes. These efficiencies will change every asset class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I anticipate that the entire financial system will ultimately be automated. So while I consistently talk about Bitcoin and a decentralized digital currency, it is important to remember that the same disruption happening to money will happen to stocks, bonds, and commodities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great read.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Anthony Pompliano aka “Pomp” is a crypto investor and author of the prolific Off the Chain Substack and podcast. He recently wrote a post entitle The Machines will Run the Financial World about how all assets are being tokenized into currencies (many through blockchain but not all). This enables quicker transactions, T0 settlement times and a market that never closes. These efficiencies will change every asset class:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Minimum Viable Products</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190730/minimum-viable-products.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Minimum Viable Products" /><published>2019-07-30T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-30T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190730/minimum-viable-products</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190730/minimum-viable-products.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ll be giving a talk at Ryerson for a product management prep course, covering topics like Minimum Viable Products and Defining a Value Proposition. This post is an outline of the narrative of the first talk about MVPs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building anything is an investment - of time and capital. Investments are probabilistic - which means there is risk involved and a chance that things will fail. Startups in particular have a high failure rate - and over 40% fail because they built something no one cared about - there was no market need. Humans hate risk - it’s scary, but most importantly - failure sucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where MVPs come in. Minimum viable products are a framework for derisking investments. MVP’s came from the Lean Startup Movement created by Eric Ries as a framework for launching new startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The minimum viable product is that version of a new product which allows a team to collect the maximum amount of validated learning about customers with the least effort.” — Eric Ries&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An MVP is a way to test the water - a small investment that helps us justify the big investment. It’s a test, not necessarily the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly an MVP has to  be &lt;em&gt;viable&lt;/em&gt; and actually solve the original problem in some way. And that product can be anything - a landing page with a promise, a service provided, or something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MVP’s are about derisking, not eliminating all risk. Minimum viable products exist to help you test a hypothesis but you won’t know all the details until you actually launch. MVP’s can be applied to existing products too, not just new products. There are some examples of &lt;a href=&quot;https://speckyboy.com/successful-minimum-viable-products/&quot;&gt;successful MVP’s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software is getting easier to create. Risk to start is getting lower and it’s easier than ever to create a fully functional MVP especially with new tools and the rise of the No Code Movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the most successful companies in technology started as MVPs - I’m looking forward to seeing what these students create!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ll be giving a talk at Ryerson for a product management prep course, covering topics like Minimum Viable Products and Defining a Value Proposition. This post is an outline of the narrative of the first talk about MVPs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blackbox</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190729/blackbox.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blackbox" /><published>2019-07-29T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-29T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190729/blackbox</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190729/blackbox.html">&lt;p&gt;I made an angel investment recently in &lt;a href=&quot;www.blackboxai.tech&quot;&gt;Blackbox&lt;/a&gt;. They have built an incredible voice search engine and their demo  blew me away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blackbox is able to take thousands of hours of voice data and tokenize it, and then layered on a semantic search capability. In their demo, they used recorded podcasts, and I was able to ask it questions on the fly like “what do the best VCs look for in their investments?” - and it returned the exact snippets in the podcasts where that was answered. It was incredible and really demonstrates that we’re so early in realizing AI’s potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to supporting their journey.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I made an angel investment recently in Blackbox. They have built an incredible voice search engine and their demo blew me away.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Mirage of Cloud Gaming</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190728/cloud-based-gaming.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mirage of Cloud Gaming" /><published>2019-07-28T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-28T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190728/cloud-based-gaming</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190728/cloud-based-gaming.html">&lt;p&gt;This post is set of notes from &lt;a href=&quot;https://redef.com/original/how-cloud-gaming-will-and-wont-disrupt&quot;&gt;great article&lt;/a&gt; about the promise of cloud gaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cloud gaming is the new “thing” in the media industry. Whether it’s a game publisher or platform, there’s constant talk and even more ambition to be the so-called “Netflix of gaming”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Gaming’s reliance on technology platforms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This reliance has several interconnected consequences. First, gaming is more powerfully influenced by technology (and therefore technology change) than other categories. Put another way, business models and content flow more strongly from tech than to technology. Evidence of this is abundant; regardless of whether content or distribution is king, making games under the wrong technological premises will always come back to haunt you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On how new gaming platforms are not zero sum, vs. other forms of media like music.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://d2dpa77enk4uif.cloudfront.net/app/uploads/20190705200459/%40BallMatthew_Cloud11.png&quot; alt=&quot;Gaming Platforms&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On how new platforms and media types evolved together:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://d2dpa77enk4uif.cloudfront.net/app/uploads/20190705145635/%40BallMatthew_Cloud3.png&quot; alt=&quot;New Platforms&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This post is set of notes from great article about the promise of cloud gaming.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Noticing Anxiety</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190725/awareness.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Noticing Anxiety" /><published>2019-07-25T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-25T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190725/awareness</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190725/awareness.html">&lt;p&gt;Anxiety can be triggered by anything and it’s one of the most common mental health issues. I’ve found it takes a very intentional practice to deal with it as it comes up for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step to overcoming it is to simply notice when it’s happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found it useful to change the internal narrative from “I’m feeling anxious” to “I’m experiencing anxiety”. This detaches the feeling from your character. You don’t associate yourself as being anxious but recognize once in a while it invades your thought process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Anxiety can be triggered by anything and it’s one of the most common mental health issues. I’ve found it takes a very intentional practice to deal with it as it comes up for myself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Your Organization Needs a Learning Ecosystem</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190722/why-your-company-needs-a-learning-ecosystem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your Organization Needs a Learning Ecosystem" /><published>2019-07-22T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-22T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190722/why-your-company-needs-a-learning-ecosystem</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190722/why-your-company-needs-a-learning-ecosystem.html">&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2019/07/your-organization-needs-a-learning-ecosystem?utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_campaign=hbr&amp;amp;utm_source=linkedin&quot;&gt;excellent and timely article&lt;/a&gt; from HBR about how to build a &lt;em&gt;learning ecosystem&lt;/em&gt; in an organization, focusing on how redeploying people to new challenges can accelerate learning. Some notes from the article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the importance of learning in an organization:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Like a biological ecosystem, organizations are either growing or they’re dying. And organizations grow when their employees are learning. So if you want a high-growth organization, you need to create a learning ecosystem to support high-growth individuals — to expose them to new and challenging opportunities before their roles become stale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On redeployments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Companies need to see that a high-growth employee who loves to learn is a very valuable asset. Redeploying them on a new learning curve within the organization keeps their expertise in-house and allows them to share and build on it — a potentially exponential gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On other ways of promoting learning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Job swapping is only one strategy to put employees on new learning curves, help break down silos, and maximize shared organizational learning. Ongoing training and educational opportunities, job sharing, mentoring and outreach programs are a few other examples. You can get creative in how you mix things up, move people around, and offer employees new opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An excellent and timely article from HBR about how to build a learning ecosystem in an organization, focusing on how redeploying people to new challenges can accelerate learning. Some notes from the article:</summary></entry></feed>