<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-06T10:45:14-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Some Productivity Learnings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190905/productivity-lessons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Productivity Learnings" /><published>2019-09-05T12:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-05T12:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190905/productivity-lessons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190905/productivity-lessons.html">&lt;p&gt;I had a really great conversation today about managing time, and ended up going over some of my most important learnings about productivity over the last year. These are some of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with &lt;a href=&quot;/20180902/self-curiosity.html&quot;&gt;self curiosity&lt;/a&gt;. Try to understand your daily energy levels (what time of day you are most productive), and design your day around that. That will be a quick win that will help you understand how to replicate productive times throughout the day. I started this by &lt;a href=&quot;/20180918/time-tracking-update.html&quot;&gt;logging my time&lt;/a&gt; for an extended period to observe where it was being spent. Spend time to look back - I do &lt;a href=&quot;/20180911/productivity-planning-retros.html&quot;&gt;retrospectives&lt;/a&gt; on a regular basis to find patterns and ways I can improve. When you find out time is being spent in a way, or a time you don’t want it to - try to take it back. It’s yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving &lt;em&gt;yourself&lt;/em&gt; requires as much intention as improving &lt;em&gt;your work&lt;/em&gt;. Remember that you and your work are two separate things. Externalizing yourself from your work allows you to stay calm. A good tool is to understand the emotional triggers that lead you into time-consuming thought patterns (stress, intense excitement). I do this with an anxiety journal where I write down “what happened” and “how it made me feel”. The act of noting these triggers itself relieves stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By nature, this list will get better over time as I learn more about myself and what makes me productive and happy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I had a really great conversation today about managing time, and ended up going over some of my most important learnings about productivity over the last year. These are some of them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Thoughts on Marketplace Identity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190904/marketplace-identity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Thoughts on Marketplace Identity" /><published>2019-09-04T12:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-04T12:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190904/marketplace-identity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190904/marketplace-identity.html">&lt;p&gt;Marketplaces are a great place for consumers and producers to come together online. Across industries, dual-sided marketplaces have untapped latent demand or better utilized supply and created really interesting businesses along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As marketplaces grow, consumers come to expect the benefits of economies of scale - better selection, price and overall fulfillment experience. As producers become more savvy, they will want to exercise more control over the entire customer experience. Ultimately, as entrepreneurs, most of them will want to own that customer relationship themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This creates a choice that defines the identity the marketplace - to focus on building the largest end-customer base, or to focus on helping sellers become the most successful. There are of course examples where building for both can work for an extended period of time, but managing &lt;a href=&quot;/20190710/maintaining-equilibrium-marketplace-development.html&quot;&gt;equlibrium&lt;/a&gt; is incredibly difficult as marketplaces scale.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Marketplaces are a great place for consumers and producers to come together online. Across industries, dual-sided marketplaces have untapped latent demand or better utilized supply and created really interesting businesses along the way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Flywheels</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190903/why-flywheels.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Flywheels" /><published>2019-09-03T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-03T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190903/why-flywheels</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190903/why-flywheels.html">&lt;p&gt;Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://flywheels.substack.com/p/why-flywheels&quot;&gt;Flywheels&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funnel has been the dominant mental model to understand product performance for software startups. It was coined by Dave McClure of 500 Startups fame, and describes a customer journey through a product, from the channel they arrived to the point they start paying you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a lot of software, this experience encapsulated the user journey well enough, and funnels became the most common model to measure startup health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They highlight some important measures of success. The proportions of users that make it through each step, especially over a time-series, can give us a really good understanding of how well a specific part of the business is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that funnels are still an incomplete model. A funnel is simply one part of the flywheel,  and only operates in a single direction. We know how much things are happening, but don’t know why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more complete model for growing products is the &lt;em&gt;flywheel&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A flywheel is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cycle_graph#Directed_cycle_graph&quot;&gt;cyclical graph&lt;/a&gt;, where each node represents a key event or user action that drives the business forward. This makes them a more complete way of understanding how a business actually grows, by tying together the events that create continued usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best products create flywheel effects where the effects of one event can cause that event to happen again. For example, a user joining a social network might interact with some content and share it to someone outside the network, causing someone new to join the network, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a simple example but in reality, the nuanced events that drive businesses forward are pretty fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this newsletter I intend to explore fast growing businesses across industries, and also look at some already successful businesses retrospectively to examine how they grew through the lens of a flywheel.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Cross-posted from Flywheels.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A New Writing Project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190901/flywheels.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A New Writing Project" /><published>2019-09-01T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-01T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190901/flywheels</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190901/flywheels.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m starting another writing project - this one is a newsletter called Flywheels, and I will be hosting it on Substack. Flywheels is a weekly deep dive into a specific company and will analyse makes them grow. I’ll cover companies of all sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://flywheels.substack.com&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll post the free content from the newsletter on this blog as well (there will be some paid posts at some point). Subscribe if you’re interested!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m starting another writing project - this one is a newsletter called Flywheels, and I will be hosting it on Substack. Flywheels is a weekly deep dive into a specific company and will analyse makes them grow. I’ll cover companies of all sizes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Immigration</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190828/immigration.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Immigration" /><published>2019-08-28T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-28T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190828/immigration</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190828/immigration.html">&lt;p&gt;There’s been some uproar online about the People’s Party billboards that popped up in Toronto recently, decrying mass immigration. It’s disgusting but not surprising; Canada is not immune to blatant state-sponsored racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience is the immigrant experience, but probably not the typical one. I’ve gone through so many visas and statuses I’ve lost count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came to Canada in 1997 on a diplomatic visa, and started school at the University of Waterloo. I transferred to a student visa, and also did a number of co-op terms in the United States (on a J1 training visa) at Amazon.com in Seattle. I had all intentions of moving to the US. But, the visa for my last co-op term wasn’t granted because the Embassy deemed I had spent “too many terms” in the US, and needed to go back to my country of citizenship (India) to apply my training for atleast two years. That wasn’t an option, so I stayed in Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was 2003, and there weren’t too many tech companies around. I called and emailed over 250 companies in two weeks looking for a technical internship starting immediately. Only one company answered - Tira Wireless - and that’s where I worked for my last term and as my first full time job. At Tira, I moved from a work visa and started my application for permanent residence. I officially landed as an immigrant around 2009, and a citizen a few years later. In total, the nerve-wracking process took almost 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immigration is a tense process, and every step is a small win towards the life you want to live. It also creates loyalties around those that helped you along the way. Tira is no longer around, but I’ll always remember it as the company that supported and sponsored in this important transition in my life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There’s been some uproar online about the People’s Party billboards that popped up in Toronto recently, decrying mass immigration. It’s disgusting but not surprising; Canada is not immune to blatant state-sponsored racism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One Year Anniversary</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190827/one-year.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Year Anniversary" /><published>2019-08-27T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-27T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190827/one-year</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190827/one-year.html">&lt;p&gt;Today, one year ago, I &lt;a href=&quot;/20180827/starting-a-new-habit.html&quot;&gt;started a habit&lt;/a&gt; of writing [almost] everyday. This is post number 345.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve learned a lot about the topics I’ve explored, and a little about myself. What has surprised me is how useful this artifact has become in daily conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my favorite posts have been about leadership, societal trends, mental models, productivity, and investing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love writing here. It’s slowly becoming a stronger part of my identity, and I intend to continue for a while.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today, one year ago, I started a habit of writing [almost] everyday. This is post number 345.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Income Sharing Agreements (ISA’s)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190826/income-sharing-agreements.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Income Sharing Agreements (ISA's)" /><published>2019-08-26T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-26T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190826/income-sharing-agreements</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190826/income-sharing-agreements.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently subscribed to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://transcend.substack.com/&quot;&gt;Transcend Network substack&lt;/a&gt;. It’s an interesting newsletter about the future of education and work, and this week they posted an overview of Income Sharing Agreements, or ISA’s. These have become very popular and apparently 40% of the current crop of YC companies use some form of ISAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ISA’s are a simple funding agreement that provides upfront education (or payment of education fees), in return for a share of future employment income. Lambda School is an ISA that pays for coding school and asks students for their first paycheck of the tech job they landed. They are a great way to align incentives between students and those providing training. One of the reasons they are being used now is because of the global skills gap, which is especially pronounced in the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1100,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fceca7b05-f0a6-4df8-abf0-2d0b3548903b_432x327.png&quot; alt=&quot;ISA's Incentives&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about ISA’s on the Transcend Network’s newsletter &lt;a href=&quot;https://transcend.substack.com/p/a-slice-of-the-worlds-income-transcend&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently subscribed to the Transcend Network substack. It’s an interesting newsletter about the future of education and work, and this week they posted an overview of Income Sharing Agreements, or ISA’s. These have become very popular and apparently 40% of the current crop of YC companies use some form of ISAs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Purpose of a Corporation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190821/purpose-of-a-corporation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Purpose of a Corporation" /><published>2019-08-21T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190821/purpose-of-a-corporation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190821/purpose-of-a-corporation.html">&lt;p&gt;Since 1997, a group of CEO’s of the biggest American corporations have been getting together in an annual  Business Roundtable summit. In their most recent summit, they issued a startement committing to a new purpose of a corporation (since 1997, this has been to serve shareholders, and to maximize shareholder value). The new mandate includes this, but also some other &lt;a href=&quot;https://opportunity.businessroundtable.org/ourcommitment/&quot;&gt;committments&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Delivering value to our customers. We will further the tradition of American companies leading the way in meeting or exceeding customer expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Investing in our employees. This starts with compensating them fairly and providing important benefits. It also includes supporting them through training and education that help develop new skills for a rapidly changing world. We foster diversity and inclusion, dignity and respect.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Dealing fairly and ethically with our suppliers. We are dedicated to serving as good partners to the other companies, large and small, that help us meet our missions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Supporting the communities in which we work. We respect the people in our communities and protect the environment by embracing sustainable practices across our businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Generating long-term value for shareholders, who provide the capital that allows companies to invest, grow and innovate. We are committed to transparency and effective engagement with shareholders.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Each of our stakeholders is essential. We commit to deliver value to all of them, for the future success of our companies, our communities and our country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am immediately reminded of the &lt;a href=&quot;/20181020/leadership-lattice-simplified.html&quot;&gt;leadership lattice&lt;/a&gt; - a mental model for &lt;em&gt;how companies work&lt;/em&gt; and leader’s role within it. The lattice describes how leaders have to manage their attention towards individual growth, team productivity, the product of their effort, the extent of impact in their market, and the second order effects of that impact. This broader responsibility is reflected in this mandate as well with some level of committment from the CEO’s of these orgs. While it feels good to commit to this, it feels reactionary, a bit late, and I remain skeptical about it’s impact. I hope I’m wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Since 1997, a group of CEO’s of the biggest American corporations have been getting together in an annual Business Roundtable summit. In their most recent summit, they issued a startement committing to a new purpose of a corporation (since 1997, this has been to serve shareholders, and to maximize shareholder value). The new mandate includes this, but also some other committments:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The WeWork IPO</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190820/wework-ipo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The WeWork IPO" /><published>2019-08-20T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-20T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190820/wework-ipo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190820/wework-ipo.html">&lt;p&gt;Ben Thompson from Stratechery makes the bull case for the WeWork IPO, and compares it to the AWS business. Which I think is an apt analogy. It’s a first principles approach - think about the largest item on a startup financial statement and rent is probably high up there. WeWork turns a fixed cost into a variable expense based on usage, allowing startups to allocate their capital to what matters more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is nothing more fixed than real estate, yet WeWork’s offering transforms real estate into a variable cost for all kinds of companies, with benefits that roughly mirror public clouds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;New companies can have instant access to a well-appointed office space and pay for only a desk or two, and then grow as needed.
Growing companies do not need to spend time on extensive build-outs months or years ahead of future growth, and instead pay for more space as they need it.
Established companies no longer need to have a real estate competency all over the world, and can in fact expand to new territories with far less risk than previously required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really interesting take and could very well become true, but still a massive leap of faith. WeWork’s financial and operational red flags cannot be ignored. As Ben himself wrote, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stratechery.com/2019/why-wework-isnt-aws-and-the-ceo-problem-cloudflares-s-1-contrasting-s-1s/&quot;&gt;leadership matters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ben Thompson from Stratechery makes the bull case for the WeWork IPO, and compares it to the AWS business. Which I think is an apt analogy. It’s a first principles approach - think about the largest item on a startup financial statement and rent is probably high up there. WeWork turns a fixed cost into a variable expense based on usage, allowing startups to allocate their capital to what matters more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Marketplaces, Decentralization and Losing Trust (Part 2)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190819/marketplaces-decentralization-customers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marketplaces, Decentralization and Losing Trust (Part 2)" /><published>2019-08-19T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-19T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190819/marketplaces-decentralization-customers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190819/marketplaces-decentralization-customers.html">&lt;p&gt;This is the second in a series of posts about how decentralization takes place in marketplaces - through an erosion of trust in intermediaries. In my &lt;a href=&quot;/20190818/marketplaces-decentralization-trust-supply-side.html&quot;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt;, I examined how trust breaks down in suppliers and what that causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customers losing trust happens when the marketplace no longer offers the level of convenience (through price or selection), or doesn’t invest in improving the fulfillment experience of a product or service sold in the marketplace. This is generally a slower process - one bad experience will not mean a customer writes off the marketplaces; but over time dissatisfaction can compound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, supplier mistreatment creates a side effect of lost trust with customers. This is true especially in today’s ecosystem where customers are more discerning about the goods and services they consume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opportunity here is two sided. One is to provide customers with the same level of utility  when purchasing directly from multiple suppliers.  For example, discovery or managing your fulfillment  experience (e.g shipping tracking). If the friction or cost of switching is too high customers will likely stay with the central marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also opportunity in offering services that the central marketplace probably wouldn’t provide because it’s against their ethos or values, or goes against their core business model. For example, offering easy data portability is not in Facebooks interest. DuckDuckGo is a good example here but not “technically” a marketplace. Lyft is another one, in that their ethos is much more friendly and supportive to their drivers at a time when people are losing trust in Uber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customer trust is tricky. Gaining it takes time. Losing it starts slowly and then fast. It pays to be proactive about some issues. Centralized Marketplaces carry an additional burden that they have to manage both sides. Decentralized marketplaces become stronger as bad suppliers fail, and overall customer experience goes up. This makes them inherently antifragile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This is an evolving set of thoughts and will likely be updated over time).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is the second in a series of posts about how decentralization takes place in marketplaces - through an erosion of trust in intermediaries. In my first post, I examined how trust breaks down in suppliers and what that causes.</summary></entry></feed>