<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-17T10:10:29-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Some Thoughts on Risk</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190916/the-big-short-risk-investing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Thoughts on Risk" /><published>2019-09-16T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-16T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190916/the-big-short-risk-investing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190916/the-big-short-risk-investing.html">&lt;p&gt;The Big Short is one of my favorite movies. Such great storytelling about the different dimensions of the financial collapse in 2007, told through the lens of a prescient few that actually benefitted from the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It reminded me a bit of what’s going on in today’s economic environment where capital is at an all time high, reflected in frothy valuations across private and public markets. There are a lot of signals that the party is going to end soon, but who knows. I don’t have a crystal ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also made me think about the fragility of centralized institutions - corporations and governments alike. Businesses operate trying to maintaining an equilibrium between supply and demand to keep innovating. Governments feel permanent but are also just constructed institutions that have real flaws. Right now, many governments are waking up to a threat to their sovereignty that they have never dealt with before - delvaluation of their money due to decentralized cryptocurrencies. Libra has actually done them a favor in attaching a singular body to the face of global cryptocurrency, and governments around the world are now actively blocking it through regulation. Bitcoin, created over a decade ago, still grows strong because there isn’t any one target to block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, in the face of upcoming risk, the safest place to be is a place of &lt;em&gt;self awareness&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;self reliance&lt;/em&gt;, to a place of personal antifragility. We can weather any storm when our futures are not tied to those of a larger institution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Big Short is one of my favorite movies. Such great storytelling about the different dimensions of the financial collapse in 2007, told through the lens of a prescient few that actually benefitted from the crisis.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paper Secrets and Open Enterprises</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190915/paper-secrets-open-startups.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paper Secrets and Open Enterprises" /><published>2019-09-15T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-15T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190915/paper-secrets-open-startups</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190915/paper-secrets-open-startups.html">&lt;p&gt;A few disconnected throughts about the concept of company secrets and open startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies are sharing more than they ever have before. Companies are openly sharing their best practices. Open source is the foundation upon which startups today are built. Patents are somewhat irrelevant for software startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notion of “company secrets” is dated in the world of the open internet. I’ll go so far as to say companies often just hold &lt;em&gt;paper secrets&lt;/em&gt; protected by NDA’s that aren’t really enforcable. This includes everything from internal practices, technology to financial secrets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information flows freely in private and public channels. Infact, CEO’s are the new celebrities, openly talking about how their organizations work on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open startups have embraced this shift, infact using openness as an opportunity for increased accountability. There is more benefit from being open than not, and open can even become a competitive advantage when it’s compounded over time. I think of companies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.basecamp.com&quot;&gt;Basecamp&lt;/a&gt; - built on open source technology they founded, and to this day actively sharing their best practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funny thing is, enterprise software hasn’t modelled this construct just yet, or atleast at scale. Slack is doing this this with shared channels, but for some reason that hasn’t really taken off. Creating an environment of learning together, especially between trusted organizations, I believe is a powerful one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A few disconnected throughts about the concept of company secrets and open startups.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Grouped Future</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190914/our-grouped-future.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Grouped Future" /><published>2019-09-14T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-14T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190914/our-grouped-future</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190914/our-grouped-future.html">&lt;p&gt;A16 recently published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/09/06/china-is-cashing-in-on-group-chats/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on how Chinese companies are using group chat interfaces for everything from customer service, education, commerce and travel. It makes a lot of sense. Group chats are often trusted digital spaces full of high-intent users, often because they self select to become a part of the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;From chatbots to shopping via smart speaker, previous modes of conversational commerce have largely failed to live up to the hype in the US. But perhaps the reason is not that we are still waiting for next-generation technology; rather, we’ve been viewing commerce too narrowly, as an individual experience. Group chats set up by businesses don’t have to feel transactional; to users, such chats can feel more like interest groups than one-on-one sales pitches. They can provide community and crowdsourced knowledge in an organic way while simultaneously helping the brand behind them build trust and sell products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group chats are already huge in India. Whatsapp has optimized for communication to flow between group chats - accelerated by a very prominent “forward” button on images and video. Information spreads between groups so things can spread exponentially faster than individual sharing. This has some clear downfalls, especially when political and medical misinformation is spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groups are the primary construct in which people socialize in a mobile-first world, and I think it’s only a matter of time until major platforms open up a bit more to allow for some innovation in these spaces.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A16 recently published a post on how Chinese companies are using group chat interfaces for everything from customer service, education, commerce and travel. It makes a lot of sense. Group chats are often trusted digital spaces full of high-intent users, often because they self select to become a part of the group.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Rule of 40</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190913/the-rule-of-40.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rule of 40" /><published>2019-09-13T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-13T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190913/the-rule-of-40</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190913/the-rule-of-40.html">&lt;p&gt;I was recently reminded of the Rule of 40 for growing SaaS businesses (coined by Brad Feld in &lt;a href=&quot;https://feld.com/archives/2015/02/rule-40-healthy-saas-company.html&quot;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;), which states that the sum of a business growth rate and it’s profit margin should equal to approximately 40%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if a business is growing at 20% (assuming YoY), it should generate 20% of profit. If you are growing at 100% assuming YoY, you can stand to &lt;em&gt;lose&lt;/em&gt; 60% and still be considered “healthy”. This is simply a benchmark but is a good one to resolve growth vs. profitability decisions. Growth rates can also be benchmarked based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2015/02/01/the-saas-travel-adventure/&quot;&gt;T2D3 framework&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth and profit seldom grow in unison because companies do things that move one forward and strain the other, so having a simple to understand rule to maintain balance is very useful.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I was recently reminded of the Rule of 40 for growing SaaS businesses (coined by Brad Feld in this blog post), which states that the sum of a business growth rate and it’s profit margin should equal to approximately 40%.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Losing Focus</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190912/losing-focus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Losing Focus" /><published>2019-09-12T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-12T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190912/losing-focus</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190912/losing-focus.html">&lt;p&gt;“It is incredibly easy to lose focus”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend told me this yesterday; it resonated a lot. It made me think about focus through the lens of inversion. There are a lot of tools and frameworks avaialable for people to maintain focus. But, “keeping focus” is like a goal that you’re always fighting against. It sounds obvious, but anytime you &lt;em&gt;lose focus&lt;/em&gt;, you’ve lost in your battle to &lt;em&gt;keep it&lt;/em&gt;. So it demotivates you, and makes you feel like distraction is a part of your identity versus something that you simply experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, instead of trying to keep focus, just try to note when you’ve lost it. And when you do, bring it back to whatever you were working on last. The ability to note your distraction and come back to the task at hand is like a muscle - it will become stronger over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, you will also understand the &lt;em&gt;triggers&lt;/em&gt; that lead to distractive patterns. The best way to keep focus is then to avoid those triggers - something that is more actionable than simply trying to “keep focus”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“It is incredibly easy to lose focus”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Incomplete Financial Products</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190911/flexible-financial-products.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Incomplete Financial Products" /><published>2019-09-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190911/flexible-financial-products</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190911/flexible-financial-products.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bradmillscan/status/1171494009228812289&quot;&gt;this thread on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; about the banking experience for an elderly gentleman in Canada. It’s frankly horrific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The financial product landscape is monopolized by banks, which wouldn’t be a bad thing if there was a greater range of  products available. There are so many segments of the population that have unique problems that are not being served by existing products. This is true especially in Canada which is a very multicultural society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a more customer centric approach to banking and looking at the unique needs of these segments - the elderly, immigrants, caregivers - are paramount to creating a better banking experience. Whether it’s loan products with friendlier terms, financing for those taking care of their parents, appealing to those that have a cultural inhibition to debt - all of these things are not being addressed through the current product suite across banks. They have taken a bank-centric vs. customer centric approach, and it shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a problem and a huge opportunity. Thankfully, this is a known problem and many fintech companies (the entire industry, arguably) are actively working on solutions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently read this thread on Twitter about the banking experience for an elderly gentleman in Canada. It’s frankly horrific.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">9/11</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190911/nine-eleven.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="9/11" /><published>2019-09-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190911/nine-eleven</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190911/nine-eleven.html">&lt;p&gt;Eighteen years ago today, the world changed when the Twin Towers collapsed. It’s one of those &lt;em&gt;where were you when it happened&lt;/em&gt; moments. This is my story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in Seattle and it was the second day of an internship at Amazon.com. It was 2001 and I was working on the [tiny] mobile team. A friend generously lent me a space on their couch while I looked for an apartment, so I was sleeping on the couch when my friend woke me and turned on the TV. As the events were still unfolding, many major cities like Seattle were on high alert and were evacuating their skyscrapers. We actually went in to work, but then rushed back home. We were warned that being in a highrise wasn’t safe. It was a real and unforgettable fear. It was what I felt during scud missile attacks during the first Gulf War in Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also a time that brought people together. Strangers became family and friends, collectively supporting each other over the next few hours and days. I’m sure many of those bonds still last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans are capable of infinite love and hate. In a strange way, both were on display that day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Eighteen years ago today, the world changed when the Twin Towers collapsed. It’s one of those where were you when it happened moments. This is my story.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Notes on Culture and Decision Making</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190910/notes-on-culture.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Notes on Culture and Decision Making" /><published>2019-09-10T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-10T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190910/notes-on-culture</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190910/notes-on-culture.html">&lt;p&gt;Companies are complex systems. We create abstractions to simplify working within them. For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Strategy” is an abstraction for the collective of short and long term decisions to win in a market. 
“Operations” is an abstraction for the sum of working norms in place towards some enterprise output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s “Culture”, probably the most misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture is an abstraction for the sum of all interactions between people in an organization. Often articulated as a set of “Values”, this encompasses everything from everyday decision making to creating a sense of belonging and psychological safety. The broadest definition of culture is all-encompassing, and that’s perhaps why it’s interpreted in so many ways across companies. Today, it’s normal to see a company culture&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I read a really good blog post by Casey Winters, CPO at Eventbrite, who wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;https://caseyaccidental.com/cultural-values/&quot;&gt;cultural values&lt;/a&gt;. In it, he describes how cultural values are better described on a &lt;em&gt;spectrum&lt;/em&gt; rather than on their own. For example, on the spectrum of speed vs. quality, Facebook encourages it’s employees to bias towards speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much of culture is reflected in decision making, which in itself is an exercise in evaluating trade-offs. Cultural values should be clear about those trade-offs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Companies are complex systems. We create abstractions to simplify working within them. For example,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Notes on Fintech</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190909/fintech-growth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Notes on Fintech" /><published>2019-09-09T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-09T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190909/fintech-growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190909/fintech-growth.html">&lt;p&gt;Some thoughts about common growth and expansion vectors for Fintech startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first direction is horizontal expansion to offer more financial products (e.g. insurances, mortgages, loans, etc). This is the most common approach. Investment service providers expand to offer different savings and investment products. A good example is Wealthfront - known for it’s investment platform, which also now offers bridge loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second vector is verticalization, i.e. to own more of the customer experience upto the point of creating financial products. This applies to fintech’s that are mostly discovery / referral businesses. Verticalization means owning the application process and providing the financial product itself (i.e. a loan or insurance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of the above approaches lead to a fintech turning into a neo-bank (a digital native financial service provider).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third vector is geographic expansion. This approach requires an investment in regulatory compliance but is a relatively smaller investment than a bank establishing branches overseas. This is less common but there are some good examples of this - Wealthsimple in Canada operates in the US and UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three examples have a common thread - take a digital first, customer driven approach to financial services and compete on &lt;em&gt;simplicity&lt;/em&gt; to get the financial products.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Some thoughts about common growth and expansion vectors for Fintech startups.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Travel Decentralized</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190908/travel-decentralized.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Travel Decentralized" /><published>2019-09-08T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-08T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190908/travel-decentralized</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190908/travel-decentralized.html">&lt;p&gt;I live to travel. I love that tech has made it easy to experience the world, whether its through instant online booking, social recommendations or home-sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the convenience is great, I do miss parts of the travel agent experience. I miss the ability to contact someone that understands your travel preference, can find you things you might not have been looking for, and make the process of travel planning more fun than work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What tech has done is taken a fragmented supply (flights, hotels, etc) and make it really easy for the customer to make the best choices at the cheapest cost. In similar ways to other marketplaces, those suppliers now depend on travel bookings by these sites and advertise good reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I wonder if there’s a need for a product to help those travel agents become more successful, and to help people &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; travel agents. I have friends with amazing taste that refer people to travel destinations without participating in any upside for that referral. It would be really interesting to see a product that helps them participate in that; I think it’s worth it for all sides involved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I live to travel. I love that tech has made it easy to experience the world, whether its through instant online booking, social recommendations or home-sharing.</summary></entry></feed>