<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-05-27T23:59:10-04:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Why Not Us?</title><link href="/20190523/raptors.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Not Us?" /><published>2019-05-23T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-23T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20190523/raptors</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20190523/raptors.html">&lt;p&gt;The Toronto Raptors made the NBA finals for the first time in it’s 25 year history, defeating the Milwaukee Bucks 100-94 in Game 6 of the Eastern Conference Finals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s very little else on my mind. But more than the game, it’s this question. Why &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not Toronto? Why not the Raptors? Why do we carry a collective impostor syndrome that tells us - we’re good, but not &lt;em&gt;good enough&lt;/em&gt; for that ultimate title. It can feel undeserved; unattainable. It’s also bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not us? There’s no reason. It’s time to get our mental stigmas out of our own way - and show the world what we’re capable of. Let’s go, Raptors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Toronto Raptors made the NBA finals for the first time in it’s 25 year history, defeating the Milwaukee Bucks 100-94 in Game 6 of the Eastern Conference Finals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Potential of Interactive Entertainment</title><link href="/20190523/easports-interactivity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Potential of Interactive Entertainment" /><published>2019-05-23T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-23T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20190523/easports-interactivity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20190523/easports-interactivity.html">Laura Miele, Chief Studios Officer at Electronic Arts spoke today at Collision about the power of gaming. She emphasized how interactive entertainment creates environments of collaboration and collective problem solving. It was a great talk and speaks a lot to the vision that we're building for Tap by Wattpad. 

{% include youtube.html youtube_id=&quot;CFP_6tGvKHY&quot; %}

Starts at about 1hr 5m from the beginning of the Livestream.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Laura Miele, Chief Studios Officer at Electronic Arts spoke today at Collision about the power of gaming. She emphasized how interactive entertainment creates environments of collaboration and collective problem solving. It was a great talk and speaks a lot to the vision that we’re building for Tap by Wattpad.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Ivy Lee Method</title><link href="/20190522/ivy-lee.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Ivy Lee Method" /><published>2019-05-22T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-22T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20190522/ivy-lee</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20190522/ivy-lee.html">Today I learned of a simple productivity technique called the [Ivy Lee method](https://jamesclear.com/ivy-lee), created in 2018 but still relevant.

&gt; 1. At the end of each work day, write down the six most important things you need to accomplish tomorrow. Do not write down more than six tasks.
&gt; 2. Prioritize those six items in order of their true importance.
&gt; 3. When you arrive tomorrow, concentrate only on the first task. Work until the first task is finished before moving on to the second task.
&gt; 4. Approach the rest of your list in the same fashion. At the end of the day, move any unfinished items to a new list of six tasks for the following day.
&gt; 5. Repeat this process every working day.

There's an app that makes this easier, appropriately named [Ivy](https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ivy-stress-free-to-do-lists/id1458049415?ls=1&amp;mt=8). I really appreciate the retrospective graphs. A few months ago I started using a simpler productivity system - weekly planning and retrospectives. For the latter, I look at what I accomplished vs. what I committed to. Retrospectives highlight my mistakes, which I try to avoid in my next round of planning.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today I learned of a simple productivity technique called the Ivy Lee method, created in 2018 but still relevant.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Collision Day 1 Retrospective</title><link href="/20190521/collision-day-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Collision Day 1 Retrospective" /><published>2019-05-21T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-21T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20190521/collision-day-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20190521/collision-day-1.html">Today was the first day of Collision. There was so much happening on the floor, and it was really great to see Toronto as the centre of the Tech universe. 

Here are some general themes I noticed:
- Tech is dealing with Trust issues. More so, the lack thereof. Companies are operating in environments where trust is no longer implied but an earned currency. This came up in many contexts - discussions about social media companies and their role in distributing trusted news, or millennials relationship with traditional banks. Also amongst ourselves in the tech community- especially towards the central powers of FANG. 
- Workforces on demand especially for engineering talent. Hiring is the biggest issue facing most startups and can be the main reason why many don't get off the ground. There are a number of startups solving this problem especially for the early stage of shipping a V1. 
- Technology and higher order problems. I'm biased because I'm also interested in this space. I saw a number of really interesting startups on the floor working on a range of solutions to psychological and social issues - everything from mental health to creating empathy through software. 

I was overwhelmed with the first day, perhaps because I was surprised at how much is happening. I'm looking forward to seeing what themes emerge in the next few days.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today was the first day of Collision. There was so much happening on the floor, and it was really great to see Toronto as the centre of the Tech universe.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting Investor Behaviour</title><link href="/20190520/predicting-investor-behaviour-investopedia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting Investor Behaviour" /><published>2019-05-20T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-20T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20190520/predicting-investor-behaviour-investopedia</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20190520/predicting-investor-behaviour-investopedia.html">A really cool talk from the CEO of Investopedia about how they are able to predict market trends based on search behaviour. It highlights a few things:

* Most investors are newbies and rely on sites like Investopedia regularly
* Most investors over follow the market and make short term decisions for quick rewards (not a good move)
* Understanding investor intent is the strongest leading indicator of investment. Investopedia is a great source of this information. 

{% include youtube.html youtube_id=&quot;Dq6LzLWtq7U&quot; %}

I'm still looking for the slide deck that was being presented - will update this post when I find it.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A really cool talk from the CEO of Investopedia about how they are able to predict market trends based on search behaviour. It highlights a few things:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Game of Thrones</title><link href="/20190519/game-of-thrones.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Game of Thrones" /><published>2019-05-19T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-19T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20190519/game-of-thrones</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20190519/game-of-thrones.html">After 8 seasons, Game of Thrones is over. It was the most successful show in television history. Some facts from [Wikipedia](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Game_of_Thrones):

- The series premiered on HBO in the United States on April 17, 2011, and concluded on May 19, 2019, with 73 episodes broadcast over eight seasons.
- The series has received 47 Primetime Emmy Awards, the most by a drama series, including Outstanding Drama Series in 2015, 2016, and 2018.
- The first season averaged 9.3 million viewers per episode. By season 7 it was 32.8 million. Season 8 numbers aren't out yet but I wouldn't be surprised if it touched 40M or more. 

GoT was a cultural phenomenon by all measures. It's the kind of story universe that can turn into books, TV shows, movies and amusement parks. The show might be done but I don't think we're done with these characters just yet.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">After 8 seasons, Game of Thrones is over. It was the most successful show in television history. Some facts from Wikipedia:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How We Got Here</title><link href="/20190518/how-we-got-here.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How We Got Here" /><published>2019-05-18T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-18T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20190518/how-we-got-here</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20190518/how-we-got-here.html">I was talking to someone recently about Facebook and responsible technology. More specifically, what led to Facebook being weaponized for all sorts of bad things. 

Besides the specifics of the Facebook situation, I believe it comes down to a few broader factors.

Software is _different_ than most technology. We need to recognize software has almost unlimited surface area - which explains how it's &quot;eating the world&quot;. Software, especially internet software, has almost infinite leverage. A piece of code written in a basement can produce real world outcomes across the globe.

Second, there are no real regulations on what is allowed vs not. It was hard to think of the potential of internet software, let alone how to prevent any bad actors. 

Third, 'irresponsible' progress continues to be celebrated. Whether it's blitzscaling, ignoring local laws, or simply moving fast and breaking things - the technology industry wears irresponsibility as a badge of honor. Without any regulation, decisions are made with a singular lens.

I think we're only starting to see the downsides of not building software responsibly, and there doesn't seem to be a widely held solution yet.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I was talking to someone recently about Facebook and responsible technology. More specifically, what led to Facebook being weaponized for all sorts of bad things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sunshine</title><link href="/20190517/sunshine.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sunshine" /><published>2019-05-17T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-17T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20190517/sunshine</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20190517/sunshine.html">The weather has finally turned a corner. The sun is shining in Toronto after the longest winter in recent history (this might not be true but it really felt like it). 

So much changes when the sun is out. Optimism abounds. Problems solve themselves. A simple walk can change everything.

Like many others, I'm feeling thankful and looking forward to the summer.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The weather has finally turned a corner. The sun is shining in Toronto after the longest winter in recent history (this might not be true but it really felt like it).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Complete Guide to Deep Work</title><link href="/20190516/complete-guide-to-deep-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Complete Guide to Deep Work" /><published>2019-05-16T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-16T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20190516/complete-guide-to-deep-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20190516/complete-guide-to-deep-work.html">The Doist published an excellent [guide to Deep Work](https://doist.com/blog/complete-guide-to-deep-work/). It explains the concept and provides some real world strategies to create environments of deep work in your day. They focus on intentionality of the structure. In the section about [how to build a deep work routine](https://doist.com/blog/complete-guide-to-deep-work/#Build_a_Deep_Work_Routine), it mentions:

&gt; Practicing intention with your time and considering when you’ll fit in periods of focus is an important part of succeeding with a deep work habit.

The four elements of that are:
- **Location** - A space that's conducive to deep work
- **Duration** - A period of time that works for you (starting small then increasing over time as you build your &quot;deep work muscle&quot;)
- **Structure** - The rules for the session - whether its digital distractions or how you will measure success
- **Requirements** - What's required to help create the environment - music, food, etc. This will be learned over time.

Check out the whole guide [here](https://doist.com/blog/complete-guide-to-deep-work/).</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Doist published an excellent guide to Deep Work. It explains the concept and provides some real world strategies to create environments of deep work in your day. They focus on intentionality of the structure. In the section about how to build a deep work routine, it mentions:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finance for Immigrant Families</title><link href="/20190514/finance-for-immigrants.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finance for Immigrant Families" /><published>2019-05-14T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-14T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/20190514/finance-for-immigrants</id><content type="html" xml:base="/20190514/finance-for-immigrants.html">Every society and culture has unique norms and behaviour when it comes to money. When an individual or family migrates to a different country, they bring those mental models with them. This can include, for example, different expectations around loan repayment or how money is pooled in an atomic family. All aspects of personal finance are affected - earning, borrowing, budgeting, saving, investing, etc. 

Nowhere is this more pronounced than Canada - a country that is soon to be 50% immigrants in a few years. And yet, the financial products available to most Canadians are not geared  towards these unique needs. 

This becomes extra complicated with newer generations that are raised in Canada but also have cultural and familial obligations to fulfill.  

I think by considering the unique needs of immigrant families and cultures, financial service providers will benefit _everyone_. Sometimes it's just a  knowledge asymmetry. 

This is one of those areas where focusing on the minority improves the majority experience with a service.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Every society and culture has unique norms and behaviour when it comes to money. When an individual or family migrates to a different country, they bring those mental models with them. This can include, for example, different expectations around loan repayment or how money is pooled in an atomic family. All aspects of personal finance are affected - earning, borrowing, budgeting, saving, investing, etc.</summary></entry></feed>