<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-22T23:28:31-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Your Organization Needs a Learning Ecosystem</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190722/why-your-company-needs-a-learning-ecosystem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your Organization Needs a Learning Ecosystem" /><published>2019-07-22T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-22T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190722/why-your-company-needs-a-learning-ecosystem</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190722/why-your-company-needs-a-learning-ecosystem.html">&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2019/07/your-organization-needs-a-learning-ecosystem?utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_campaign=hbr&amp;amp;utm_source=linkedin&quot;&gt;excellent and timely article&lt;/a&gt; from HBR about how to build a &lt;em&gt;learning ecosystem&lt;/em&gt; in an organization, focusing on how redeploying people to new challenges can accelerate learning. Some notes from the article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the importance of learning in an organization:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Like a biological ecosystem, organizations are either growing or they’re dying. And organizations grow when their employees are learning. So if you want a high-growth organization, you need to create a learning ecosystem to support high-growth individuals — to expose them to new and challenging opportunities before their roles become stale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On redeployments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Companies need to see that a high-growth employee who loves to learn is a very valuable asset. Redeploying them on a new learning curve within the organization keeps their expertise in-house and allows them to share and build on it — a potentially exponential gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On other ways of promoting learning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Job swapping is only one strategy to put employees on new learning curves, help break down silos, and maximize shared organizational learning. Ongoing training and educational opportunities, job sharing, mentoring and outreach programs are a few other examples. You can get creative in how you mix things up, move people around, and offer employees new opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An excellent and timely article from HBR about how to build a learning ecosystem in an organization, focusing on how redeploying people to new challenges can accelerate learning. Some notes from the article:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sleep</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190721/sleep.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sleep" /><published>2019-07-21T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-21T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190721/sleep</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190721/sleep.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m not feeling great today, and need to rest. In that spirit I’m writing a very short post about the importance of sleep. I read recently that Sleep is the ultimate &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nootropic&quot;&gt;Nootropic&lt;/a&gt; - it just takes 8 hours to take effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the National Institute for Health:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Without sleep you can’t form or maintain the pathways in your brain that let you learn and create new memories, and it’s harder to concentrate and respond quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sleep is important to a number of brain functions, including how nerve cells (neurons) communicate with each other.  In fact, your brain and body stay remarkably active while you sleep.  Recent findings suggest that sleep plays a housekeeping role that removes toxins in your brain that build up while you are awake.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Everyone needs sleep, but its biological purpose remains a mystery.  Sleep affects almost every type of tissue and system in the body – from the brain, heart, and lungs to metabolism, immune function, mood, and disease resistance.  Research shows that a chronic lack of sleep, or getting poor quality sleep, increases the risk of disorders including high blood pressure, cardiovascular disease, diabetes, depression, and obesity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m not feeling great today, and need to rest. In that spirit I’m writing a very short post about the importance of sleep. I read recently that Sleep is the ultimate Nootropic - it just takes 8 hours to take effect.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paradigm Shifts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190717/paradigm-shifts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paradigm Shifts" /><published>2019-07-17T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-17T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190717/paradigm-shifts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190717/paradigm-shifts.html">&lt;p&gt;Ray Dalio penned another really great post about major paradigm shifts - going through each major decade since the 1920’s and then making some calls for what is ahead. He ends with an advisory note to buy gold as a way to hedge the upcoming risk vs equity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most people now believe the best “risky investments” will continue to be equity and equity-like investments, such as leveraged private equity, leveraged real estate, and venture capital, and this is especially true when central banks are reflating. As a result, the world is leveraged long, holding assets that have low real and nominal expected returns that are also providing historically low returns relative to cash returns (because of the enormous amount of money that has been pumped into the hands of investors by central banks and because of other economic forces that are making companies flush with cash). I think these are unlikely to be good real returning investments and that those that will most likely do best will be those that do well when the value of money is being depreciated and domestic and international conflicts are significant, such as gold. Additionally, for reasons I will explain in the near future, most investors are underweighted in such assets, meaning that if they just wanted to have a better balanced portfolio to reduce risk, they would have more of this sort of asset. For this reason, I believe that it would be both risk-reducing and return-enhancing to consider adding gold to one’s portfolio. I will soon send out an explanation of why I believe that gold is an effective portfolio diversifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check it out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/paradigm-shifts-ray-dalio&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ray Dalio penned another really great post about major paradigm shifts - going through each major decade since the 1920’s and then making some calls for what is ahead. He ends with an advisory note to buy gold as a way to hedge the upcoming risk vs equity.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Empowering Marketplace Suppliers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190716/empowering-creators.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Empowering Marketplace Suppliers" /><published>2019-07-16T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-16T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190716/empowering-creators</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190716/empowering-creators.html">&lt;p&gt;We had a really great discussion today about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.ca/Long-Tail-Future-Business-Selling/dp/1401309666&quot;&gt;The Long Tail&lt;/a&gt; at Wattpad’s monthly product book club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Long Tail argues that more value exists by aggregating all the small niches together than in the small group of hit products or content. By this theory Youtube ultimately has more lasting value than Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sparked another discussion on the different ways technology companies can play a role in aggregating the long tail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is driven by customer demand - in the case of content, this is driven by &lt;em&gt;what audiences want&lt;/em&gt;. This approach focuses on audience desires for free access, amazing discovery experiences and opportunities to connect with each other. There’s a network effect which improves recommendations that’s created when other audience members join. In this approach, the supply side - creators - often do whatever it takes to conform to what audiences want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is supply focused - to help every creator &lt;em&gt;become as successful as they can be&lt;/em&gt;. This is where the customer is the creator and the product is a set of utilities to help them build audiences and make money from their craft. In this world, creators are empowered to find the channels that work for them vs. being beholden to any one single channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both can yield massive amounts of enterprise value and can both help the Long Tail become successful, but are polar opposite in the type of businesses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We had a really great discussion today about The Long Tail at Wattpad’s monthly product book club.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building Learning Infrastructures at Startups</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190715/learning-infrastructures-at-startups.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building Learning Infrastructures at Startups" /><published>2019-07-15T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-15T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190715/learning-infrastructures-at-startups</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190715/learning-infrastructures-at-startups.html">&lt;p&gt;Given the massive disparity between easy access to capital and difficult access to amazing talent, startups - especially those in seed/series A stage - are in a desparate situation. They are losing talent to better funded startups and more established players, and at the same time fighting towards finding product market fit. Their only advantage - access to more stock options - is also getting weaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help startups stay competitive in the market, they need to offer something more. And I believe that comes in the form of an environment for fast paced learning. Ultimately, a startup is a learning machine, and an employee that enters a successful startup is guaranteed an opportunity to grow at a disproportionate rate than the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, setting up an infrastructure for learning at any company takes a lot of time. Learning management is a mature industry and there are a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.g2.com/categories/corporate-lms&quot;&gt;lot of competitors&lt;/a&gt;. And when a startup prioritizes learning, an LMS is often not the first solution. They do a few scattered things - setting a training budget, hiring coaches, using recommended vendors for workshops, and so on. None of these things are tracked with any meaningful ROI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, most of these infrastrctures do not account for the needs of modern knowledge workers - social learning opportunities, content delivered in super engaging ways, and the opportunity to raise their personal profile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a need in this market for a modern learning management system that turns every startup into a learning machine instantaneously - one that fosters learning communities, focuses on content optimised for comprehension (vs consumption).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Given the massive disparity between easy access to capital and difficult access to amazing talent, startups - especially those in seed/series A stage - are in a desparate situation. They are losing talent to better funded startups and more established players, and at the same time fighting towards finding product market fit. Their only advantage - access to more stock options - is also getting weaker.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Context Switching and Calendars</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190714/calendars-context-switching.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Context Switching and Calendars" /><published>2019-07-14T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-14T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190714/calendars-context-switching</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190714/calendars-context-switching.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve written about my frustration with mobile calendar apps before. The most annoying part of dealing with calendars on a mobile device is context switching between communication apps (chat, email) and calendars (for availability). It’s an experience that could be solved by integrating communication features like chat directly within a calendar app itself. Every event would open to a chat message between attendees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would do a number of things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chat and email would be freed of the clutter of coordination messages. The back and forth to coordinate events is a huge reason events don’t happen at all. This friction is bad enough that it prevents real world social interaction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would be easier to refer back to conversations and documents related to the event itself, and create a forum to review/rate event.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would give calendars a natural network effect - more people on this app would add value to everyone else on the platform in your social circle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calendars are an inherently social product that we are all forced to play in single player mode - just because of lack of options. Hoping this changes soon and Google/Apple fixes this problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve written about my frustration with mobile calendar apps before. The most annoying part of dealing with calendars on a mobile device is context switching between communication apps (chat, email) and calendars (for availability). It’s an experience that could be solved by integrating communication features like chat directly within a calendar app itself. Every event would open to a chat message between attendees.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Travel</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190713/travel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Travel" /><published>2019-07-13T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-13T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190713/travel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190713/travel.html">&lt;p&gt;Travel has always been a part of my personal narrative. I lived around the world up until high school - spending three years a piece in Denmark, Malawi, Saudi Arabia, India and The Philippines. In 1997 I finally settled in Toronto - the most multicultural city in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parenting takes you back to your own childhood, and I’ve often thought how I would even come close to recreating this experience for our family. Relocation seems like such a momentous challenge of finding a new home, livelihood and social support system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, what if that process wasn’t so difficult? What if you could painlessly coordinate the entire process of finding a new home and job in a new country, and connect with like minded people to build a support system? This sounds like ultra fringe behaviour but we all have friends that have moved to a different country just to experience a different life for a few years. It could become more normal much the same way renting your house to strangers is on Airbnb, or getting into a strangers car on Lyft or Uber. I’d like to imagine a future in which this is possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Travel has always been a part of my personal narrative. I lived around the world up until high school - spending three years a piece in Denmark, Malawi, Saudi Arabia, India and The Philippines. In 1997 I finally settled in Toronto - the most multicultural city in the world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Solar</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190712/solar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Solar" /><published>2019-07-12T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-12T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190712/solar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190712/solar.html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2019/07/giant-batteries-and-cheap-solar-power-are-shoving-fossil-fuels-grid&quot;&gt;Science Mag&lt;/a&gt; on the progress of solar technology:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This month, officials in Los Angeles, California, are expected to approve a deal that would make solar power cheaper than ever while also addressing its chief flaw: It works only when the sun shines. The deal calls for a huge solar farm backed up by one of the world’s largest batteries. It would provide 7% of the city’s electricity beginning in 2023 at a cost of 1.997 cents per kilowatt hour (kWh) for the solar power and 1.3 cents per kWh for the battery. That’s cheaper than any power generated with fossil fuel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the power of technology cost curves. Incremental improvements slowly drive down costs of new technology - often while incumbents write off new entrants as not being good/fast/cheap enough. Soon after better tech becomes &lt;em&gt;cheaper&lt;/em&gt; than the alternative, change happens fast and incumbents get displaced.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">From Science Mag on the progress of solar technology:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No Coders</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190711/nocoders.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Coders" /><published>2019-07-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190711/nocoders</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190711/nocoders.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nocode.tech/&quot;&gt;‘No Code’&lt;/a&gt; is a movement that enables non-technical entrepreneurs to create real, working digital products. Tools to do this include Shopify, Webflow, Carrd, Glitch and many others. A great starting point for understanding the movement is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.makerpad.co/&quot;&gt;Makerpad&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As web and mobile products become easier to build, we’re about to see a massive increase in the top of the funnel for new products being created. This inflection means more innovate products in market, but a proportional increase in competition. No code tools are also helping designers and developers collaborate and share common mental models and tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an exciting wave of growth that can be as powerful as the appstores themselves and will likely create many more digital entrepreneurs along the way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">‘No Code’ is a movement that enables non-technical entrepreneurs to create real, working digital products. Tools to do this include Shopify, Webflow, Carrd, Glitch and many others. A great starting point for understanding the movement is Makerpad.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Shape Up</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190710/shape-up.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shape Up" /><published>2019-07-10T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-10T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190710/shape-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190710/shape-up.html">&lt;p&gt;Another book from the crew at Basecamp - this one called &lt;a href=&quot;https://basecamp.com/shapeup/&quot;&gt;Shape Up&lt;/a&gt;, and details their development process with illustrations. They introduced some concepts in &lt;a href=&quot;https://basecamp.com/books/calm&quot;&gt;It doesn’t have to be crazy at work&lt;/a&gt;, especially that of the 6-week project limit. I would call this the most &lt;em&gt;Rails&lt;/em&gt; approach to project management - eschewing complexity and reinforcing simple conventions in process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a quick and impactful read.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Another book from the crew at Basecamp - this one called Shape Up, and details their development process with illustrations. They introduced some concepts in It doesn’t have to be crazy at work, especially that of the 6-week project limit. I would call this the most Rails approach to project management - eschewing complexity and reinforcing simple conventions in process.</summary></entry></feed>