<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-17T23:41:53-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Fifth Discipline</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190617/revisiting-the-fifth-discipline.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fifth Discipline" /><published>2019-06-17T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-17T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190617/revisiting-the-fifth-discipline</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190617/revisiting-the-fifth-discipline.html">&lt;p&gt;The Fifth Discipline is one of my favorite leadership books. I’ll be coordinating a discussion on the book tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some disconnected notes on the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A learning organization is committed to self betterment and adaptiveness to change. This makes it naturally resillient and likely to last longer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A shared vision is developed together. Magic happens when you can connect someone’s personal vision to one that the company needs. It creates a natural flow that is impossible to do if leadership is inflexible about the vision. People who do not share the same vision might not contribute as much to the organization.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Systems thinking helps to connect everything together. I’ve used this in the past in the development of the leadership lattice - a framework of how companies work that highlights how everything is connected to each other.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Team Learning is a form of flow. When a team is focused on the same things and is consistently readjusting itself through instrospection and intelligent dialogue, it can create powerful business results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal mastery requires some level of introspection, but cannot be forced. It must be led by example and through creating environments of psychological safety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Fifth Discipline is one of my favorite leadership books. I’ll be coordinating a discussion on the book tomorrow.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Score Takes Care of Itself</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190616/the-score-takes-care-of-itself.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Score Takes Care of Itself" /><published>2019-06-16T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-16T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190616/the-score-takes-care-of-itself</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190616/the-score-takes-care-of-itself.html">&lt;p&gt;Recently read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sachinrekhi.com/bill-walsh-the-score-takes-care-of-itself&quot;&gt;What Silicon Valley Can Learn From Bill Walsh’s The Score Takes Care of Itself&lt;/a&gt;. Lots of great takeaways, for example this one on OKR’s and goalsetting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But what Bill Walsh correctly points out is that the ultimate outcome metric that you are so focused on in your OKRs is not in-fact in your control. Many of the inputs to that outcome are in your control. But certainly not the outcome itself. And so what Bill is saying is that an over-fixation on that outcome metric actually doesn’t help you get there. You should instead focus on the part that you can control. And when you do this well, the score (the ultimate outcome metric you care about) takes care of itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This illustrates Bill Walsh’s style to focus on the inputs (what you can directly control) vs. outputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you start to put these elements of Bill’s leadership style together, you start to see how it differs from the conventional wisdom. Bill encourages you to focus on the inputs and the process instead of the ultimate outcomes as the outcomes are not in your control. Bill expects leaders to be functional experts in the roles on their team in order to develop the Standard of Performance. These leaders are not just people managers. They are the very best at what they do. And they develop a powerful system, via the Standard of Performance and a passion for teaching, of inculcating their team to make them the very best at their roles. But unlike the benevolent dictator model, Bill certainly doesn’t encourage you to call all the shots yourself. But instead to build up the team and the team culture to be able to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Recently read What Silicon Valley Can Learn From Bill Walsh’s The Score Takes Care of Itself. Lots of great takeaways, for example this one on OKR’s and goalsetting:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">History</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190614/history.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="History" /><published>2019-06-14T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-14T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190614/history</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190614/history.html">&lt;p&gt;History made. Still don’t know what to say, so I’ll just leave this here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/N7z6ukP.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Freddie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">History made. Still don’t know what to say, so I’ll just leave this here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Game 6</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190613/game-6.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Game 6" /><published>2019-06-13T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-13T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190613/game-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190613/game-6.html">&lt;p&gt;2 minutes left in the 3rd. We could be one quarter away from a championship. I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can barely think straight and wanted to capture this moment. Half of me wants to scream; the other half just wants to take a nap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UPDATE: We won. Going to scream in the streets for a few hours.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">2 minutes left in the 3rd. We could be one quarter away from a championship. I don’t know.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Five Lessons from History</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190611/five-lessons-from-history.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five Lessons from History" /><published>2019-06-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190611/five-lessons-from-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190611/five-lessons-from-history.html">&lt;p&gt;Pretty great &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/five-lessons-from-history/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; from Morgan Housel on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/authors/morgan/&quot;&gt;Collaborative Fund blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The most important lessons from history are the takeaways that are so broad they can apply to other fields, other eras, and other people. That’s where lessons have leverage and are most likely to apply to your own life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the my takeaways and favorite snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesson 1: Everyone has a plan until they get punched in the face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People suffering from sudden, unexpected hardship are likely to adopt views they previously thought unthinkable … Hard times make people do and think things they’d never imagine when things are calm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesson 2: It takes a special kind of crazy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reversion to the mean occurs because people persuasive enough to make something grow don’t have the kind of personalities that allow them to stop before pushing too far … Being right is the enemy of staying right because it leads you to forget the way the world works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesson 3: Things sometimes look like they’re getting better when they’re actually getting worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unsustainable things can last longer than you anticipate. Identifying that something is unsustainable does not provide much information on when that thing will stop. This happens because of incentives and storytelling. Incentives are often tied to maintaining only one part of a system, not a whole system (see: ratings agencies, mortgage brokers during credit crisis). Storytelling because if enough people believe something is true, unsustainable ideas can gain durable life support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesson 4: Progress happens too slowly for people to notice; setbacks happen too fast for people to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The irony is that growth – if you can stick around – is a more powerful force, because it compounds. But setbacks capture greater attention because they happen suddenly … Understanding the speed differences between growth and loss explains a lot of things, from why pessimism is seductive to why long-term thinking is so hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesson 5: Wounds heal, scars last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Those who survive calamities – an important distinction – have a remarkable ability to adapt and rebuild. It’s often far greater than you expect it to be at the end of the calamity. But there’s a big difference between a wound healing and a scar remaining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We can see and measure just about everything in the world except people’s moods, fears, hopes, grudges, goals, triggers, and expectations. That’s partly why history is such a continuous chain of baffling events, and always will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Pretty great post from Morgan Housel on the Collaborative Fund blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deflation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190610/deflation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deflation" /><published>2019-06-10T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-10T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190610/deflation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190610/deflation.html">&lt;p&gt;One point. What an insane game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much anticipation and energy carried us to this point; the city was ready for a celebration. It feels like someone took the ground beneath us, but we’re still floating waiting for the drop. I feel deflated, and need to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good things don’t come easy, definitely not for Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3-2, heads held high, ready for the next one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">One point. What an insane game.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Not-To-Do List</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190609/to-not-do-lists.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Not-To-Do List" /><published>2019-06-09T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-09T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190609/to-not-do-lists</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190609/to-not-do-lists.html">&lt;p&gt;Inversion applies well to the productivity problem. Instead of asking what to do to be more productive, look for what is making you unproductive, and solve those problems. In my case, it’s the amount and broad range of commitments not tied to my immediate goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this week I’m forgoing my to-do list for a “not-to-do” list. A list of commitments to cancel, meetings I won’t attend, and conversations I no longer need to continue. Also - a reminder that I should &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; be committing to these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I should be doing more often, but I have a backlog I need to clear. It’s time to free up time to focus on what’s most important and start saying no more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Inversion applies well to the productivity problem. Instead of asking what to do to be more productive, look for what is making you unproductive, and solve those problems. In my case, it’s the amount and broad range of commitments not tied to my immediate goals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning Infrastructures at a Startup</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190608/learning-infrastructures.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning Infrastructures at a Startup" /><published>2019-06-08T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-08T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190608/learning-infrastructures</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190608/learning-infrastructures.html">&lt;p&gt;A few unstructured notes on learning in startups today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Companies today have to accept a broader responsibility to develop their people in order to stay competitive in the market. This has always been true in a sense, but more pronounced in today’s hiring environment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acquiring and retaining talent is the single most important issue for most startups. But, most HR teams are consumed the former (acquisition).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The opportunity for continual growth is the most common reason why people join, stay or leave a company. Learning and development activities are an important pillar of this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning today goes beyond good content and how it’s delivered. It covers the full range of investment that a company is making in an individual. This includes - improving their personal brand, building effective networks, learning through peers, coaching and mentorship.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning infrastructures take a long time to build, and as a startup there’s a gap in the market for a ‘turnkey’ learning management system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Employees are not empowered enough, and often feel alone in self betterment in a startup. They need active approaches, time and budget set aside, and feet in the right doors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most if not all of the tech giants and larger tech companies have very strong infrastructures for continual learning. Many credit company success to those programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A few unstructured notes on learning in startups today:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Long Game</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190607/the-long-game.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Long Game" /><published>2019-06-07T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-07T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190607/the-long-game</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190607/the-long-game.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m on my way to watch Game 4, and ended up in a wormhole of basketball analysis videos on Youtube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s one I found really interesting - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1IGwlu7LkKI&quot;&gt;How The Raptors Became An Elite NBA Team With Only Non-Lottery Players&lt;/a&gt;. I remember each of these events as a fan, and it’s really interesting to see how it all strings together into a broader strategy. Perhaps this is just another example of the past seeming so linear and intentional, but it’s a cool story nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1IGwlu7LkKI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m on my way to watch Game 4, and ended up in a wormhole of basketball analysis videos on Youtube.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Urgency</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190605/urgency.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Urgency" /><published>2019-06-05T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-05T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190605/urgency</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190605/urgency.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s 11:50 pm. That gives me 10 minutes to write and publish a post that I haven’t even conceived yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for some reason, I’m not worried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10 minutes is also 600 seconds, a unit shift that adds a different perspective. Some funny math starts to happen - If the fastest person in the world can run 100 meters in less than 10 seconds, in 600 seconds they can run 6000 meters. Obviously this isn’t true, but the perspective, however flawed, creates abundance from scarcity. This triggers a peace of mind and creates space for focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mental tricks alone aren’t enough. A fast approaching deadline is another type of boundary in which creativity can flourish. A boundary that can be manufactured consistently by, well, procrastinating. This is a familiar place - I subconsciously wait for times like this to &lt;em&gt;force&lt;/em&gt; creative output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be amazing if I could maintain this pace of output throughout the day. But for now…time’s up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It’s 11:50 pm. That gives me 10 minutes to write and publish a post that I haven’t even conceived yet.</summary></entry></feed>