<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-03T10:49:33-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Antifragile Marketplaces</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191002/antifragile-marketplaces.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antifragile Marketplaces" /><published>2019-10-02T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-02T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191002/antifragile-marketplaces</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191002/antifragile-marketplaces.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a few conversations recently about the concept of anti fragility as it applies to marketplaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antifragility is a concept that any entity actually gets stronger as a result of shock, or damage. It can be applied in business, medicine, systems design and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The antifragile is beyond the resilient or robust. The resilient resists shocks and stays the same; the antifragile gets better and better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting thought exercise is how we can design our marketplaces to be antifragile by nature. The shocks can be the loss of entities on any side. For example, the loss of a supplier, or exodus of customers. Can a marketplace actually get better if a supplier is lost, or goes out of business? In decentralized marketplaces (like Teachable or Shopify), this is precisely what happens. It actually improves the quality bar of overall suppliers on the platform. Exodus of customers is similar in decentralized marketplaces - because the damage is limited to one supplier - and an exodus of customers can be a good sign that supplier shouldn’t be in business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we’re going to see a lot more of these types of decentralized marketplaces in the future and it will be good for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve had a few conversations recently about the concept of anti fragility as it applies to marketplaces.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We Are All Going to Die</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191002/we-are-all-going-to-die.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Are All Going to Die" /><published>2019-10-02T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-02T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191002/we-are-all-going-to-die</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191002/we-are-all-going-to-die.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We are all going to die.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember when Jeremie Saunders said this during his talk at TEDxToronto from a few years ago. At the time, Jeremie was 29 years old, and was three months away from his &lt;em&gt;prescribed&lt;/em&gt; date of death due to Cystic Fibrosis. I can’t nearly do it justice, so here is the talk in full:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UQniNh_6LOY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my favorite passages and quotes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On death and freedom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cystic Fibrosis is one of the best things that have happened to me. No longer does that sentence - “Cystic Fibrosis is a fatal genetic disease” - carry the weight of fear, rejection and anger. Instead it’s become this powerful source of inspiration - &lt;strong&gt;it drives me&lt;/strong&gt;. You see, my unavoidable fate opened up my eyes so wide that it fundamentally changed what it means to live day in and day out, moment to moment. Cystic Fibrosis has essentially given me the impetus to not only &lt;em&gt;accept&lt;/em&gt; my own mortality, but to &lt;em&gt;embrace&lt;/em&gt; my own mortality. With that comes this extraordinary sense of freedom. And I can take that freedom and sprinkle it into my life by living like nothing is unattainable. I can take that big scary concept of death and instead of fear it, Use it, as a tool to motivate myself to live life to the fullest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On living fully, a quote from Mark Twain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The fear of death follows from the fear of life. A man who lives fully is prepared to die at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremie is an incredible human and continues to share his message through his podcast Sickboy, about others who live with chronic or terminal illness, in order to destigmatize illness and build community for those who are sick. Check it out &lt;a href=&quot;http://sickboypodcast.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“We are all going to die.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Experimenting with Comments</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191001/experimenting-with-comments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experimenting with Comments" /><published>2019-10-01T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-01T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191001/experimenting-with-comments</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191001/experimenting-with-comments.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m adding comments to posts on the blog, based on feedback from the micro-community that’s actually reading it (also, thank you, its appreciated more than you know).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;www.disqus.com&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;. It’s been relatively simple so far, thanks to the simple &lt;a href=&quot;https://tarunsachdeva.disqus.com/admin/install/platforms/jekyll/&quot;&gt;install instructions&lt;/a&gt;. Let’s see what happens!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m adding comments to posts on the blog, based on feedback from the micro-community that’s actually reading it (also, thank you, its appreciated more than you know).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Story of Us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190930/the-story-of-us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Story of Us" /><published>2019-09-30T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-30T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190930/the-story-of-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190930/the-story-of-us.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://waitbutwhy.com/2019/08/story-intro.html&quot;&gt;The Story of Us&lt;/a&gt; is the latest series from the &lt;a href=&quot;www.waitbutwhy.com&quot;&gt;Wait but Why&lt;/a&gt; blog. It’s an incredibly well told story of human history. I’m still working through it because it’s long but so well told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you come across something that you just &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; you’ll be referring back to often. This feels like one of those gems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Story of Us is the latest series from the Wait but Why blog. It’s an incredibly well told story of human history. I’m still working through it because it’s long but so well told.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Public Market Reckoning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190929/public-market-reckoning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Public Market Reckoning" /><published>2019-09-29T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-29T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190929/public-market-reckoning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190929/public-market-reckoning.html">&lt;p&gt;As more tech IPO’s tank, it’s clear that public market investors are not reacting well to the potential of the hottest companies in tech today. They want real margins that can sustain businesses in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred Wilson wrote an excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://avc.com/2019/09/the-great-public-market-reckoning/&quot;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; on this recently, and cited a post I’ve seen referred to often, &lt;a href=&quot;http://abovethecrowd.com/2011/05/24/all-revenue-is-not-created-equal-the-keys-to-the-10x-revenue-club/&quot;&gt;All Revenue is Not Created Equal&lt;/a&gt;. From the post is an excellent description of how valuation should differ based on the margins in a business:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is a huge difference between companies with high gross margins and those with lower gross margins. Using the DCF framework, you cannot generate much cash from a revenue stream that is saddled with large, variable costs. As a result, lower gross margin companies will trade a highly discounted price/revenue multiples. All things being equal, gross margin percentage should have a direct impact on price/revenue multiple, as there will obviously be more gross margin dollars to contribute to free cash flow. Journalists who quickly apply 10x multiples to all private companies should at the very least consider gross margin levels in their analysis.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great post on this topic, that I’ve referred to in the past as well, is Tren Wilson’s post, &lt;a href=&quot;https://25iq.com/2017/02/04/gross-margin-for-fun-and-profit-involves-beer-and-music-streaming/&quot;&gt;Gross Margin for Fun and Profit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As more tech IPO’s tank, it’s clear that public market investors are not reacting well to the potential of the hottest companies in tech today. They want real margins that can sustain businesses in the long run.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day Off</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190928/day-off.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day Off" /><published>2019-09-28T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-28T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190928/day-off</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190928/day-off.html">&lt;p&gt;I considered taking a day off writing today. I’m not feeling great, so the last thing I want to do is sit in front of a computer and write because of self-created commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When something is built into a system, it’s absence is felt. I immediately regretted the decision and started this post shortly after. Mostly a placeholder for when the feeling returns - which it undoubtedly will.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I considered taking a day off writing today. I’m not feeling great, so the last thing I want to do is sit in front of a computer and write because of self-created commitment.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes for an Essay on Software and Society</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190927/software-society-essay-notes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes for an Essay on Software and Society" /><published>2019-09-27T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-27T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190927/software-society-essay-notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190927/software-society-essay-notes.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m writing a more comprehensive essay on the role software is playing in society. This post is a set of highly disconnected points I want to make in that essay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inherently software is an infinitely moldable, interactive, and updateable object.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software is plastic. It has an infinite creative space, and will soon become everything. When that happens, it will also become &lt;em&gt;invisible&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI helps software create patterns - patterns that help us see, hear, and create.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People who make software need to deeply understand the spoken and unspoken needs of the people.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People who make software must accept both the first and second order effects of what they are creating, especially given how easy it is to distribute and get people’s attention.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software is eating the world - first by &lt;em&gt;modelling it&lt;/em&gt;, then by creating something that only exist only in software. This is a consistent pattern that applies in many scenarios and industries.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software is becoming closer to us. We are already wearing software, driving software, and living in software.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software is starting to solve some higher order human functions - we learn, meditate, and empathize with software. But we don’t have software-native ways to do those things, yet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What happens when software has finished eating the world? What do we have to watch out for? Technologists love to extrapolate potential but software’s place in society will likely be more balanced and neutral.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be updating this post as I structure these thoughts further.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m writing a more comprehensive essay on the role software is playing in society. This post is a set of highly disconnected points I want to make in that essay.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting Closer to Software, Again</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190926/getting-closer-to-software.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Closer to Software, Again" /><published>2019-09-26T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-26T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190926/getting-closer-to-software</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190926/getting-closer-to-software.html">&lt;p&gt;Amazon announced it’s echo buds recently, creating a low priced Airpods competitor tied to the Alexa ecosystem. The relatively low pricepoint ($130) can skyrocket adoption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago I wrote about how we are &lt;a href=&quot;/20190129/closer-software.html&quot;&gt;getting closer to software&lt;/a&gt;. While Echobuds aren’t novel, it’s just another development in bringing software closer to our physical selves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also happened to talk to a student from &lt;a href=&quot;https://theksociety.com/&quot;&gt;The Knowledge Society&lt;/a&gt;, an incubator for some brilliant high school students - who was investigating the world of 3D printed organs, gene editing and CRISPR. This is how software is eating the world from the inside out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technologists love to extrapolate potential, but mass adoption is often a multi-decade sport. But at the same time, our future already exists in today’s science fiction. It’s wild to think about our world in twenty or thirty years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Amazon announced it’s echo buds recently, creating a low priced Airpods competitor tied to the Alexa ecosystem. The relatively low pricepoint ($130) can skyrocket adoption.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Thoughts on Social Finance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190925/social-finance.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Thoughts on Social Finance" /><published>2019-09-25T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-25T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190925/social-finance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190925/social-finance.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday Anish Acharya published this post entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/09/24/how-fintech-startups-find-users/&quot;&gt;Five Ways Fintech Companies can find Customers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the tactics he mentioned was activating social networks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Social networks have been largely underutilized in fintech thus far. But existing social bonds can be a powerful tool used to encourage saving and extend credit—ROSCAs are an age-old (offline) example. Looking ahead, a16z general partner Connie Chan recently wrote about the use of WhatsApp and WeChat groups in China to facilitate product experiences in travel, shopping, fitness, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two layers to social finance. One leans on the dynamics in which money moves between people. This encompasses everything from peer to peer transfers to shared savings pools (the ROSCAs referred to above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is simply adding a social layer on top of the current financial services, that encourages people to be more open about matters of money. This includes safe spaces to ask others about money (Reddit’s finance forums, for example - although I wouldn’t broadly classify Reddit as a safe space), but also things like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetcleo.com/&quot;&gt;cheeky financial advice chat bots&lt;/a&gt; that are fun to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our relationships with money are complicated, and many seek social validation to make sure they’re on the right track. For most, being a part of the right pack is exactly what they need. Financial advisors provide this ability but there’s so much more room for experimentation here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Yesterday Anish Acharya published this post entitled Five Ways Fintech Companies can find Customers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Zone To Win</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190924/zone-to-win.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zone To Win" /><published>2019-09-24T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-24T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190924/zone-to-win</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190924/zone-to-win.html">&lt;p&gt;Geoffrey Moore, author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crossing_the_Chasm&quot;&gt;Crossing the Chasm&lt;/a&gt;, was in Toronto today giving a talk about his new book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zonetowin.com/&quot;&gt;Zone to Win&lt;/a&gt;. It details a framework for how established enterprises can compete amongst the threat of disruptive innovations. In it, he details 4 “zones” of work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Performance Zone, where the key metric is to make the number. It consists of the sales organizations accountable for bookings and the product and service organizations accountable for revenue—and no one else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Productivity Zone, where success means delivering efficient systems and effective programs while ensuring all operations are regulatory compliant. Virtually everyone who is not directly accountable for a booking or revenue number works here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Incubation Zone, where the objective is to make, market, and sell products and services that are highly disruptive to the status quo. These efforts are deliberately kept sequestered from the prior two zones to speed cycle time, embrace innovation, and take risk. Success here consists of creating viable businesses in net new uncorrelated categories that can be scaled to material size.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Transformation Zone, where success equates either to driving an incubated business to material scale or fending off a direct attack on a core business model. In either case an initiative in this zone takes priority over all activities in the other three zones, and they must make whatever adjustments necessary to accommodate it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first 3 are fairly well understood. “Performance” and “Productivity” are relevant to sustaining innovation - either extracting maximum value from a market, or for enabling functions. The Incubation zone efforts are the lab-type efforts that exist in almost every enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to say that big companies can’t innovate isn’t really true. Most big companies work well in Zone 1 and 2. They also invest in Zone 3, to address the disruptive forces themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his presentation, he highlighted cases from 56 companies that were once market leaders, all had innovation labs, but never were able to counter the disruptive forces working against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reason, in all those organizations, was the lack of a “transformation” zone type effort. In this zone, companies move into &lt;em&gt;war time&lt;/em&gt; mode to ensure that the successful incubated projects are actualized into the rest of the company. Most companies fail at this - even successful incubated projects either struggle to integrate with the rest of the organization / product line. In this zone, everyone in the organization needs to be &lt;em&gt;focused&lt;/em&gt; on making this transformation successful, which can sometimes mean sacrificing short term revenue targets for revenue growth potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few examples are Apple’s focus on the iPod (when the Mac was making it the most money), and Microsoft’s recent shift to cloud computing (so dramatic that there’s no longer a Windows division in the company).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Geoffrey Moore, author of Crossing the Chasm, was in Toronto today giving a talk about his new book, Zone to Win. It details a framework for how established enterprises can compete amongst the threat of disruptive innovations. In it, he details 4 “zones” of work:</summary></entry></feed>