<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-02T23:41:32-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Boring Technology (DRAFT)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190702/boring-technology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boring Technology (DRAFT)" /><published>2019-07-02T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-02T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190702/boring-technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190702/boring-technology.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked in tech long enough to see a familiar game play out many times: engineers want to use the latest and greatest technology, often overlooking the maintenance cost of new tech. At the same time, they look down on ‘old technology’ as inferior, when the opposite is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan McKinley has a great presentation on this topic aptly titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://boringtechnology.club/&quot;&gt;Boring Technology&lt;/a&gt;. Check it out; its a great read and nails the problem very well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve worked in tech long enough to see a familiar game play out many times: engineers want to use the latest and greatest technology, often overlooking the maintenance cost of new tech. At the same time, they look down on ‘old technology’ as inferior, when the opposite is true.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Free Agency</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190701/secrets.markdoown" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free Agency" /><published>2019-07-01T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-01T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190701/secrets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190701/secrets.markdoown">The first day of NBA free agency has been a whirlwind. Some massive trades by Brooklyn - with KD and Kyrie although Durant's injury almost guarantees we won't see this play out until 2020/2021. 

The most WTF trade of the day was the  announcement Golden State and Brooklyn  agreed on a sign-and-trade, sending D’Angelo Russell to the Warriors on a four-year, $117M maximum contract. 🤔

Obviously we're still waiting for the Fun Guy to make his decision. Unsurprisingly, he clearly knows how to keep a secret.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The first day of NBA free agency has been a whirlwind. Some massive trades by Brooklyn - with KD and Kyrie although Durant's injury almost guarantees we won't see this play out until 2020/2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Learning Styles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190701/learning-styles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Learning Styles" /><published>2019-07-01T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-01T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190701/learning-styles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190701/learning-styles.html">&lt;p&gt;Had a really great conversation today about how learning styles greatly affect comprehension. This would indicate instructors should cater their courses to every individual. So if someone is a visual learner we should look for a way to visually represent our lessons to them. Except this isn’t always true and most importantly doesn’t always lead to better outcomes. I read a &lt;a href=&quot;https://career.ucsf.edu/sites/career.ucsf.edu/files/Article%20UCSF%20SEJC%20January%202017.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; on this topic which concludes the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Theories of learning styles suggest that individuals think and learn best in different ways. These are not differences of ability but rather preferences for processing certain types of information or for processing information in certain types of way. If accurate, learning styles theories could have important implications for instruction because student achievement would be a product of the interaction of instruction and the student’s style. There is reason to think that people view learning styles theories as broadly accurate, but, in fact, scientific support for these theories is lacking. We suggest that educators’ time and energy are better spent on other theories that might aid instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientific American &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-problem-with-learning-styles/&quot;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; something similar, that while people understand they have different learning styles, they don’t behave rationally in picking the right learning strategy. From the article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Despite knowing their own, self-reported learning preferences, nearly 70% of students failed to employ study techniques that supported those preferences. Most visual learners did not rely heavily on visual strategies (e.g., diagrams, graphics), nor did most reading/writing learners rely predominantly on reading strategies (e.g., review of notes or textbook), and so on. Given the prevailing belief that learning styles matter, and the fact many students blame poor academic performance on the lack of a match between their learning style and teachers’ instructional methods, one might expect students to rely on techniques that support their personal learning preferences when working on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some more resources on the topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://buildingrti.utexas.org/resource-pages/learning-styles-neuromyth-debunked&quot;&gt;Learning Styles: Neuromyth Debunked&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5366351/&quot;&gt;Evidence-Based Higher Education – Is the Learning Styles ‘Myth’ Important?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Had a really great conversation today about how learning styles greatly affect comprehension. This would indicate instructors should cater their courses to every individual. So if someone is a visual learner we should look for a way to visually represent our lessons to them. Except this isn’t always true and most importantly doesn’t always lead to better outcomes. I read a paper on this topic which concludes the following:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Waves</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190626/waves.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waves" /><published>2019-06-26T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-26T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190626/waves</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190626/waves.html">&lt;p&gt;A product or company’s success is dependent on the waves it’s riding. These waves can be broad market trends, shifts in behaviour or the success of other products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, mobile app companies rode the wave of broad global smartphone adoption. Similarly, instability in the public markets increases adoption of Bitcoin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s nice to think success is always fully earned, the truth is in understanding the broader system. It’s often the larger waves that influence a company’s success more than anything else.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A product or company’s success is dependent on the waves it’s riding. These waves can be broad market trends, shifts in behaviour or the success of other products.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Printing Your Brain on Paper</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190625/printing-your-brain-on-paper.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Printing Your Brain on Paper" /><published>2019-06-25T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-25T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190625/printing-your-brain-on-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190625/printing-your-brain-on-paper.html">&lt;p&gt;Mindmapping is the act of articulating a thought pattern onto paper (or screen). Great clarity emerges from visualizing how thoughts connect. It becomes a systems diagram for thought - showing how one thought triggers another in a chain reaction. When I feel stuck on a decision, it’s often because that chain reaction creates a cyclical pattern I keep traversing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision mindmaps look like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Directed_acyclic_graph&quot;&gt;directed acyclical graph&lt;/a&gt;. Each node represents an Action or State, and each arrow represents a specific path of consequence (which then leads to another action or state).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of decisions, a node would be something like “Work at Company X” or “Ship Feature Y”. Connector arrows lead to other states. Obviously a state can also include emotional states like ‘satisfaction’, or ‘regret’. This can both increase self awareness and decision-making quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connecting them on paper gives me &lt;em&gt;control&lt;/em&gt; - it removes me from the thought, gives me a guide to navigate it, which then results in a more sound decision. Charlie Munger’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/2013/04/munger-two-step/&quot;&gt;approach to decision making&lt;/a&gt; is a two step process - first understand the forces at play, and then the psychological factors that might be leading you astray. A mindmap is a great way to understand both.s&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Mindmapping is the act of articulating a thought pattern onto paper (or screen). Great clarity emerges from visualizing how thoughts connect. It becomes a systems diagram for thought - showing how one thought triggers another in a chain reaction. When I feel stuck on a decision, it’s often because that chain reaction creates a cyclical pattern I keep traversing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">When They See Us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190624/when-they-see-us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When They See Us" /><published>2019-06-24T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-24T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190624/when-they-see-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190624/when-they-see-us.html">&lt;p&gt;Ava DuVernay’s latest work is a 4 part series on Netflix about the Central Park 5. It goes into detail about their experience - on the night of the event, throughout unfair incarceration, and assimilation back into normal society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will grip you, make your blood boil, and make you cry. It is important storytelling. Check it out on Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ava DuVernay’s latest work is a 4 part series on Netflix about the Central Park 5. It goes into detail about their experience - on the night of the event, throughout unfair incarceration, and assimilation back into normal society.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190623/one.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One" /><published>2019-06-23T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-23T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190623/one</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190623/one.html">&lt;p&gt;They turned one today; I’m so happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cl.ly/e388b73e182e/Image%202019-06-26%20at%2011.50.07%20PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;One&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">They turned one today; I’m so happy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Systems, Hallucination &amp;amp; Vision, and Making vs. Selling Art</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190622/hallucination-vision.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Systems, Hallucination &amp; Vision, and Making vs. Selling Art" /><published>2019-06-22T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-22T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190622/hallucination-vision</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190622/hallucination-vision.html">&lt;p&gt;This is easily a classic conversation. Brian Koppelman (of Rounders, Billions fame) sat down with Marc Andressen to talk about selling creativity, systems thinking, and so much more. So amazing. &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/03/12/hallucination-vision-scenius-networks-selling-using-making-art-brian-koppelman-marc-andreessen/&quot;&gt;Read here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Brian: But I guess what I’m asking is, how do you learn to — Do you think one can learn to do both things? To be a creator, founder/creator, and the salesman of your own work? Like, how does one learn to do that?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Marc: Yes. Well, so first of all… put it this way — this is, again, where I think systems thinking is actually helpful — ao, actually, we have a lot of this, so we have a lot of sort of founders who are like classical engineers, and they’re sort of classical introverts and the idea of having to go, kind of, you know, sell is like anathema, like, the idea. You know, they’ve got these kind of, I would say, misperceptions of the salesman as somebody who’s wearing a shiny suit &amp;lt;Brian: Yes, perfect!&amp;gt; selling somebody something that they don’t need.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And so, we have a couple of responses to that. We have a specific response to that, which is actually the role of sales is (at least in our industry) is not to sell something you don’t need — it’s actually to help somebody buy what they actually do need. And we can have a long conversation about that. The really good sales people in Silicon Valley who make a lot of money become very personally bonded to their customers; they end up going to their customers’, you know, weddings, to their kids’ weddings — like, they become like, very close allies to the careers of their customers. We can have a long conversation about that. It’s a real form of value-add to the customer.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But even deeper than that. The thing I tell the engineers is, look, dealing with customers, it’s another systems problem. Like, you are the master of solving a systems problem, which is how to get the computer to do what you want. Like, people aren’t computers, they’re different, but there is a system for dealing people. You can engineer a system for dealing with people. And actually, when you work with top-end sales people, what you find is they have incredibly elaborate, like, very real systems. Like, very, very, very thought-through kind of abstract systems of how they basically run like, a large-scale sales campaign and how they deal with the customer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is easily a classic conversation. Brian Koppelman (of Rounders, Billions fame) sat down with Marc Andressen to talk about selling creativity, systems thinking, and so much more. So amazing. Read here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Risk</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190621/risk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Risk" /><published>2019-06-21T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-21T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190621/risk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190621/risk.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been faced with some decisions recently that have tested my risk tolerance. Almost serendipitously I was catching up on The Knowledge Project, in particular &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/howard-marks/&quot;&gt;this episode&lt;/a&gt; featuring Howard Marks of Oaktree Capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some notes from this conversation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Outperformance: By definition this requires contrarian thinking. Getting ahead &lt;em&gt;by definition&lt;/em&gt; means you’re working either smarter or harder than everyone else. Working harder isn’t en vogue these days. And while Nothing is really deterministic but ultimately working hard is a predictor of success more than it isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two paragraphs from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/howard-marks/&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt; really hit home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To be an out-performer, you have to think different from the crowd. But most of the time, the crowd is about as close to being right as you can get. Ergo, the problem. So, to be an above average investor, number one you have to think different from the crowd. But number two, you have to be right. So, second-level thinking is thinking which is different and better.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The question is not, do you dare to be great? The question is, do you dare to be different? To diverge from the pack is required if you’re going to be a superior in anything. Number two, do you dare to be wrong? Number three, do you dare to look wrong? Because even things which are going to be right in the long run, maybe look wrong in the short run. So, you have to be willing to live with all those three things, different, wrong, and looking wrong, in order to be able to take the risk required and engage in the idiosyncratic behavior required for success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been faced with some decisions recently that have tested my risk tolerance. Almost serendipitously I was catching up on The Knowledge Project, in particular this episode featuring Howard Marks of Oaktree Capital.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Slack’s IPO</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190620/slack-ipo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Slack's IPO" /><published>2019-06-20T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-20T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190620/slack-ipo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190620/slack-ipo.html">&lt;p&gt;Slack IPO’d today and I was looking through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sec.report/Document/0001628280-19-004786/&quot;&gt;S-1&lt;/a&gt; they filed a few months prior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack gets a lot of love from the tech press, and &lt;a href=&quot;/20180923/slack-product-network-ecosystem.html&quot;&gt;I’m a fan&lt;/a&gt; of the product. I was taken aback at the scale of their loss and particularly the sales and marketing costs. Slack is upheld as the champion of bottoms up organic growth in the enterprise, but the numbers tell a slightly different story. Obviously an outsiders perspective but pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the risks section of their S-1:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have incurred significant net losses in each year since our inception, including net losses of $146.9 million, $140.1 million, and $138.9 million in fiscal years 2017, 2018, and 2019, respectively. We expect to continue to incur net losses for the foreseeable future and we may not achieve or maintain profitability in the future. Because the market for Slack, and the features, integrations, and capabilities we offer on Slack, is rapidly evolving and has not yet reached widespread adoption, it is difficult for us to predict our future results of operations or the limits of our market opportunity. &lt;strong&gt;We expect our operating expenses to significantly increase over the next several years as we hire additional personnel, particularly in sales and marketing&lt;/strong&gt;, expand our partnerships, operations, and infrastructure, both domestically and internationally, continue to enhance Slack and develop and expand its features, integrations and capabilities, and expand and improve our application programming interfaces, or APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Slack IPO’d today and I was looking through the S-1 they filed a few months prior.</summary></entry></feed>