<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-08-27T09:19:58-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Income Sharing Agreements (ISA’s)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190826/income-sharing-agreements.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Income Sharing Agreements (ISA's)" /><published>2019-08-26T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-26T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190826/income-sharing-agreements</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190826/income-sharing-agreements.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently subscribed to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://transcend.substack.com/&quot;&gt;Transcend Network substack&lt;/a&gt;. It’s an interesting newsletter about the future of education and work, and this week they posted an overview of Income Sharing Agreements, or ISA’s. These have become very popular and apparently 40% of the current crop of YC companies use some form of ISAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ISA’s are a simple funding agreement that provides upfront education (or payment of education fees), in return for a share of future employment income. Lambda School is an ISA that pays for coding school and asks students for their first paycheck of the tech job they landed. They are a great way to align incentives between students and those providing training. One of the reasons they are being used now is because of the global skills gap, which is especially pronounced in the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1100,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fceca7b05-f0a6-4df8-abf0-2d0b3548903b_432x327.png&quot; alt=&quot;ISA's Incentives&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about ISA’s on the Transcend Network’s newsletter &lt;a href=&quot;https://transcend.substack.com/p/a-slice-of-the-worlds-income-transcend&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently subscribed to the Transcend Network substack. It’s an interesting newsletter about the future of education and work, and this week they posted an overview of Income Sharing Agreements, or ISA’s. These have become very popular and apparently 40% of the current crop of YC companies use some form of ISAs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Purpose of a Corporation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190821/purpose-of-a-corporation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Purpose of a Corporation" /><published>2019-08-21T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190821/purpose-of-a-corporation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190821/purpose-of-a-corporation.html">&lt;p&gt;Since 1997, a group of CEO’s of the biggest American corporations have been getting together in an annual  Business Roundtable summit. In their most recent summit, they issued a startement committing to a new purpose of a corporation (since 1997, this has been to serve shareholders, and to maximize shareholder value). The new mandate includes this, but also some other &lt;a href=&quot;https://opportunity.businessroundtable.org/ourcommitment/&quot;&gt;committments&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Delivering value to our customers. We will further the tradition of American companies leading the way in meeting or exceeding customer expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Investing in our employees. This starts with compensating them fairly and providing important benefits. It also includes supporting them through training and education that help develop new skills for a rapidly changing world. We foster diversity and inclusion, dignity and respect.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Dealing fairly and ethically with our suppliers. We are dedicated to serving as good partners to the other companies, large and small, that help us meet our missions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Supporting the communities in which we work. We respect the people in our communities and protect the environment by embracing sustainable practices across our businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Generating long-term value for shareholders, who provide the capital that allows companies to invest, grow and innovate. We are committed to transparency and effective engagement with shareholders.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Each of our stakeholders is essential. We commit to deliver value to all of them, for the future success of our companies, our communities and our country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am immediately reminded of the &lt;a href=&quot;/20181020/leadership-lattice-simplified.html&quot;&gt;leadership lattice&lt;/a&gt; - a mental model for &lt;em&gt;how companies work&lt;/em&gt; and leader’s role within it. The lattice describes how leaders have to manage their attention towards individual growth, team productivity, the product of their effort, the extent of impact in their market, and the second order effects of that impact. This broader responsibility is reflected in this mandate as well with some level of committment from the CEO’s of these orgs. While it feels good to commit to this, it feels reactionary, a bit late, and I remain skeptical about it’s impact. I hope I’m wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Since 1997, a group of CEO’s of the biggest American corporations have been getting together in an annual Business Roundtable summit. In their most recent summit, they issued a startement committing to a new purpose of a corporation (since 1997, this has been to serve shareholders, and to maximize shareholder value). The new mandate includes this, but also some other committments:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The WeWork IPO</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190820/wework-ipo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The WeWork IPO" /><published>2019-08-20T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-20T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190820/wework-ipo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190820/wework-ipo.html">&lt;p&gt;Ben Thompson from Stratechery makes the bull case for the WeWork IPO, and compares it to the AWS business. Which I think is an apt analogy. It’s a first principles approach - think about the largest item on a startup financial statement and rent is probably high up there. WeWork turns a fixed cost into a variable expense based on usage, allowing startups to allocate their capital to what matters more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is nothing more fixed than real estate, yet WeWork’s offering transforms real estate into a variable cost for all kinds of companies, with benefits that roughly mirror public clouds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;New companies can have instant access to a well-appointed office space and pay for only a desk or two, and then grow as needed.
Growing companies do not need to spend time on extensive build-outs months or years ahead of future growth, and instead pay for more space as they need it.
Established companies no longer need to have a real estate competency all over the world, and can in fact expand to new territories with far less risk than previously required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really interesting take and could very well become true, but still a massive leap of faith. WeWork’s financial and operational red flags cannot be ignored. As Ben himself wrote, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stratechery.com/2019/why-wework-isnt-aws-and-the-ceo-problem-cloudflares-s-1-contrasting-s-1s/&quot;&gt;leadership matters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ben Thompson from Stratechery makes the bull case for the WeWork IPO, and compares it to the AWS business. Which I think is an apt analogy. It’s a first principles approach - think about the largest item on a startup financial statement and rent is probably high up there. WeWork turns a fixed cost into a variable expense based on usage, allowing startups to allocate their capital to what matters more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Marketplaces, Decentralization and Losing Trust (Part 2)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190819/marketplaces-decentralization-customers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marketplaces, Decentralization and Losing Trust (Part 2)" /><published>2019-08-19T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-19T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190819/marketplaces-decentralization-customers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190819/marketplaces-decentralization-customers.html">&lt;p&gt;This is the second in a series of posts about how decentralization takes place in marketplaces - through an erosion of trust in intermediaries. In my &lt;a href=&quot;/20190818/marketplaces-decentralization-trust-supply-side.html&quot;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt;, I examined how trust breaks down in suppliers and what that causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customers losing trust happens when the marketplace no longer offers the level of convenience (through price or selection), or doesn’t invest in improving the fulfillment experience of a product or service sold in the marketplace. This is generally a slower process - one bad experience will not mean a customer writes off the marketplaces; but over time dissatisfaction can compound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, supplier mistreatment creates a side effect of lost trust with customers. This is true especially in today’s ecosystem where customers are more discerning about the goods and services they consume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opportunity here is two sided. One is to provide customers with the same level of utility  when purchasing directly from multiple suppliers.  For example, discovery or managing your fulfillment  experience (e.g shipping tracking). If the friction or cost of switching is too high customers will likely stay with the central marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also opportunity in offering services that the central marketplace probably wouldn’t provide because it’s against their ethos or values, or goes against their core business model. For example, offering easy data portability is not in Facebooks interest. DuckDuckGo is a good example here but not “technically” a marketplace. Lyft is another one, in that their ethos is much more friendly and supportive to their drivers at a time when people are losing trust in Uber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customer trust is tricky. Gaining it takes time. Losing it starts slowly and then fast. It pays to be proactive about some issues. Centralized Marketplaces carry an additional burden that they have to manage both sides. Decentralized marketplaces become stronger as bad suppliers fail, and overall customer experience goes up. This makes them inherently antifragile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This is an evolving set of thoughts and will likely be updated over time).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is the second in a series of posts about how decentralization takes place in marketplaces - through an erosion of trust in intermediaries. In my first post, I examined how trust breaks down in suppliers and what that causes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Marketplaces, Decentralization and Losing Trust (Part 1)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190818/marketplaces-decentralization-trust-supply-side.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marketplaces, Decentralization and Losing Trust (Part 1)" /><published>2019-08-18T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-18T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190818/marketplaces-decentralization-trust-supply-side</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190818/marketplaces-decentralization-trust-supply-side.html">&lt;p&gt;Some disconnected thoughts about marketplaces, decentralization and trust:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first wave of marketplaces has been about setting up intermediaries between suppliers and customers across different industries. Sometimes the supply has come from existing sources (e.g. Expedia for Hotels and Flights), and other times a marketplace distinguishes itself because of a unique form of supply (Airbnb, Uber). Customers obviously benefit from convenience and access to this supplier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For suppliers, these intermediaries did well to establish a source of revenue that perhaps didn’t exist before - e.g. for drivers of UberX, hosts on Airbnb. In many cases, that has become a significant portion of personal income and there are countless stories of people leaving their day jobs. These folks are often makers, creators and entrepreneurs in their own right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as these intermediaries become more powerful, they often do things to drive marketplace value, (or sometimes, just in the name of customer centricity) that ends up harming these suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I believe will end up happening is a new crop of companies that exist solely to help these entrepreneurs operate as independent entities. These companies will provide suppliers with what the marketplaces do - the ability to reach customers, manage the customer relationship, and ensure that their customers are being fulfilled. This is already well underway in retail (Shopify being the clear example here), but also in journalism (Substack), Food delivery (Dumpling), and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how I believe &lt;em&gt;decentralization&lt;/em&gt; takes place - through a slow erosion trust in intermediaries that are acting to optimize the overall marketplace versus trying to make their suppliers successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In future posts, I’ll explore how trust in the intermediary gets eroded on the customer end, and what opportunities that will create.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Some disconnected thoughts about marketplaces, decentralization and trust:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Diversifying Well</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190817/diversifying-well.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Diversifying Well" /><published>2019-08-17T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-17T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190817/diversifying-well</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190817/diversifying-well.html">&lt;p&gt;This has been a bonkers week for the stock &lt;a href=&quot;https://ca.finance.yahoo.com/quote/%5EDJI?p=^DJI&quot;&gt;market&lt;/a&gt;. It’s timely to read an essay like the one Ray Dalio published recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/diversifying-well-most-important-thing-you-need-do-order-ray-dalio/?published=t&quot;&gt;Diversifying Well Is the Most Important Thing You Need to Do in Order to Invest Well&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason comes down to two principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Extreme moves in markets and economies are largely self-correcting, because when they happen, they set into motion adjustments that tend to reverse those extremes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People tend to extrapolate what they have gotten used to. As a result, after an extended period of a certain type of market and economic behavior (a paradigm), it is likely to be “discounted” or “priced in” to the markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combining these two highlights why diversification is most important:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Because of those last two principles combined—and because policy makers tend to move to reverse extremes in the markets and economies—we have big reversals and big paradigm shifts in markets and economies. It is also why having a well-diversified portfolio that is rebalanced to maintain that diversification has a much better expected return-risk ratio than any single investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This has been a bonkers week for the stock market. It’s timely to read an essay like the one Ray Dalio published recently Diversifying Well Is the Most Important Thing You Need to Do in Order to Invest Well.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Writing Regularly Has Taught Me</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190814/what-has-writing-regularly-taught-me.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Writing Regularly Has Taught Me" /><published>2019-08-14T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-14T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190814/what-has-writing-regularly-taught-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190814/what-has-writing-regularly-taught-me.html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I received a message from a friend asking, “What have you learned from writing on your blog regularly?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great question that provoked a number of thoughts, and I decided to write out my replies as a blog post itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, writing creates deeper comprehension. Learning and expressing a readable opinion is a great forcing function for understanding any topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing also teaches brevity and the art of getting to the point. Infact, writing is more often &lt;em&gt;removing&lt;/em&gt; words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing as a habit has taught me about myself - my default systems and common excuses. This is likely the byproduct of a the daily commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, writing has become an instrument to do work. It’s not exactly learning, but there’s a ton of value here. I often end meetings saying, ‘I’m going to write about this’, and that post has lasting value (and a nice reminder of our interaction).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today, I received a message from a friend asking, “What have you learned from writing on your blog regularly?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trends in Seed Investing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190811/seed-investing-trends.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trends in Seed Investing" /><published>2019-08-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190811/seed-investing-trends</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190811/seed-investing-trends.html">&lt;p&gt;Tom Tunguz recently shared some &lt;a href=&quot;https://tomtunguz.com/which-categories-of-seed-startups-are-thriving-which-aren-t/&quot;&gt;data and insights on seed investing trends&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s growing: AI, Blockchain, Fintech, Food and Beverage and Software (automating internal processes). 
What’s not: Advertising, Analytics, Big Data and Social Media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This data is a &lt;em&gt;signal of investor confidence level&lt;/em&gt; in each of these markets, which is correlated (and sometimes cuasal) to growth in the markets themselves. It’s important to understand this abstraction - especially since seed investing sometimes suffers from herd behaviour. For that reason, there’s probably an argument to discount the outliers, especially given the &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2019/03/16/decade-in-review-trends-in-seed-and-early-stage-funding/&quot;&gt;rise in seed funds&lt;/a&gt; over the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Tom Tunguz recently shared some data and insights on seed investing trends.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Risk in Startups</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190808/classic-risk-vs-quantum-risk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Risk in Startups" /><published>2019-08-08T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-08T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190808/classic-risk-vs-quantum-risk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190808/classic-risk-vs-quantum-risk.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about early stage startup risk especially in working on the presentations about minimum viable products. In that discussion, I’ll be talking about how MVP’s are a framework for de-risking startup investments. In the early stages of a startup, the risk of getting to product market fit is the largest (but not only) reason why most startups fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came across this article about startup risk authored by Kanyi Maqubela - &lt;a href=&quot;https://kanyi.blog/2018/10/18/classical-risk-vs-quantum-risk/&quot;&gt;classic risk vs. quantum risk&lt;/a&gt; - and it summarizes the &lt;em&gt;weight&lt;/em&gt; of product/market fit risk really well - essentially, the risk associated with P/M fit is so much higher than all other risks associated with activities in that stage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What does that mean for company formation? What if risk, as a function of milestones, looked less like classical mechanics, where there can be continuous, curve-like de-risking in time? What if all of the activity that comes along with building a company does not in fact de-risk it? What if product market-fit is in fact the only discrete state in the early stage that de-risks a company?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, you can de-risk an early stage venture through in many different ways but only P/M fit matters. Simply put, if you haven’t built the right product for the right people &lt;em&gt;at the right time&lt;/em&gt;, nothing else matters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been thinking about early stage startup risk especially in working on the presentations about minimum viable products. In that discussion, I’ll be talking about how MVP’s are a framework for de-risking startup investments. In the early stages of a startup, the risk of getting to product market fit is the largest (but not only) reason why most startups fail.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Helping Ideapreneurs Become Entrepreneurs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190802/helping-ideapreneurs-become-entrepreneurs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Helping Ideapreneurs Become Entrepreneurs" /><published>2019-08-02T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190802/helping-ideapreneurs-become-entrepreneurs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190802/helping-ideapreneurs-become-entrepreneurs.html">&lt;p&gt;Most startups fail because they built something no one wanted (I read that it was upto 42%, but obviously not scientific). So, the path to building something out of nothing is fraught with risk, something that those working in larger companies are less likely to make. However, their years of industry insight may be extremely valuable in de-risking any enterprise from Day 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not try to solve both these problems together, by building a service to accelerate the path of validation for those with great product ideas - in partnership with a trusted group of product experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be a turnkey service that offers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy setup of an MVP - whether it’s a landing page for a new app or quick prototype of the product.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performance marketing to target the right consumer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reporting and analytics on how well the MVP did, with a recommendation for whether they want to continue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is obviously great dealflow for pre-seed stage VC, so access to a VC network would be a easy add on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Most startups fail because they built something no one wanted (I read that it was upto 42%, but obviously not scientific). So, the path to building something out of nothing is fraught with risk, something that those working in larger companies are less likely to make. However, their years of industry insight may be extremely valuable in de-risking any enterprise from Day 1.</summary></entry></feed>