<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-07T17:25:50-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Some Notes on the State of Online Discourse</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191007/some-notes-on-our-online-discourse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Notes on the State of Online Discourse" /><published>2019-10-07T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-07T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191007/some-notes-on-our-online-discourse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191007/some-notes-on-our-online-discourse.html">&lt;p&gt;We’re divided on so many fronts these days. One of them is whether our online expressions should become immediately accountable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we publish something on the internet or tweet something to our followers, we immediately have an &lt;em&gt;audience&lt;/em&gt; for those thoughts. That carries a sense of responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are those that argue one shouldn’t concern themselves with the audience’s reaction - express the thought, act on them, see them through to their fullest extent. Life is an experiment and we need fearlessness to move society forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are those that argue that we &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; read the room. We cannot act with reckless abandon, and that people with leverage have an inherent responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a new problem, but the rise of influencer culture has magnified it and made it a mainstream issue. On one side, the most powerful person in the world is openly acting like an asshole on Twitter. On another side, people are feeling censored and attacked for their thoughts, and choosing to stay silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem I see is intelligent people ignoring nuance. Over applying simplistic mental models. Some people acting childishly, not understanding the leverage of their mediums and expressions. And on another side, people acting as if one human can truly understand the full second order effects of their action, holding infinite possibility in their head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe we’ll get to a place where we’ll be able to have decent social discourse and be able to grow together, but recognizing there are some just beginning that process. Perhaps that will just take time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We’re divided on so many fronts these days. One of them is whether our online expressions should become immediately accountable.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t Raise More Than You Need</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191006/dont-raise-more-than-you-need.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don't Raise More Than You Need" /><published>2019-10-06T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-06T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191006/dont-raise-more-than-you-need</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191006/dont-raise-more-than-you-need.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s generally good advice for companies to only raise the amount of capital for what’s absolutely necessary, and no more. The definition of &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; is context specific, but most often it’s getting through a certain stage or getting ready for a future investment round, IPO, or another milestone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you raise too little, obviously that can handicap a companies ability to reach these goals. When raising too much, decision quality suffers - companies choose to do &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; and prioritize less. This leads to a decline in output quality - be it in product, sales, or any business leading function. Startups often tend to spend what they raise, and being overcapitalized leads to saying yes to everything. Ofcourse, there is also the issue of over-valuing your company too early and the difficulty in raising another round in that situation. These and other issues are discussed in Mark Suster’s article from 2016, &lt;a href=&quot;https://bothsidesofthetable.com/why-raising-too-much-money-can-harm-your-startup-5adc112e1259&quot;&gt;Why Raising Too Much Money Can Harm Your Startup&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funny thing is, this applies not just to companies but to VC funds too. There weren’t that many examples of the counter argument before but now there’s Softbank’s Vision Fund, obviously an easy target these days. Excess capital clouds decision making, especially you’re in the sole business of deploying capital. It obviously affects the leading fund, but also other investors as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when funds are awash with capital, Softbank is probably not the only outlier, and it’s only a matter of time until the hens come home to roost.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It’s generally good advice for companies to only raise the amount of capital for what’s absolutely necessary, and no more. The definition of necessary is context specific, but most often it’s getting through a certain stage or getting ready for a future investment round, IPO, or another milestone.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Notes on Three Big Things</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191005/three-big-things.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Notes on Three Big Things" /><published>2019-10-05T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-05T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191005/three-big-things</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191005/three-big-things.html">&lt;p&gt;Human history seems to be a popular topic to write about these days. Maybe it’s the Sapiens effect, or just the amount of change that’s happening in the world. People want to know what’s next, and are looking to the past for answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morgan Housel just published &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/three-big-things-the-most-important-forces-shaping-the-world/&quot;&gt;Three Big Things&lt;/a&gt;, is one of the best essays I’ve read recently on the topic of human history. It talks about how much of what we experience is a second, third and n-th order effect from some &lt;em&gt;big things&lt;/em&gt; that happened many years ago. Our modern society, for example, has largely been shaped by the events of World War II. Our current norms of personal finance, military strategy, and even civil rights are a result of the war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three other big things that he discusses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A shift in demographics: Modern society is aging, people are living longer, working longer and having fewer kids. Immigrants will make their way to become the majority. These changes will be the most important factors shaping economic output in the upcoming decades. Want to know which economies will fare well? Observe the demographics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The breaking point for wealth inequality: The wealth gap has never been worse, and there’s a cyclical trend at play - the pendulum will start to swing the other way as masses lose trust in economic and political systems. Morgan states, “…power is transitory. It shifts when those who don’t have it get so fed up that they bond together to gain enough influence to take it back. Never underestimate the power of a unified group of powerless people with a shared goal.” There will be a disruption in education, an increase in entrepreneurs, and new systems will be built along the way. It is a time to be optimistic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Realizing the full potential of the internet: Access to information has changed the dynamics of how society works. Whether it’s solving a crime or finding a life partner, we are just scratching the surface of what’s possible when there’s an ever present information layer in our daily lives. While this will do a lot of good - more nuance in our understanding of the world, meritocracy that actually works - there are also some big, unsolved problems, such as the loss of privacy and spreading misinformation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing about these trends is &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt;. That’s the whole point - we are so fascinated by the new that we miss out on the tidal waves that we are already on. This essay brings that into perspective so well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Human history seems to be a popular topic to write about these days. Maybe it’s the Sapiens effect, or just the amount of change that’s happening in the world. People want to know what’s next, and are looking to the past for answers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Systems and Our Destiny</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191004/owning-your-destiny.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Systems and Our Destiny" /><published>2019-10-04T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-04T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191004/owning-your-destiny</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191004/owning-your-destiny.html">&lt;p&gt;There is a time to trust the system and there’s a time to own your destiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system gives us comfort and a &lt;em&gt;sense&lt;/em&gt; of community. Everyone needs some kind of system they trust. We have built incredible political, religous, financial, medical and social systems in the name of progress. And along many dimensions, there &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; been incredible progress. These systems all work together in a complex ways and often seem random when observed on short time scales. Taking a step back we see that most systems follow some kind of cyclical pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not all is well. Our systems have given us convenience, but in some places have removed our individualism. Ironically, they have given us many individual comforts, but made us collectively weaker in some places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, from where I stand, I’m observing a collective questioning of &lt;em&gt;all of our systems&lt;/em&gt;. While the action is not abnormal, the scale and scope of it is. People are losing trust in &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;, even though it’s not immediately obvious. And as a result, we’re seeing new systems being formed, and many of them are focused on helping people &lt;em&gt;own their destiny&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s owning your data, helping people become entrepreneurs, or changing the core units of monetary value - everything is being shaken up. In 10 years, we will look to this brief period as a critical juncture in human history.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There is a time to trust the system and there’s a time to own your destiny.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We Are All Going to Die</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191003/we-are-all-going-to-die.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Are All Going to Die" /><published>2019-10-03T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-03T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191003/we-are-all-going-to-die</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191003/we-are-all-going-to-die.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We are all going to die.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember when Jeremie Saunders said this during his talk at TEDxToronto from a few years ago. At the time, Jeremie was 29 years old, and was three months away from his &lt;em&gt;prescribed&lt;/em&gt; date of death due to Cystic Fibrosis. I can’t nearly do it justice, so here is the talk in full:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UQniNh_6LOY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my favorite passages and quotes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On death and freedom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cystic Fibrosis is one of the best things that have happened to me. No longer does that sentence - “Cystic Fibrosis is a fatal genetic disease” - carry the weight of fear, rejection and anger. Instead it’s become this powerful source of inspiration - &lt;strong&gt;it drives me&lt;/strong&gt;. You see, my unavoidable fate opened up my eyes so wide that it fundamentally changed what it means to live day in and day out, moment to moment. Cystic Fibrosis has essentially given me the impetus to not only &lt;em&gt;accept&lt;/em&gt; my own mortality, but to &lt;em&gt;embrace&lt;/em&gt; my own mortality. With that comes this extraordinary sense of freedom. And I can take that freedom and sprinkle it into my life by living like nothing is unattainable. I can take that big scary concept of death and instead of fear it, Use it, as a tool to motivate myself to live life to the fullest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On living fully, a quote from Mark Twain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The fear of death follows from the fear of life. A man who lives fully is prepared to die at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremie is an incredible human and continues to share his message through his podcast Sickboy, about others who live with chronic or terminal illness, in order to destigmatize illness and build community for those who are sick. Check it out &lt;a href=&quot;http://sickboypodcast.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“We are all going to die.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Antifragile Marketplaces</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191002/antifragile-marketplaces.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antifragile Marketplaces" /><published>2019-10-02T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-02T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191002/antifragile-marketplaces</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191002/antifragile-marketplaces.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a few conversations recently about the concept of anti fragility as it applies to marketplaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antifragility is a concept that any entity actually gets stronger as a result of shock, or damage. It can be applied in business, medicine, systems design and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The antifragile is beyond the resilient or robust. The resilient resists shocks and stays the same; the antifragile gets better and better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting thought exercise is how we can design our marketplaces to be antifragile by nature. The shocks can be the loss of entities on any side. For example, the loss of a supplier, or exodus of customers. Can a marketplace actually get better if a supplier is lost, or goes out of business? In decentralized marketplaces (like Teachable or Shopify), this is precisely what happens. It actually improves the quality bar of overall suppliers on the platform. Exodus of customers is similar in decentralized marketplaces - because the damage is limited to one supplier - and an exodus of customers can be a good sign that supplier shouldn’t be in business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we’re going to see a lot more of these types of decentralized marketplaces in the future and it will be good for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve had a few conversations recently about the concept of anti fragility as it applies to marketplaces.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Experimenting with Comments</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20191001/experimenting-with-comments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experimenting with Comments" /><published>2019-10-01T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-01T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20191001/experimenting-with-comments</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20191001/experimenting-with-comments.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m adding comments to posts on the blog, based on feedback from the micro-community that’s actually reading it (also, thank you, its appreciated more than you know).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;www.disqus.com&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;. It’s been relatively simple so far, thanks to the simple &lt;a href=&quot;https://tarunsachdeva.disqus.com/admin/install/platforms/jekyll/&quot;&gt;install instructions&lt;/a&gt;. Let’s see what happens!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m adding comments to posts on the blog, based on feedback from the micro-community that’s actually reading it (also, thank you, its appreciated more than you know).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Story of Us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190930/the-story-of-us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Story of Us" /><published>2019-09-30T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-09-30T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190930/the-story-of-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190930/the-story-of-us.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://waitbutwhy.com/2019/08/story-intro.html&quot;&gt;The Story of Us&lt;/a&gt; is the latest series from the &lt;a href=&quot;www.waitbutwhy.com&quot;&gt;Wait but Why&lt;/a&gt; blog. It’s an incredibly well told story of human history. I’m still working through it because it’s long but so well told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you come across something that you just &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; you’ll be referring back to often. This feels like one of those gems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Story of Us is the latest series from the Wait but Why blog. It’s an incredibly well told story of human history. I’m still working through it because it’s long but so well told.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Public Market Reckoning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190929/public-market-reckoning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Public Market Reckoning" /><published>2019-09-29T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-09-29T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190929/public-market-reckoning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190929/public-market-reckoning.html">&lt;p&gt;As more tech IPO’s tank, it’s clear that public market investors are not reacting well to the potential of the hottest companies in tech today. They want real margins that can sustain businesses in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred Wilson wrote an excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://avc.com/2019/09/the-great-public-market-reckoning/&quot;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; on this recently, and cited a post I’ve seen referred to often, &lt;a href=&quot;http://abovethecrowd.com/2011/05/24/all-revenue-is-not-created-equal-the-keys-to-the-10x-revenue-club/&quot;&gt;All Revenue is Not Created Equal&lt;/a&gt;. From the post is an excellent description of how valuation should differ based on the margins in a business:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is a huge difference between companies with high gross margins and those with lower gross margins. Using the DCF framework, you cannot generate much cash from a revenue stream that is saddled with large, variable costs. As a result, lower gross margin companies will trade a highly discounted price/revenue multiples. All things being equal, gross margin percentage should have a direct impact on price/revenue multiple, as there will obviously be more gross margin dollars to contribute to free cash flow. Journalists who quickly apply 10x multiples to all private companies should at the very least consider gross margin levels in their analysis.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great post on this topic, that I’ve referred to in the past as well, is Tren Wilson’s post, &lt;a href=&quot;https://25iq.com/2017/02/04/gross-margin-for-fun-and-profit-involves-beer-and-music-streaming/&quot;&gt;Gross Margin for Fun and Profit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As more tech IPO’s tank, it’s clear that public market investors are not reacting well to the potential of the hottest companies in tech today. They want real margins that can sustain businesses in the long run.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day Off</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190928/day-off.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day Off" /><published>2019-09-28T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-09-28T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190928/day-off</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190928/day-off.html">&lt;p&gt;I considered taking a day off writing today. I’m not feeling great, so the last thing I want to do is sit in front of a computer and write because of self-created commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When something is built into a system, it’s absence is felt. I immediately regretted the decision and started this post shortly after. Mostly a placeholder for when the feeling returns - which it undoubtedly will.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I considered taking a day off writing today. I’m not feeling great, so the last thing I want to do is sit in front of a computer and write because of self-created commitment.</summary></entry></feed>