<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-05-21T00:48:48-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How We Got Here</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190518/how-we-got-here.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How We Got Here" /><published>2019-05-18T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-18T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190518/how-we-got-here</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190518/how-we-got-here.html">&lt;p&gt;I was talking to someone recently about Facebook and responsible technology. More specifically, what led to Facebook being weaponized for all sorts of bad things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the specifics of the Facebook situation, I believe it comes down to a few broader factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software is &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; than most technology. We need to recognize software has almost unlimited surface area - which explains how it’s “eating the world”. Software, especially internet software, has almost infinite leverage. A piece of code written in a basement can produce real world outcomes across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there are no real regulations on what is allowed vs not. It was hard to think of the potential of internet software, let alone how to prevent any bad actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, ‘irresponsible’ progress continues to be celebrated. Whether it’s blitzscaling, ignoring local laws, or simply moving fast and breaking things - the technology industry wears irresponsibility as a badge of honor. Without any regulation, decisions are made with a singular lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we’re only starting to see the downsides of not building software responsibly, and there doesn’t seem to be a widely held solution yet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I was talking to someone recently about Facebook and responsible technology. More specifically, what led to Facebook being weaponized for all sorts of bad things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sunshine</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190517/sunshine.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sunshine" /><published>2019-05-17T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-17T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190517/sunshine</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190517/sunshine.html">&lt;p&gt;The weather has finally turned a corner. The sun is shining in Toronto after the longest winter in recent history (this might not be true but it really felt like it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much changes when the sun is out. Optimism abounds. Problems solve themselves. A simple walk can change everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many others, I’m feeling thankful and looking forward to the summer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The weather has finally turned a corner. The sun is shining in Toronto after the longest winter in recent history (this might not be true but it really felt like it).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Complete Guide to Deep Work</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190516/complete-guide-to-deep-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Complete Guide to Deep Work" /><published>2019-05-16T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-16T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190516/complete-guide-to-deep-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190516/complete-guide-to-deep-work.html">&lt;p&gt;The Doist published an excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://doist.com/blog/complete-guide-to-deep-work/&quot;&gt;guide to Deep Work&lt;/a&gt;. It explains the concept and provides some real world strategies to create environments of deep work in your day. They focus on intentionality of the structure. In the section about &lt;a href=&quot;https://doist.com/blog/complete-guide-to-deep-work/#Build_a_Deep_Work_Routine&quot;&gt;how to build a deep work routine&lt;/a&gt;, it mentions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Practicing intention with your time and considering when you’ll fit in periods of focus is an important part of succeeding with a deep work habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four elements of that are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;/strong&gt; - A space that’s conducive to deep work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration&lt;/strong&gt; - A period of time that works for you (starting small then increasing over time as you build your “deep work muscle”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Structure&lt;/strong&gt; - The rules for the session - whether its digital distractions or how you will measure success&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Requirements&lt;/strong&gt; - What’s required to help create the environment - music, food, etc. This will be learned over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the whole guide &lt;a href=&quot;https://doist.com/blog/complete-guide-to-deep-work/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Doist published an excellent guide to Deep Work. It explains the concept and provides some real world strategies to create environments of deep work in your day. They focus on intentionality of the structure. In the section about how to build a deep work routine, it mentions:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finance for Immigrant Families</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190514/finance-for-immigrants.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finance for Immigrant Families" /><published>2019-05-14T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-14T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190514/finance-for-immigrants</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190514/finance-for-immigrants.html">&lt;p&gt;Every society and culture has unique norms and behaviour when it comes to money. When an individual or family migrates to a different country, they bring those mental models with them. This can include, for example, different expectations around loan repayment or how money is pooled in an atomic family. All aspects of personal finance are affected - earning, borrowing, budgeting, saving, investing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowhere is this more pronounced than Canada - a country that is soon to be 50% immigrants in a few years. And yet, the financial products available to most Canadians are not geared  towards these unique needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This becomes extra complicated with newer generations that are raised in Canada but also have cultural and familial obligations to fulfill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think by considering the unique needs of immigrant families and cultures, financial service providers will benefit &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes it’s just a  knowledge asymmetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of those areas where focusing on the minority improves the majority experience with a service.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Every society and culture has unique norms and behaviour when it comes to money. When an individual or family migrates to a different country, they bring those mental models with them. This can include, for example, different expectations around loan repayment or how money is pooled in an atomic family. All aspects of personal finance are affected - earning, borrowing, budgeting, saving, investing, etc.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Global Talent Pool</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190513/a-global-talent-pool.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Global Talent Pool" /><published>2019-05-13T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-13T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190513/a-global-talent-pool</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190513/a-global-talent-pool.html">&lt;p&gt;Restricting talent to a local candidate pool isn’t a sustainable way to build a company. It’s impossible not to look outside a city especially in a competitive hiring environment like today. Remote-only organizations are becoming more common, and companies have to start building cultures where remote workers can thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does it mean to do business in a global talent pool? Some considerations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hiring becomes both easier and more difficult. Finding the best people globally means there’s greater space for meritocracy vs privelege. But, finding the right person is now the proverbial needle in a haystack.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping create team dynamics in a global talent pool is extremely difficult. This is a common challenge with remote work. Individuals can feel isolated and teams may not feel as cohesive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There’s an additional overhead investment to make remote successful. This can include operational issues like knowledge management.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A global talent pool affects all parts of a company system - there’s great potential when it can work, but it won’t come without proactive investment. For many, that may be too tough a hurdle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Restricting talent to a local candidate pool isn’t a sustainable way to build a company. It’s impossible not to look outside a city especially in a competitive hiring environment like today. Remote-only organizations are becoming more common, and companies have to start building cultures where remote workers can thrive.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Toronto’s Moment</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190512/torontos-moment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toronto's Moment" /><published>2019-05-12T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-12T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190512/torontos-moment</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190512/torontos-moment.html">&lt;p&gt;What a shot. Kawhi’s buzzer beater capped off an otherwise ugly game of basketball. The fourth quarter was tense. That last point was the most important bucket in Raptors history. Apparently also the first time that’s ever happened in a Game 7 of an NBA playoffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/K42-D8QPnok&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18 Years ago, Vince Carter was in the same position, against the same team, with the same stakes. He came up short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3emK-oy0LyQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s so much to say about moments like this, but right now it’s just a time to &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; them. The whole city feels dialed into this. Lots of work ahead but that was an incredible victory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What a shot. Kawhi’s buzzer beater capped off an otherwise ugly game of basketball. The fourth quarter was tense. That last point was the most important bucket in Raptors history. Apparently also the first time that’s ever happened in a Game 7 of an NBA playoffs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Negative Second Order Effects</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190511/second-order-effects.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Negative Second Order Effects" /><published>2019-05-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190511/second-order-effects</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190511/second-order-effects.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking recently about second order effects. Specifically about planning for the success of a product or service. We spend a lot of time trying to avoid failure that we don’t think enough about the consequences of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions start with - what happens if a product becomes insanely successful. The predictable positive effects are cool, but not interesting. What is, though, is how might a product be &lt;em&gt;abused&lt;/em&gt;? Knowing that something like this exists - what could a potential bad actor do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook is at the butt of these discussions now. Specifically for not being able to see (or worse yet act on) how bad actors can manipulate a global network. The newsfeed is the product which perpetuates all things good and bad on Facebook, and for many years was treated as the most effective way to harvest global attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it deserves a pause sometimes to sit back and think of the negative effects of what you’re working on, and ask whether a vision is worth achieving at all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been thinking recently about second order effects. Specifically about planning for the success of a product or service. We spend a lot of time trying to avoid failure that we don’t think enough about the consequences of success.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Where User Research Lives</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190510/where-user-research-lives.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where User Research Lives" /><published>2019-05-10T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-10T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190510/where-user-research-lives</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190510/where-user-research-lives.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usability.gov/what-and-why/user-research.html&quot;&gt;User research&lt;/a&gt; is a critical to the design process. But, In an early stage software startup, designers and product managers often share the role. Here’s how I’ve seen the role been split up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A UX designer will split their time in conducting research. Product plays a supporting role, often booking interviews and capturing insights. This can only happen when design has the capacity, AND there’s enough interest from one UX designer to play this role.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Product does most of the research, because design is focused on the critical path of prototyping and building the product. Product steps in because there’s no capacity. This happens quite often, perhaps more so than the first case.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design does attitudinal research (understanding why people would use your product), and product focuses on behavioural research (how people use it - through A/B testing etc). This split can carry through for a long time, even when there are dedicated researchers on the team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, what matters most is that you understand who your users are, the problems they’re having, and how well your solution is helping. The role abstractions are helpful, but every company answers these questions in a different way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">User research is a critical to the design process. But, In an early stage software startup, designers and product managers often share the role. Here’s how I’ve seen the role been split up.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buffet on Amazon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190509/buffet-amazon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buffet on Amazon" /><published>2019-05-09T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-09T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190509/buffet-amazon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190509/buffet-amazon.html">&lt;p&gt;A short post today, Actually - not even. This is an interesting video I saw today - it’s of Warren Buffett talking about investing in Amazon during Berkshire Hathaway’s recent annual meeting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2c2-RANz3gk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A short post today, Actually - not even. This is an interesting video I saw today - it’s of Warren Buffett talking about investing in Amazon during Berkshire Hathaway’s recent annual meeting:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Communities and Investment</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190508/investment-communities.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Communities and Investment" /><published>2019-05-08T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-08T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190508/investment-communities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190508/investment-communities.html">&lt;p&gt;I had a really interesting conversation recently about the dynamics of investor communities. This specifically was about individual investors vs. venture or other institutions, but some principles apply in both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first question was - who are the participants? You would likely have a spectrum of people, ranging from bystanders (not investing, just here to listen) to investors of different types, to the communicators (ones sharing strategy). This isn’t dissimilar to content communities where you have consumers, participators and creators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second question is - what are the needs of each participant? For a bystander, a steady stream of content - information / conversation / editorial. For someone that’s investing - there are some utilitarian needs - the ability to manage and grow their portfolios. For those in a community sharing strategies, perhaps its the ability to participate in conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another major consideration is the privacy and security norms for an investment centric community. Investment and social proof go hand-in-hand, but people still need full agency over information sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robinhood, StockTwits, SeekingAlpha are all good examples of these types of communities - each catering to a different participant and need.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I had a really interesting conversation recently about the dynamics of investor communities. This specifically was about individual investors vs. venture or other institutions, but some principles apply in both.</summary></entry></feed>