<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-07T11:07:19-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Apple Vision Pro</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20230606/apple-vision-pro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apple Vision Pro" /><published>2023-06-06T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-06-06T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20230606/apple-vision-pro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20230606/apple-vision-pro.html"><![CDATA[<p>Cool to see Apple doing what they do best. Some very disconnected thoughts on the VisionPro:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Eye tracking + pinch interaction sounds absolutely wild. Look at an app, pinch to select👌🏽. Very reminiscent of how iPhone touchscreen was 10x better than others.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Feels like a new design space for accessibility. Can even imagine apps to help those with nervous system disorders (e.g. stroke victims) recover certain coordination functions, once more apps become a thing.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Might not be intentional but enabling 2D apps in 3D is a great way to onboard existing devs.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Naming it Vision Pro (vs. just Vision) is in line with a strong tradition of consumer vs. pro products. Also makes sense why Productivity is the leading message Vision Pro (my guess is “Vision” will focus on entertainment + “connection” features.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Not hard to imagine an entire media ecosystem available “Only on Apple Vision”. Strong Apple TV+ play here too, possibly. Apple plays long games so this is probably many years out.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Lots more cool stuff here - <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/">https://developer.apple.com/videos/</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cool to see Apple doing what they do best. Some very disconnected thoughts on the VisionPro:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Being Back, and Fluid Lives</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20210801/fluid-lives.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Being Back, and Fluid Lives" /><published>2021-08-01T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-08-01T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20210801/fluid-lives</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20210801/fluid-lives.html"><![CDATA[<p>The last published post to this blog was in August 2020. Before then, I was writing daily for almost two years. The habit has to be rebuilt, starting with this short post.</p>

<p>The world is a different place. COVID is relentless and the vaccines are a miracle. Feels like everyone’s lost someone to this virus. And yet, optimism is abundant. Especially if you’re building software.</p>

<p>The relationships we’re building at ‘work’ and ‘school’ are happening in software first, and in real life second (or not at all). It’s a good time to help humans to do more on the internet, and there’s so much to explore.</p>

<p>And because of this change, the day is regimented by our identity, not a daily commute to an office. Life just feels more <strong>fluid</strong>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The last published post to this blog was in August 2020. Before then, I was writing daily for almost two years. The habit has to be rebuilt, starting with this short post.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Triggering ‘Flow’ State</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200817/flow-state.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Triggering ‘Flow’ State" /><published>2020-08-17T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-17T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200817/flow-state</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200817/flow-state.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the first post in months. I’m working on a bigger essay right now, but I’ve missed publishing on this space. This is a short post is about how to trigger Flow state, and is a summary of <a href="https://medium.com/personal-growth-lab/how-to-reach-flow-state-using-10-flow-state-triggers-473aa28dc3e5">this article</a> by Jari Roomer. This is especially relevant now, when people are working and learning in enviroments not initially created for productivity.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)">Flow</a> is a state of complete immersion in whatever activity someone is doing; often signalled by losing complete track of time. You know when it happens, but it <em>can</em> be triggered. This article provides ten ways that contribute to flow state.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Eliminate all <em>external</em> distractions: put your phone away, turn off notifications.</li>
  <li>Eliminate internal distractions. This is tougher but meditation and journalling help to clear the mind. Most imporantly, don’t try to enter flow state when stressed.</li>
  <li>Work at your Biological Peak Time (BPT). Don’t fight it if you naturally get fatigued at a certain time of day.</li>
  <li>Listen to the right kind of music. Repetitive, non-vocal music, that stretches for an extended period of time.</li>
  <li>Work on one very specific task. Entering flow state with a list of things to do won’t work. Pick a task.</li>
  <li>The task must be challenging enough, but not TOO challenging. If it’s too difficult, it will create stress and will be difficult to reach flow (see #2)</li>
  <li>Have a clear outcome or goal. When you don’t know what you’re working towards, you don’t know when to finish, and procrastination loves it when this lack of clarity exists - it will push you towards quitting earlier.</li>
  <li>Strategically consume caffeine. 200mg per day max (each cup is about 96mg). 400mg creates anxiety.</li>
  <li>Stay hydrated. Not surprising but lack of hydration leads to a distracted state of mind.</li>
  <li>Create a mental cue. A special sentence, action that you repeat <em>every</em> time you want to enter flow state.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the first post in months. I’m working on a bigger essay right now, but I’ve missed publishing on this space. This is a short post is about how to trigger Flow state, and is a summary of this article by Jari Roomer. This is especially relevant now, when people are working and learning in enviroments not initially created for productivity.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The New Course, or The Atomic Unit of Digital Schools</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200608/the-new-course.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The New Course, or The Atomic Unit of Digital Schools" /><published>2020-06-08T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-08T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200608/the-new-course</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200608/the-new-course.html"><![CDATA[<p>The first generation of online courses focused on the structured delivery of [mostly] video content, sometimes with accompanying materials.</p>

<p>Today, the structure of online courses is so much more, and some of the more successful ones I’ve seen have common elements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>They all come with a supportive community of peers learning the same thing. Whether it’s a Slack group or Discourse forum, what you’re learning is just as important as <em>who you’re learning with</em>.</li>
  <li>They center around the instructor first, not the content. Twitter is an incredible learning platform because the act of Following is an indication of interest. Some people join courses today because the relationship with the course content starts with their connection with the instructor. Traditionally, you choose a course topic and then get introduced to the instructor.</li>
  <li>They encourage public accountability. The act of creating things in public (through writing and other creative fields) creates a natural skin-in-the-game.</li>
  <li>Built in status through exclusivity. Being a part of a (sometimes) restricted community creates a feeling of exclusivity. Completing the course and being a part of the alumni network carries social status too, just in the same way graduating from a university would.</li>
</ul>

<p>In essence, moving to a default digital space in education means we’re seeing a lot of the shared support structures around courses that a “school” would provide be available to every course itself. It’s an interesting shift.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The first generation of online courses focused on the structured delivery of [mostly] video content, sometimes with accompanying materials.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Twitter and Passive Learning (Updated)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200527/twitter-learning-platform.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Twitter and Passive Learning (Updated)" /><published>2020-05-27T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-27T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200527/twitter-learning-platform</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200527/twitter-learning-platform.html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I had a conversation with a friend about new tools enabling ‘passive learning’ - non-traditional platforms that facilitate learning through your existing media diet. For example, <a href="http://www.arist.co">Arist</a>, which delivers learning content through regular text messages. Others optimize for moments of heightened curiosity in any subject, instead of a fixed curriculum based progression. Browser extensions like <a href="http://www.usefluent.co">UseFluent</a>, and <a href="http://www.jointoucan.com">Toucan</a> are examples of this. Each platform affordance creates for different modes of storytelling and recall.</p>

<p>And while these platforms are really interesting, Twitter is the biggest passive learning platform in the world.</p>

<p>It creates a new learning modality not possible before - the consistent exposure to discussions amongst experts and those learning from experts. Anytime I’m interested in a topic, following Twitter users from that subcommunity or topic is a great way to immerse myself.</p>

<p>It also creates a natural graduation from passive to active learning through the forms of interaction - reading tweets, participating in conversations, creating new tweets about the topic. The exercise of doing everything in public creates a natural skin in the game for learning.</p>

<p>Although it’s primarily a social platform (can be performative, not always a safe space) - it’s ability to create a natural learning experiences is pretty interesting.</p>

<p>UPDATE: A <a href="https://twitter.com/naval/status/1265875306901934081">tweet from Naval</a> today reminded me of how lists can be used to shape Twitter into a learning platform vs. a social platform. You can create lists around experts in your areas of interest - and Twitter allows you (on mobile) to add them as additional tabs besides your primary feed. Really cool and underused capability.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Yesterday I had a conversation with a friend about new tools enabling ‘passive learning’ - non-traditional platforms that facilitate learning through your existing media diet. For example, Arist, which delivers learning content through regular text messages. Others optimize for moments of heightened curiosity in any subject, instead of a fixed curriculum based progression. Browser extensions like UseFluent, and Toucan are examples of this. Each platform affordance creates for different modes of storytelling and recall.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How it Feels</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200526/how-it-feels.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How it Feels" /><published>2020-05-26T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-26T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200526/how-it-feels</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200526/how-it-feels.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been too long since I’ve posted. There are entire <em>categories</em> of uncertainty I’m planning for in other parts of life. I’ve also been working on a longer essay on the rapid digitization of school and work. I’ve missed this space, as my days feel incomplete without some kind of creative output.</p>

<p>Felt apt to start again by chronicling how it all feels. Since my last post, the virus spread is continuing. Many countries have managed to flatten the curve and places like Singapore have even stopped a second outbreak. But it continues is some of the larget countries. China is going back into lockdown. Brazil’s leadership is completely ignoring the virus and will quickly take over the US in cases. The US just crossed 100,000 deaths, more than the lives lost in Vietnam. India’s cases are rising, despite strict lockdowns and contact tracing infrastructure.</p>

<p>So, this isn’t over. Not even close.</p>

<p>We are back in Canada after a few months in New York, putting that life adventure on pause. Healthy, content, and planning for the future.</p>

<p>My daily routine has evolved. I’m up earlier, working out and meditating more. But the workday is intense. I’ve also noticed people are becoming very, very tired of this shit. The burden on everyone is huge and parents have a unique set of challenges. Most schools have cancelled the school year. Knowledge workers around the world are becoming accustomed to a digital by default workday. Childcare is becoming a real issue for families that are balancing it all.</p>

<p>Over and above anything else I’m thinking of the opportunities around us. Moving our spaces of learning and working into a digital space <em>by default</em> is probably the biggest societal change I might ever witness.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s been too long since I’ve posted. There are entire categories of uncertainty I’m planning for in other parts of life. I’ve also been working on a longer essay on the rapid digitization of school and work. I’ve missed this space, as my days feel incomplete without some kind of creative output.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Principles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200518/first-principles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Principles" /><published>2020-05-18T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-18T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200518/first-principles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200518/first-principles.html"><![CDATA[<p>A common refrain when building new products is to build painkillers, not vitamins. It’s a way of saying - build products that solve a real problem for users. One they are familiar with, and hate dealing with.</p>

<p>Sometimes this is obvious - they will tell you their pain, and it will be obvious. Most times it’s not and takes investigation - through conversation, and the learning from building products that <em>don’t</em> work quite as well.</p>

<p>Innovating from first principles is an exercise in serving a customer need, with the best tools available to you at the time. This cycle takes many years and many companies die in the effort. Some can do it once, but very few can do it again and again.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A common refrain when building new products is to build painkillers, not vitamins. It’s a way of saying - build products that solve a real problem for users. One they are familiar with, and hate dealing with.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A New System (Updated)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200516/new-system.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A New System (Updated)" /><published>2020-05-16T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-16T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200516/new-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200516/new-system.html"><![CDATA[<p>The world is at home and facing the reality that the school year is going to end without students returning to classrooms. Despite this, learning hasn’t stopped. Quite the opposite. And this new reality is revealing cracks in our existing education system.</p>

<p>Some thoughts on what’s going on and predictions on what might happen, across different stages…</p>

<ul>
  <li>K-12 systems will like return in a physical form, driven by the need for a safe haven for children while parents are working. Public K-12 is government funded, so the system will only meaningfully change if that investment can respond to the needs of students. We will likely see a rise in homeschooling and privatized education at lower costs, to make up for the inadequate public schooling system.</li>
  <li>For systems of higher education, there will be a few key changes. First, the move to digital delivery will bring down the price of getting a ‘premium’ education. That’s only the first of many other n-th order effects here. Second, we’ll see more innovation in schools providing certainty of a successful career (most schools have been training people for the wrong thing). Everything from financing (ISA’s) to companies offering education credits as part of work. This will see the notion of school and working becoming interleaved.</li>
  <li>We’ll see a rise in platforms targeted at self directed learners - students that want to define their own curiculum and learn at their own pace. “K-12” and “higher education” are simply labels and remnants of the past system.</li>
  <li>For those already in the workforce, there will be a massive need on upskilling and reskilling to participate in the knowledge economy. For others, it’s a time to take back control, and start building their own communities and businesses online.</li>
  <li>In a knowledge economy, long term capital success is directly tied to the ability for companies to build intellectual moats. The best companies are learning organizations and feel like learning communities. The tools that help us in this process will go beyond communication - they will help us organize our thoughts, compound our collective knowledge and help us in the journey of learning.</li>
</ul>

<p>Clearly there is a new system being created, and more change is quickly approaching.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The world is at home and facing the reality that the school year is going to end without students returning to classrooms. Despite this, learning hasn’t stopped. Quite the opposite. And this new reality is revealing cracks in our existing education system.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Outlining an Essay On Learning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200427/an-essay-about-education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Outlining an Essay On Learning" /><published>2020-04-27T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-27T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200427/an-essay-about-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200427/an-essay-about-education.html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is highly unstructured. It is a set of questions and thoughts for a broader essay on how broader technological advancement plays out in education and work.</p>

<ul>
  <li>To understand the future we should look into the past. How did the current K-12 and college come to be? What was the innovation that drove the creation of these institutions? What can we learn from those forces, if anything. Detail some of the forces of government, religion and industry have played defining roles in the formation and purpose of some of the world’s ‘top’ schools.</li>
  <li>Let’s dive into the relationship between industry and education. How have they played a role in the past, and how do these forces drive each other. Look into the major revolutions - agricultural, industrial and information.</li>
  <li>In the knowledge economy, education and work are tied together much more closely than prior revolutions. In the past - education was theory and work was practical. Now, those worlds are intertwined. Learning never stops, and the application is fundamental to the learning experience. These facts reinforce the connection:
    <ul>
      <li>Companies are playing increasing roles in supporting the student journey (from the rise in co-operative education, ISA’s, to company sponsored education). Examples of this are Lambda, Holberton, Springboard.</li>
      <li>Companies are learning machines that produce capital and knowledge. They behave like learning communities. In the past, the knowledge of company operation could be managed by a small group of executives. Now, there is so much knowledge being created at all levels that acting on business knowledge is required at all levels.</li>
      <li>The tools of learning are shared with the tools of working. What we do to compound information, individually and in teams, play roles in achieving student outcomes.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>As education and work become more intertwined, credentialism doesn’t just belong to the education sector. A 5 year stint at Google may be more respected and lead to better economic outcomes than a Harvard degree. But it goes beyond that. We have to recognize that learning is a lifelong journey and people acquire skills throughout their life - and our credential system looks less like a diploma mounted on a wall. It looks a set of badges representing skills both learned and applied. There is an interesting opportunity to turn every college degree into a set of badges, and solve the global credentialling crisis where credit isn’t recognized across borders.</li>
  <li>We are seeing a micro-ization of work and education. The rise of the gig economy is allowing people to diversify their income streams. Self directed workers, the micro-entrepreneurs. The availability of online resources making self directed learning impossibly easy. Instead of spending years at school and then years at work, people have started time dividing their careers into smaller chunks. 8 years seems like a lifetime at a company.</li>
  <li>This is not a zero sum game - the existing education system will always have a role to play, but the rise of a new system will allow for self directed learners and workers. This brings opportunity to support this infrastructure as well.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post is highly unstructured. It is a set of questions and thoughts for a broader essay on how broader technological advancement plays out in education and work.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Principles and EdTech</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20200420/first-principles-education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Principles and EdTech" /><published>2020-04-20T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-20T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20200420/first-principles-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20200420/first-principles-education.html"><![CDATA[<p>The education software industry today can roughly be divided into two camps:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Software that enables the delivery of educational material over the internet (e.g. Coursera, Skillshare).</li>
  <li>Software that enables the operation of schools and universities (e.g. Tophat).</li>
</ol>

<p>Put even more critically, both camps fall into the category of software that recreates in-person educational experiences. Software is a perfect innovation space for rapid experimentation, and it has been underleveraged for education.</p>

<p>I’m interested in what happens when we approach this problem from first principles - breaking things down to their essential truths and building upwards. In this case, the essential truths are students desire to learn and achieve a specific outcome.</p>

<p>Everything else can and probably should change.</p>

<p>I think we still have a ways to go to create <em>software native</em> educational experiences - ones have no physical equivalents at all and simply cannot exist without software itself.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The education software industry today can roughly be divided into two camps:]]></summary></entry></feed>