<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-14T21:51:23-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tarun Sachdeva</title><subtitle>Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Solar</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190712/solar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Solar" /><published>2019-07-12T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-12T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190712/solar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190712/solar.html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2019/07/giant-batteries-and-cheap-solar-power-are-shoving-fossil-fuels-grid&quot;&gt;Science Mag&lt;/a&gt; on the progress of solar technology:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This month, officials in Los Angeles, California, are expected to approve a deal that would make solar power cheaper than ever while also addressing its chief flaw: It works only when the sun shines. The deal calls for a huge solar farm backed up by one of the world’s largest batteries. It would provide 7% of the city’s electricity beginning in 2023 at a cost of 1.997 cents per kilowatt hour (kWh) for the solar power and 1.3 cents per kWh for the battery. That’s cheaper than any power generated with fossil fuel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the power of technology cost curves. Incremental improvements slowly drive down costs of new technology - often while incumbents write off new entrants as not being good/fast/cheap enough. Soon after better tech becomes &lt;em&gt;cheaper&lt;/em&gt; than the alternative, change happens fast and incumbents get displaced.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">From Science Mag on the progress of solar technology:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No Coders</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190711/nocoders.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Coders" /><published>2019-07-11T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-11T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190711/nocoders</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190711/nocoders.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nocode.tech/&quot;&gt;‘No Code’&lt;/a&gt; is a movement that enables non-technical entrepreneurs to create real, working digital products. Tools to do this include Shopify, Webflow, Carrd, Glitch and many others. A great starting point for understanding the movement is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.makerpad.co/&quot;&gt;Makerpad&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As web and mobile products become easier to build, we’re about to see a massive increase in the top of the funnel for new products being created. This inflection means more innovate products in market, but a proportional increase in competition. No code tools are also helping designers and developers collaborate and share common mental models and tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an exciting wave of growth that can be as powerful as the appstores themselves and will likely create many more digital entrepreneurs along the way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">‘No Code’ is a movement that enables non-technical entrepreneurs to create real, working digital products. Tools to do this include Shopify, Webflow, Carrd, Glitch and many others. A great starting point for understanding the movement is Makerpad.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Shape Up</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190710/shape-up.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shape Up" /><published>2019-07-10T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-10T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190710/shape-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190710/shape-up.html">&lt;p&gt;Another book from the crew at Basecamp - this one called &lt;a href=&quot;https://basecamp.com/shapeup/&quot;&gt;Shape Up&lt;/a&gt;, and details their development process with illustrations. They introduced some concepts in &lt;a href=&quot;https://basecamp.com/books/calm&quot;&gt;It doesn’t have to be crazy at work&lt;/a&gt;, especially that of the 6-week project limit. I would call this the most &lt;em&gt;Rails&lt;/em&gt; approach to project management - eschewing complexity and reinforcing simple conventions in process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a quick and impactful read.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Another book from the crew at Basecamp - this one called Shape Up, and details their development process with illustrations. They introduced some concepts in It doesn’t have to be crazy at work, especially that of the 6-week project limit. I would call this the most Rails approach to project management - eschewing complexity and reinforcing simple conventions in process.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Maintaining Equilibrium during Marketplace Development</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190710/maintaining-equilibrium-marketplace-development.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Maintaining Equilibrium during Marketplace Development" /><published>2019-07-10T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-10T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190710/maintaining-equilibrium-marketplace-development</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190710/maintaining-equilibrium-marketplace-development.html">&lt;p&gt;Some thoughts on how systems thinking can be applied to marketplace development in early stages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A marketplace is a system, and building one from scratch requires a keen sense of equilibrium on all sides. If you have too much supply, your early suppliers will leave for lack of opportunity. If demand outstrips supply, you will be left with unhappy customers (first impressions are difficult to change, although not impossible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important aspect is timing to make adjustments. In the early stage, you have to constantly tune and tweak your marketplace so that everyone is happy - quickly osscilating to resolve issues to help suppliers be successful and make customers happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sounds obvious but every initiative (project, feature, task) should have direct impact on your current marketplace. Avoid building something that will only have &lt;em&gt;second order impact&lt;/em&gt; without any meaningful changes to the &lt;em&gt;current market&lt;/em&gt;. Ask yourself - if this was built tomorrow, would our marketplace immediately change? If the answer is no, reconsider the level of investment. We buy the luxury of time when things are more established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are ofcourse many ways of maintaining equilibrium early. The most sustainable is to onboard early users slowly so that maintaining equilibrium is never a huge issue. Making sure you have a good feedback channel is critical during this time too. The other approach is to ensure your ability to iterate on changes is rapid enough to address any rising issues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Some thoughts on how systems thinking can be applied to marketplace development in early stages:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Crypto Business Models and Libra</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190708/crypto-business-models.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crypto Business Models and Libra" /><published>2019-07-08T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-08T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190708/crypto-business-models</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190708/crypto-business-models.html">&lt;p&gt;Fred Wilson recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://avc.com/2019/07/business-model-innovation/&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about how Crypto’s promise is not just in the technical but the business model innovation that comes alongside it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reminded me of the world of gaming and virtual currencies. In-app purchases and subscriptions are often mapped to coins, passes, candy and other currencies that can be redeemed in an app. Once they have been translated into these virtual currencies, we can similarly innovate on different business models that might work best in a specific scenario. For example, we can use the subscription API to give users coins every month (instead of simple access), and then use those coins to purchase content or pay other users in an app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This full capability (especially that to pay users with coins) isn’t yet possible with the In-app purchase API’s provided by Apple and Google. But ultimately, the behaviours that have a lot of traction will then get adopted into those platform API’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of Facebook - the world’s largest social network - as a game, the Libra cryptocurrency is their virtual good. Difference being that they’re not the only ones controlling it. It has value pegged to real currency, can be used to trade goods and services, and can be traded in for other currencies on different exchanges. More so, when another app uses Libra, it creates network effect for that currency and the utility value increases for users of Libra. Already, Uber, Ebay, Lyft, Spotify and others have joined. More mature games have multiple currencies running in parallel, much in the same way there are hundreds of possible cryptocurrencies to purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lot’s of hurdles still to cross, but it’s an incredibly interesting time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Fred Wilson recently wrote about how Crypto’s promise is not just in the technical but the business model innovation that comes alongside it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Software is Modelling the World</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190707/software-is-modeling-the-world.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Software is Modelling the World" /><published>2019-07-07T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-07T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190707/software-is-modeling-the-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190707/software-is-modeling-the-world.html">&lt;p&gt;I don’t like to think of software as &lt;em&gt;eating&lt;/em&gt; the world; rather just &lt;em&gt;modelling&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s modelling our personalities and relationships.
It’s modelling how we tell stories through words, music, and video and games. 
It’s modelling our money and how we interact with it.
It’s modelling how we trust and look for social proof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now wear our software, live, breathe and sleep in it. We can almost touch it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But software is imperfect: the map is not the territory. Models often over simplify and leave out the niches and edge cases, often excluding people without intending. It’s the job of the designers and builders to make sure that doesn’t happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A model is a simulation, and through that simulation we can create exponential outcomes. When those stay in the software space, they seem harmless. But when you reach a certain scale, that simulation can have unintended real-world effects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I don’t like to think of software as eating the world; rather just modelling it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Kawhi</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190706/kawhi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Kawhi" /><published>2019-07-06T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-06T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190706/kawhi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190706/kawhi.html">&lt;p&gt;What a difference a day makes. Just like that, Kawhi is no longer a Raptor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His sober get-it-done demeanor was the most &lt;em&gt;Canadian&lt;/em&gt; way to win a championship. It’s appropriate that Toronto is having the most &lt;em&gt;Canadian&lt;/em&gt; possible response: we’re upset, but we’re not angry. He wanted to go home. You can’t be mad at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether or not the backroom stories are true, it really tells of the power of the right phone call. In this case, it was Kawhi’s to Durant and then Paul George.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asking for what you want is an underappreciated skill in life and business. What sets apart the winners is often they’re just a bit more clear about what they want, and aren’t afraid to ask for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What a difference a day makes. Just like that, Kawhi is no longer a Raptor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Microlearning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190704/microlearning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Microlearning" /><published>2019-07-04T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-04T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190704/microlearning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190704/microlearning.html">&lt;p&gt;Learning happens in small increments - bits of knowledge that collectively stitch together to form mental models of understanding. So it’s only natural that online learning services minify and break up content into consumable chunks. Mobile amplifies this - shorter attention spans come with being able to consume any content on the go - we fit those moments into the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept can be extended pretty far - potentially doing away with the concept of fixed courses altogether to a more fluid learning structure. Using Microlearning structures we can eventually unbundle a college degree - although more likely is that it will  helps for the construction of more specialized degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software for learning will continue to become more adaptive to how humans learn - and microlearning is a big part of that trend for educationalists tech.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Learning happens in small increments - bits of knowledge that collectively stitch together to form mental models of understanding. So it’s only natural that online learning services minify and break up content into consumable chunks. Mobile amplifies this - shorter attention spans come with being able to consume any content on the go - we fit those moments into the day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kawhi Watch</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190703/kawhiwatch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kawhi Watch" /><published>2019-07-03T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-03T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190703/kawhiwatch</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190703/kawhiwatch.html">&lt;p&gt;The world was on #KawhiWatch today. I was getting multiple messages full of rumours and hearsay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s pretty insane to see this happening. No athlete in recent memory has gotten this type of attention. It’s incredible to be a witness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice should be  clear. Toronto objectively is a better city for Kawhi. The  chance to defend the championship, a highly competent organization at all level, and cap space to offer upto a 5 year max. That said, we probably need to chill a little bit :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The world was on #KawhiWatch today. I was getting multiple messages full of rumours and hearsay.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Boring Technology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20190702/boring-technology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boring Technology" /><published>2019-07-02T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-02T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20190702/boring-technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20190702/boring-technology.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked in tech long enough to see a familiar game play out many times: engineers want to use the latest and greatest technology, often overlooking the maintenance cost of new tech. At the same time, they look down on ‘old technology’ as inferior, when the opposite is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan McKinley has a great presentation on this topic aptly titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://boringtechnology.club/&quot;&gt;Boring Technology&lt;/a&gt;. Check it out; its a great read and nails the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve worked in tech long enough to see a familiar game play out many times: engineers want to use the latest and greatest technology, often overlooking the maintenance cost of new tech. At the same time, they look down on ‘old technology’ as inferior, when the opposite is true.</summary></entry></feed>